<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/css" href="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/code/pfs.css"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The Presbyterians loyalty and zeal for religion demonstrated in a letter by way of reply to a late fanatical pamphlet intituled The Knave uncloak'd, or, The Jesuit in its colours : shewing how industriously our modern rumpers endeavor ... to promote the good old cause : also proving Presbyterians to be schismaticks and bishops jure divino superior to presbyters : together with a serious and seasonable advertisement to all true and loyal Protestants.</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 237KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 39 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2016-02">2016-02 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">B28316</idno><idno type="EEBO-CITATION">10599453</idno>
  <idno type="VID">204734</idno>
  <idno type="EEBO-PROQUEST">2240868744</idno>
  
            <idno type="STC">Wing P3228</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">10599453</idno>
            <availability><p>This keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above is co-owned by the
    institutions providing financial support to the Early English Books Online Text Creation
    Partnership. This text is available for reuse, according to the terms of <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/"> Creative Commons 0 1.0 Universal
    licence</ref>. The text can be copied, modified, distributed and performed, even for commercial
    purposes, all without asking permission.</p></availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt><relatedItem type="facs" target="https://data.historicaltexts.jisc.ac.uk/view?pubId=eebo-e"/>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. B28316)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 204734)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 1408:33)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The Presbyterians loyalty and zeal for religion demonstrated in a letter by way of reply to a late fanatical pamphlet intituled The Knave uncloak'd, or, The Jesuit in its colours : shewing how industriously our modern rumpers endeavor ... to promote the good old cause : also proving Presbyterians to be schismaticks and bishops jure divino superior to presbyters : together with a serious and seasonable advertisement to all true and loyal Protestants.</title>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>57 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>s.n.],</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>[London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1680.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Page 10 faded with loss of print.  Beginning to page 17 from defective Edinburgh University Library copy spliced at end.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the Harvard University Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,363 texts created during Phase 1 of the project have been released into the public domain as of 1 January 2015. Anyone can now take and use these texts for their own purposes, but we respectfully request that due credit and attribution is given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Full documentation of the original data capture process is available from the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.
   All versions of the texts are now archived and freely available for download. See <ref target="https://textcreationpartnership.org/faq/#faq05">the TCP Download FAQ</ref>
   for detailed information. The TEI P5 versions are also freely available from the <ref target="https://github.com/textcreationpartnership">TCP Github repository</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp" matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)" replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char" matchPattern="(.+)" replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term type="topical_term">Presbyterianism --  Controversial literature --  Anglican authors.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2014-06 </date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images </change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-07 </date>
            <label>Renee Mayes </label>Sampled and proofread </change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-07 </date>
            <label>Renee Mayes</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited </change>
         <change>
            <date>2015-03 </date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion </change>
      <change><date>2021-05 </date><label>lb</label>TEI P5 conversion </change></revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:204734:1"/>
            <p>THE <hi>Presbyterians Loyalty,</hi> AND ZEAL for RELIGION, Briefly Demonstrated: In a LETTER, By way of Reply to a late Fanatical Pamphlet, Intituled, <hi>The Knave Uncloak'd;</hi> or, <hi>The Jesuit in its Colours.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Shewing how industriously our Modern <hi>Rumpers</hi> endeavour, under the name of <hi>Protestants,</hi> to promote the <hi>Good Old Cause.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Also proving <hi>Presbyterians</hi> to be <hi>Schismaticks,</hi> and <hi>Bishops Jure Divino</hi> superior to <hi>Presbyters.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Together with a serious and seasonable Advertisement to all True and Loyal <hi>Protestants.</hi>
            </p>
            <q>
               <p>There is a Generation that are pure in their own thoughts, and yet are not washed from their filthiness. <bibl>
                     <hi>Prov. 30.12.</hi>
                  </bibl>
               </p>
               <p>Presumptuous they are, self-willed, they are not afraid to speak evil of dignities. <bibl>
                     <hi>2 Pet. 2.10.</hi>
                  </bibl>
               </p>
               <p>Men that introduce prophaneness, are cloak'd over with a name of imaginary Religion. <bibl>
                     <hi>Prosper. lib.</hi> 2. <hi>de contemptu vitae, cap.</hi> 4.</bibl>
               </p>
            </q>
            <p>Printed in the Year 1680.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:204734:2"/>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:204734:2"/>
            <head>THE <hi>Presbyterians Loyalty</hi> AND ZEAL for RELIGION Demonstrated, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
            </head>
            <div type="section">
               <opener>
                  <salute>Good Sir Presbyter,</salute>
               </opener>
               <p>YOur Letter I received, and have hitherto deferr'd to send you a reply, as well because I could not certainly tell where to direct it, as also because I thought it altogether needless to spend any time in answering, such frivolous <hi>impertinencies,</hi> and idle <hi>whimseys;</hi> yet forasmuch as the Wise-man adviseth us <hi>to answer the fool according to his folly, lest he be wise in his own con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceit, Prov.</hi> 26.5. I concluded at last to send you these ensuing Lines as a <hi>New-years-Gift,</hi> and direct them to your <hi>Worship</hi> at <hi>Billingsgate,</hi> where I judge by your <hi>dexterity</hi> in scolding and railing <hi>Rhetorick</hi> you are a <hi>Master of Art,</hi> if not <hi>Chair-man</hi> to that quick-tongu'd and unsocia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble Society.</p>
               <p>Truly, to be railed at by the <hi>Presbyterians,</hi> is so far from giving me the least distaste, that I count it the greatest honour they can place upon me, it being now the common Character of a faithful <hi>Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>triot,</hi> and true <hi>Loyalist:</hi> And had I been in the least prais'd by such factious Spirits, I would undoubtedly suspect my own actions, and say with <hi>Socrates, What evil have I done, that these</hi> Antimonarchical Le<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vellers <hi>should commend me?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>'Tis true, you pretend to be a Son of the <hi>Church</hi> of <hi>England,</hi> and to colour your <hi>knavery,</hi> you most unfortunately make a Cloak of that holy <hi>Church,</hi> whose candour and sincerity is so <hi>transparent,</hi> that your
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:204734:3"/>pernicious designs are plainly seen through it, to the utter confusion of such <hi>hypocritical dissemblers.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>But since the world knows, a <hi>Protestant Jesuit</hi> can equivocate as well as the <hi>Puritan Papist,</hi> I think we have reason enough to believe, that by the <hi>Church</hi> of <hi>England</hi> you mean nothing else but your own <hi>Presbyterian Synagogue,</hi> which alone you esteem the true <hi>Church</hi> of <hi>Christ;</hi> for it is evident, a Son of that <hi>Church,</hi> which is now through God's Providence established among us by the Laws of the Land, you cannot pretend to be, unless such a Son as <hi>Nero</hi> was to <hi>Agrippina,</hi> who scrupled not to procure the death of his unfortunate <hi>Mother,</hi> to satisfie his own monstrous voluptuousness.</p>
               <p>You undertake to roll <hi>Sysiphus</hi> his Stone, or wash a <hi>Gypsie,</hi> to vin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicate the <hi>Presbyterians,</hi> and make us believe they are <hi>harmless Lambs,</hi> though all true Protestants hold them for <hi>ravenous Wolves,</hi> and now apprehend them most dangerous both to <hi>Church</hi> and <hi>State:</hi> yet so pitiful a defence you make in their behalf, that I cannot tell whether the <hi>Church</hi> of <hi>England</hi> has greater reason to detest your <hi>Schismatical</hi> intention, than your own <hi>Synagogue</hi> to curse your <hi>ill-manag'd</hi> under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taking; for since, as the Poet well observed,
<q>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Causa patrocinio non bona pejor erit.</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>What shall become of an ill Cause very ill defended?</l>
                  </q>
               </p>
               <p>But however you fail in the rest, you are sure not to forget the old contrivances of your Predecessors, the <hi>Parliamentarion Rebels,</hi> and their worthy Progenitors, in charging all those with <hi>Popery,</hi> that pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sum'd to make the least opposition against their bloody <hi>Zeal</hi> for the <hi>Genevesion</hi> Reformation: Which intrigue, as it prov'd most successful to the <hi>treacherous Rumpers,</hi> so it has been no less destructive and per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nicious to the <hi>Church of England,</hi> it being one of the chiefest <hi>stratagems,</hi> whereby the Rebels brought our <hi>Royal Martyr</hi> and his trustiest Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sters into an odium with the blinded Rabble.</p>
               <p>I could instance here several passages of this <hi>Presbyterian policy,</hi> but I shall content my self with two or three, and will begin with one <hi>re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>markable</hi> example, which was a <hi>praeludium</hi> to all our former distra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctions, as their present proceedings, if not timely prevented, do infal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>libly <hi>prognosticate</hi> the like revolutions to be near at hand. In the year 1632. King <hi>Charles</hi> the First, of glorious memory, took a journey into <hi>Scotland,</hi> and thought by degrees to settle there the <hi>English Liturgy,</hi> with its usual Ceremonies; which the <hi>Ring-leaders</hi> of the <hi>Presbyterian Faction</hi> in that <hi>Kingdom</hi> understanding, not onely exclaimed against
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:204734:3"/>our <hi>Liturgy</hi> as <hi>erroneous</hi> and <hi>superstitious,</hi> but also doubted not to tra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duce his Majesty for very strong inclinations to the <hi>Religion</hi> of the <hi>Church</hi> of <hi>Rome.</hi> By which contrivance they quickly possess'd the <hi>short-sighted Rabble</hi> with such tears and jealousies, as afterwards broke out into a flame of open <hi>Rebellion,</hi> to the utter ruine and destruction both of <hi>King</hi> and <hi>Countrey.</hi> See <hi>Bakers Chronicle, Edit. anno</hi> 1674. <hi>page</hi> 473.</p>
               <p>And so effectual a contrivance was this piece of policy counted by our brave <hi>Machiavilians,</hi> that in <hi>England</hi> also in the year 1641, when the Spirit within them mov'd the blind Zealots to joyn with the <hi>Scotch Rebels,</hi> (as it is recorded by the same Historian, <hi>page</hi> 535) in the dead of the night, the more to terrifie the timorous vulgar, <hi>they us'd to cry in the streets of</hi> London, <hi>That all people should arise to their defence, for the King with his Papists were coming to fire the City, and cut their threats in their beds. Than which contrivance</hi> (saith the Author) <hi>though nothing were more false, yet found the effects of truth.</hi> Likewise in <hi>No<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vemb.</hi> 1642 <hi>Vicar,</hi> the Presbyterian Historian, in his Chronicle, <hi>Part</hi> 1. <hi>page</hi> 212. speaking of the Battle of <hi>Edge-hill,</hi> gives this relation of his holy Brethren, <hi>The Sabbath day after their arrival to</hi> London, <hi>the godly and well-offected Ministers</hi> (i. e. the Presbyterian Predicants) <hi>throughout the City preached and praised the Lord publickly, for their joyful and safe return home to their Parents, Masters, and Friends, exhenting those young Solditers of Christs Army Royal still to retain, and be forward and ready to shew their courage and zeal to the defence of Gods Cause, and their Countreys welfare: shewing them the Plots of their adversaries, to have introduced Popery and Tyranny into the Kingdom; and assuring them, that this War on their parts was waged and managed by Papists, an Army of Papists be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing raised by the Kings command, contrary to his vows and protestations.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>It is needless, I suppose, to repeat here, how often most of our emi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nent <hi>Divines,</hi> and zealous <hi>Church men,</hi> ever since the <hi>Reformation,</hi> have been slandered in this manner by these hot-headed <hi>Enthusiasts,</hi> and compelled to make <hi>Apologies</hi> in their own vindication against such wicked aspersions. Was not the Learned Dr. <hi>Mountague,</hi> Bishop of <hi>Chichester,</hi> forced to write a Book, intituled, <hi>Appello Caesarem,</hi> against the malicious Calumnies of the <hi>Puritan</hi> Party, where the godly man sheweth himself so far from being daunted with their bold attempts and bloody Menaces, that, with true <hi>Christian courage</hi> he openly exposeth to the world their <hi>mysteries of iniquety,</hi> and fully discovereth their per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nicious contrivances to undermine our <hi>Church,</hi> and subvert our <hi>Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment?</hi> and amongst the rest, he speaketh in this manner, <hi>The truth is, as with the Jesuit he is an Heretick, that is not</hi> furloso <hi>more a Roman
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:204734:4"/>Catholick, so with the Puritan he is a Papist that will not run a madding with them. It is not the first time</hi> (saith he) <hi>for this very cause I have been talk'd of, esteem'd of, traduc'd as a Papist; which I can the better brook, because they have meted this measure to the Church of England it self, as sympathising with Papists in her Liturgy, Discipline, and Doctrine.</hi> In his <hi>Appeal to Cesar, part</hi> 2. <hi>c.</hi> 1. <hi>p.</hi> 110.</p>
               <p>All true Protestants therefore, who prefer the <hi>Harmonious</hi> and <hi>Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stolical Order</hi> and <hi>Government</hi> of the <hi>Church</hi> of <hi>England,</hi> before the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fused hodge-podge of the new-found <hi>Genevesian Discipline,</hi> have now (I think) sufficient reason to be ware of such dangerous contrivances for the future, and not suffer themselves to be gull'd again by such gilded pretences, which, like the <hi>Apples</hi> of <hi>Sodom,</hi> are specious indeed and beautiful without, but base and filthy within. The <hi>Presbyterians,</hi> to our sorrow, have by this policy once deceived us, and the Lord forgive them; but if they deceive us again, then the Lord forgive us. <hi>Improbe Neptunum accuset, qui iterum naufragium facit.</hi> As for my part, I de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clare before God and the World, that I renounce with all my heart and Soul as well the <hi>Idolatrous Papists,</hi> as the <hi>Anarchical Presbyterians,</hi> whose blind zeal and transparent hypocrisie, with their appurtenances, <hi>abjuro, denego, detestor.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>I must confess, the Presbyterians are something beyond the Papists in matters of <hi>Religion,</hi> neither did I ever compare them together in that point, but I supposed with the most Learned of our <hi>Church,</hi> and particularly with <hi>Englands Solomon,</hi> King <hi>James</hi> of glorious memory, in his <hi>Apology</hi> for the <hi>Oath of Allegiance, page</hi> 19. That <hi>Papists</hi> were never persecuted in this <hi>Kingdom</hi> (if not by <hi>Cromwel</hi> and his <hi>Rumpers</hi>) for matters of Faith, but for their wicked Principles, and destructive Practices against <hi>Temporal Government.</hi> And now I appeal to the judi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious Reader, if I have not sufficiently demonstrated in my former Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per out of the prime Authors and Founders of the <hi>Genevesian Gospel,</hi> as <hi>Calvin, Beza, Knox, Buchanan, &amp;c.</hi> that the Presbyterian Principles are altogether as dangerous and destructive, if not more pernicious to <hi>Temporal Government,</hi> than that of the Papists themselves. And if your Answer to this be not rather a plain confession of the crime, than any vindication thereof, let the <hi>Reader</hi> judge.</p>
               <p>First, you say, <hi>I am fain to go into other Countreys, as far as</hi> Scotland <hi>and</hi> Geneva, <hi>to prove the Rebellious Principles of the Presbyterians.</hi> But, <hi>good Sir Presbyter,</hi> is not that enough, or are not the Presbyterians every where of the same <hi>stamp</hi> and <hi>coin?</hi> And besides, why may it not be as good a way to prove the Princ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ples of the <hi>Presbyterians,</hi> by al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledging the Doctrine of the <hi>Rope</hi> of <hi>Geneva,</hi> and his chief <hi>Incendiarites,</hi>
                  <pb n="5" facs="tcp:204734:4"/>as it is to demonstrate the Principles of the <hi>Papists,</hi> by alledging the Doctrine of the <hi>Pope</hi> of <hi>Rome,</hi> and his approved <hi>Emissaries?</hi> But if neither of these reasons be sufficient in your <hi>Phantasie</hi> do but peruse Dr. <hi>Bancroft</hi> Archbishop of <hi>Canterbury's Book of dangerous Positions,</hi> and there you shall find enough even of <hi>English Presbyterians</hi> (though but Sucklings then) eagerly maintaining this <hi>Anarchical Doctrine;</hi> there you shall find a whole Chapter of that particular subject, with this Title, <hi>The Doctrine of certain</hi> English <hi>Ministers, which they learn'd at</hi> Geneva, <hi>and published of purpose to have procured the like course of Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sormation in</hi> England <hi>to that in</hi> Scotland. Behold now, <hi>Sir Presbyter,</hi> your <hi>Genevesion Gospellers,</hi> and those <hi>English</hi> too, and <hi>English</hi> that to promote the <hi>good old Cause,</hi> would not scruple to destroy that antient and <hi>Apostolical Hierarchy</hi> of the Church of <hi>England,</hi> and enflame their <hi>Native Countrey</hi> into a total combustion of Sedition and Rebellion. But let us see whether your second Answer be any thing less ridiculous or impertinent than the former. <hi>Yet admit</hi> (say you) <hi>the Presbyterians in</hi> England <hi>hold the same Principles, put the question whether were more Antimonarchical or unsase to Government, an opinion, that Tyrants and opposers of God, might</hi> (propter id) <hi>be opposed by their Subjects,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>or that a good King, one of the Reformed Religion, meerly for being such, should be deposed, dethron'd, and murthered,</hi> &amp;c? But <hi>(good Sir Phesbyter)</hi> what is more feasible, than for a Presbyterian to make a Tyrant of what <hi>Prince</hi> he pleases? We see now with what dexterity he makes <hi>Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pists and Pensioners</hi> of the most <hi>zealous Protestants,</hi> and no less <hi>faithful Patriots;</hi> and we have lately seen with what <hi>Legerdemain</hi> he made a <hi>Tyrant</hi> of the best of <hi>Princes.</hi> What Sovereign then can be secure from these Presbyterians, if it lies in their breast thus to make him either a <hi>Titus</hi> or a <hi>Nero,</hi> a clement <hi>Prince,</hi> or a cruel <hi>Tyrant?</hi> or can he think himself a <hi>Sovereign,</hi> and not rather <hi>Tenant at will</hi> to his own <hi>Anarchi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cal</hi> Subjects? Yet you would fain perswade us, your holy <hi>Puritans</hi> teach onely, that <hi>Tyrants may be opposed by their Subjects;</hi> whereas all the world can tell, how in our own days they have not onely <hi>opposed,</hi> but also <hi>deposed, dethron'd, and cruelly murdered,</hi> not a <hi>Tyrant,</hi> but the most meek and Religious of <hi>Sovereigns,</hi> and that by a <hi>formality</hi> of Law too; a thing I never heard perpetrated by any Popish Subjects since the crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the World, no, not by the most barbarous Heathens against the worst of Tyrants.</p>
               <p>As for a Kings being of the <hi>Reformed Religion,</hi> we know it signifies nothing to the Presbyterian <hi>Zealots,</hi> except he be of the <hi>Genevesian Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine</hi> and <hi>Discipline;</hi> the <hi>Church</hi> of <hi>England,</hi> say they, <hi>is neither hot nor cold, neither Popish nor Reformed.</hi> And therefore in the Year 1648,
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:204734:5"/>when the late <hi>King</hi> and <hi>Parliament</hi> were like to agree, the Presbyteri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an <hi>Incendiaries</hi> exclaimed against such proposals, untill the <hi>Genevesi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an Discipline</hi> were first established by Law. <hi>This restitution of his Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jesty</hi> (say they) <hi>to the exercise of his Royal power, before security had from him for settling Religion, your Lordships know by our eight desires, and otherwise, is conceiv'd by us to be inconsistent with the safety and se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>curity of Religion.—The bringing of his Majesty to some of his Houses in or near</hi> London, <hi>before satisfaction and security had from him in point of Religion, and in such other things as are necessary for the safety of the Kingdoms, could not (as we conceive) but be an exceeding great discou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ragement and offence to the Presbyterians in England, who will con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive that the remedy is worse than the disease.</hi> In the humble Repre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sentation of the Commissioners of the General Assembly to the Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nourable Estates of Parliament, April the 28. 1648. Likewise, in the year 1649. the <hi>Rebellious-Zealots</hi> would not submit themselves in <hi>Scotland</hi> to their natural <hi>Soveraign,</hi> his present Majesty, except <hi>he would by solemn Oath under his hand and seal, allow the National Covenant of</hi> Scotland, <hi>and the Solemn League and Covenant of</hi> Scotland, England, <hi>and</hi> Ireland, <hi>and would prosecute the ends thereof in his Royal station.</hi> See <hi>Baker</hi>'s Chronicle, page 613. Tell me now, Sir <hi>Presbyter,</hi> are not these rare examples of your Presbyterian-Loyalty to your natural Princes, and to Princes of the <hi>Protestant Church,</hi> and <hi>Reformed Religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on</hi> too? But to set down exactly the true state of the question, admit (as you say, and cannot deny) the Presbyterians of <hi>England</hi> hold the same principles with the <hi>Genevesian-Gospellers;</hi> put you the question now, whether is more <hi>Antimonarchial</hi> or unsafe to <hi>Government,</hi> an <hi>opinion</hi> or rather a <hi>fundamental doctrine,</hi> that <hi>Tyrants</hi> and opposers of God, (<hi>i. e.</hi> any Prince that hinders the <hi>growth</hi> of <hi>Presbyterie</hi>) may <hi>propter id,</hi> be oppos'd, nay, depos'd, dethron'd and cruelly Murder'd by their Subjects, as Presbyterians undeniably hold, and as undeniably have practis'd: or that it is <hi>Herefie</hi> in any <hi>Christian</hi> to affirm, that a <hi>Prince may be slain or depos'd by his Subjects for any disorder or default, either in Life or Government,</hi> as very <hi>Eminent Papists</hi> expresly teach; as (to omit those two <hi>swindging Authorities,</hi> as you call them, of the <hi>Rhemists Commentaries,</hi> and of the <hi>Council of Constance</hi>) it suffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciently appeareth by <hi>Alphons. à Castro, lib de haeres. in verbo</hi> Tyran. <hi>Dominic. à Soto,</hi> lib. 5. <hi>de Just. &amp; Jur.</hi> qu. 1. <hi>art.</hi> 3. and many others.</p>
               <p>Now do you if you can, produce such another <hi>Ecclesiastical Assem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly</hi> or <hi>Synod,</hi> or such eminent writers of the Presbyterian party, thus declaring it <hi>Impious and Heretical</hi> to believe that Subjects may Law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:204734:5"/>depose or Murder their <hi>Soveraign</hi> upon the account of any Tyran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny or <hi>oppression</hi> whatsoever, and you will make the World have a better opinion of your Sect, than ever they had hitherto: otherwise, not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withstanding all your multiplied bablings, we must conclude, <hi>to give the Devil his due,</hi> that in matter of Temporal Government, the prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciples of the Papists are far Sounder and more <hi>Orthodox,</hi> than the Presbyterian <hi>Catechism.</hi> As for the practises of the one and the other, you tell me, <hi>could I prove my charge against the Presbyterians, as unex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceptionably, as you can that of the Plot against the Papists, I would do something indeed.</hi> But I appeal to any man of common sense, if you be not as <hi>unexceptionably</hi> impudent in your bold assertions, as the Pres<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>byterians are notoriously <hi>Treacherous</hi> in their pernicious practices. The bloud of our late <hi>Martyr'd Soveraign,</hi> and the effusion of so much Protestant bloud in the late Civil Wars, (you should say, <hi>Presbyterian Rebellion</hi>) you are so impudent as to plaister it upon the unfortunate Papists, without any colour or shew of proof, (it being plain to all the World, that in the whole List of the <hi>Regicides,</hi> none is to be found but <hi>notorious Presbyterians</hi>) and withall to affirm, that the former are more evidently prov'd guilty of the <hi>present Plot,</hi> than the latter can be con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>victed of the <hi>Rebellious practices</hi> laid to their charge: whereas on the one side, we have but four or five persons to swear this horrid <hi>conspiracy</hi> against the Papists; but on the other side, all our <hi>Records,</hi> all our <hi>Histories,</hi> nay, our own <hi>memories,</hi> and all the World can testifie the late <hi>Tragical</hi> transactions, as the inhumane Murder of our <hi>Royal Martyr,</hi> the effusion of so much innocent bloud, the burning and pillaging of so many <hi>Cities, Towns</hi> and <hi>Pallaces,</hi> and in brief all the <hi>Massacres</hi> that have been committed, all the <hi>Miseries</hi> that have hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pened in this <hi>Island</hi> of <hi>Great Britain</hi> these 50 years past, to have been wholly and solely perpetrated by these Monsters of <hi>Christianity</hi> the <hi>Anarchical</hi>-Presbyterians, as well <hi>dependent</hi> as <hi>independent,</hi> as well <hi>Scotch</hi> as <hi>English,</hi> the one <hi>beginning,</hi> the other <hi>ending</hi> the <hi>Tragedy,</hi> the one <hi>Selling,</hi> the other <hi>Killing</hi> their <hi>natural Soveraign</hi> to the amazement of all the World.</p>
               <p>Oh! how happy would they think themselves now, had these vil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lanies been as private, as the present conspiracy of the Papists? Had we been trusting to the discovery of Mr. <hi>Oats,</hi> Mr. <hi>Bedlow,</hi> or the rest, concerning these presbyterian treacheries, as well as the Popish Plot; Oh! how boldly the <hi>Puritan-Gospellers</hi> would outface our witnesses? with what black colours they would paint them, to extenuate the cre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dibility of their informations? So far they would think the charge from being unexceptionably proved against them, that they would not
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:204734:6"/>doubt but they might easily perswade the World, nothing could be more unreasonable, than to believe it upon the credit of such inconsiderable witnesses, tho' now against the Papists they hold them for <hi>Delphian Oracles.</hi>
                  <q rend="margQuotes">What! (would they say) can it be Law, equity, or consci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence, to take the oaths of some few despicable fellows, very obnoxious to be suspected of malice and corruption, against the lives of good and peaceable Subjects, men of worth and known integrity? to take the oaths of living Vagabonds, before the protestations of dying Christi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans! who can be safe, if this be admitted? or if this be justice, what can be term'd injustice amongst us?</q>
               </p>
               <p>In this manner, we may be sure, or rather in far higher terms, would our <hi>Supersanctified-Hypocrites</hi> rail against these very Persons, they now so much adore for Swearing against the Papists, had their crimes been so occult as to need a discoverer; and these, nay, people of greater credit, and much less obnoxious to exception, had come in to reveal their <hi>Mysteries</hi> of iniquity. The title of <hi>His Majesties Evidence</hi> could not in the least protect them from the snarling invectives of a Presbyterian. All that Papists now say of them, signified nothing to what the Presbyterians would then vomit against them. Witness their usage of Mr. <hi>Willoughby,</hi> alias <hi>Dangerfield, &amp;c.</hi> who when he pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended to discover a Presbyterian Plot, was presently proclaim'd in the <hi>Weekly Intelligenees</hi> and other <hi>Pamphlets,</hi> the greatest Knave and Villain upon Earth, and called <hi>Knight</hi> of the Post, <hi>Newgate-Bird,</hi> and such other titles of <hi>Honour,</hi> nay, affirmed to have been actually upon the <hi>Pillory</hi> for his misdemeanours. The Title of <hi>His Majesties Evidence,</hi> or his pretend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to witness for the <hi>King,</hi> could nothing avail him against these <hi>Sansti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied</hi> creatures, tho' now he is reputed among them an <hi>Holy Proselyte</hi> newly inspir'd and illuminated by the Lord. 'Tis true, he gave then (as himself confesses) but false informations against the Presbyterians, being put on that design either by the Popish party to turn the Plot upon their adversaries, or by some Presbyterian <hi>Politicians</hi> to gain the greater credit to their new Informer, or perhaps by himself to gain such maintenance and allowance for the future, as may keep him henceforth from the tryed punishments of the <hi>Pillory,</hi> seeing those of the trade do thrive so well. There are now in the World a great number of <hi>Fool<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hardy Desperadoes,</hi> of no Fortune, but less Honesty, who think their only way to Preferment is, to run upon <hi>desperate courses,</hi> and rather than fail of an <hi>Advancement,</hi> to venture <hi>Neck and all</hi> for a Livelihood, according to that witty saying of the Satyrist:
<q>
                     <l>Aude aliquid brevibus Gyaris, ant carcere dignum,</l>
                     <l>Si vis esse aliquid; probitas laudatur &amp; alget.</l>
                  </q>
                  <pb n="9" facs="tcp:204734:6"/>For as <hi>Virgil</hi> saith, — <hi>Quid non mortalia pectora cogis Auri sacra sames?</hi> — In St. <hi>Pauls</hi> days, Godliness was great Gain; but to these, Gain is great Godliness: of whom we may justly say with the Poet,
<q>Ʋnde habeat quarit nemo, sed oportet habere.</q>
               </p>
               <p>As for Mr. <hi>Dangerfield,</hi> this only I say, altho' he gave but false Infor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mations against the Presbyterians, yet this was not then known to the generality of the people; and tho' it is undeniable, that such a Plot might well be carried on by the Ring-leaders of that Faction, without communicating it to the Vulgar; nevertheless the <hi>Puritan-Rabble</hi> did so bark and snarl at <hi>Dangerfield,</hi> as if they had known by <hi>Revelation</hi> there was no such Plot at all.</p>
               <p>But to return from this digression to our intended purpose, since reason commands us to prefer the unanimous consent of the greatest and ablest men of our <hi>Country,</hi> together with all our <hi>Histories</hi> and <hi>Records,</hi> and our own <hi>experimental knowledg,</hi> before the oaths of four or five persons, tho' never so upright in their lives, or so positive and exact in their informations; and <hi>a fortiori,</hi> of people not so qualified, but obnoxious to several exceptions and suspicious circumstances, which mightily weakens their evidence, and leaves many judicious men in sus<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pence, frustrated of their expected satisfaction of having the Plot clear'd beyond all exception: surely, we cannot but conclude the late <hi>Rebellion</hi> to be far more <hi>unexceptionably</hi> prov'd against the Presbyteri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans, than the present Plot against the Papists. Not that I would in the least vindicate the <hi>Romanists</hi> from those horrid crimes laid to their charge, for I am fully satisfied they are as apt to commit any villany to advance their <hi>Superstitions,</hi> as the Presbyterians are to promote <hi>the Good old cause;</hi> but to shew that the late <hi>Hellish Rebellion</hi> of the one, is far more undeniable than the present <hi>Conspiracy</hi> of the other.</p>
               <p>And if your own <hi>Conscience</hi> did not accuse you of the known verity of this assertion, or if you thought the <hi>Presbyterians</hi> have not really committed these Hellish abominations objected against them, to what purpose did you set the Act of <hi>Oblivion,</hi> to bring up the rear of your ridiculous <hi>Apology?</hi> Surely, things that never have been, could not have been forgotten. <hi>Oblivio est praeteritorum.</hi> Yet you very confi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dently bid me <hi>read over the several Tryals, and other pieces extant by Authority, concerning the present Plot, and see whether it be Presbyterians or Papists that murdered Sir</hi> Edmundbury Godfrey; <hi>that hired the</hi> Ruffians <hi>to murder his Sacred Majesty, and to ruine both Church and State.</hi> But I desire you to read over the late <hi>Narratives</hi> of the <hi>Rebellion</hi> in <hi>Scotland,</hi> and see whether Bresbyterians or Papists murdered the good
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:204734:7"/>
                  <hi>Bishop</hi> of St. <hi>Andrews;</hi> read over likewise the <hi>History</hi> of the late <hi>Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bellion</hi> in <hi>England,</hi> and see whether it be Presbyterians or Papists, that have (not hired <hi>Ruffians</hi> to murder, but themselves like inhumane <hi>Traytors,</hi> actually) murder'd our late <hi>Soveraign,</hi> and totally ruin'd both <hi>Church</hi> and <hi>State:</hi> and then see what you can get by the bargain, but that notwithstanding your ridiculous <hi>Apology</hi> the Presbyterians are still worse than the Papists, whereas the one did but design, the other have actually compleated our ruine. You tell us for strange news, they are not concern'd in the present <hi>Plot;</hi> and very strange it is indeed, that there should be any Plot or Conspiracy in this <hi>Kingdom,</hi> whereof the Pres<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>byterians should nor be the chief <hi>Engineers.</hi> Yet, Sir <hi>Presbyter,</hi> in my opinion you have no great reason to brag of your Brethrens inno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cence of this Popish Plot, since the world knows, they have commited greater villanies, and that in the face of the Sun, and for <hi>Religion</hi> too. Besides, I advise you to observe the common saying, <hi>Lauda finem,</hi> and tho' your <hi>mysteries</hi> of iniquity be not yet revealed, yet beware least be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the present discovery be at an end, your Presbyterians be not found as deeply concern'd, as any Papist alive, either in this, or in another Plot of their own: for how can it be thought, that such <hi>Politick</hi> and active <hi>Machiavels</hi> should let this occasion slip, or omit the fairest op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portunity they could expect of overthrowing their greatest adversaries, the one as <hi>Idolatrous</hi> Papists, the other either as <hi>Popishly</hi> inclined, or as introducers of <hi>Tyranical</hi> and <hi>Arbitrary Government?</hi> I omit here, that I have seen several reasons and arguments, very specious indeed to out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward appearance, strongly insinuating that the Presbyterians are the <hi>primum mobile</hi> even of the present Plot, and the chief, if not the sole contrivers of all these troubles, fraudulently corrupting and suborning most of those witnesses, that came in to swear against the Papists, pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>posely to draw the <hi>Kingdom</hi> into a confusion, and thereby restore the <hi>Cromwellian Gospel</hi> and <hi>Government.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>In this assertion, I know, there is no <hi>impossibility</hi> or <hi>contradiction</hi> to be found; I believe it very <hi>feasible</hi> (and without doubt it has been of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten done) to corrupt and suborn men of better credit and reputation than these witnesses have been, that have yet appeared in this disco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very; and withall I am sure, the Presbyterians are too apt to commit any villany to promote the <hi>Good old cause:</hi> yet nevertheless, because we must not insist upon unprov'd, tho' probabie suspicions, when we have enough even of plain demonstrations to or <gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> our intended purpose of shewing how dangerous our <hi>Puritian</hi>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> if not prudently and timely prevented, are to our <hi>Church</hi> a <gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> probability of this charge, I leave to be weigh'd and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <hi>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 span">
                        <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                     </gap>icious</hi> Reader.
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:204734:7"/>In the interim, tell me I beseech you, what may be the reason that the Presbyterians are the activest and most eager prosecutors of the Papists upon the account of this Plot, and also the greatest promoters and ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mirers of those witnesses, that appear against them. Are the Presbyte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rians the ablest men in the <hi>Kingdom?</hi> or do they only apprehend the danger of this Plot? Do they love their <hi>Religion, Lives,</hi> or <hi>Liberties,</hi> better than Protestants love theirs? or were not Protestants to be made away, had this Plot gon on, as well as the Presbyterians? why then are not the latter as moderate as the former, or the former as mad as the latter? Truly, I have heard several <hi>Judicious Protestants</hi> affirm, they could never believe, that the Presbyterians should be so hot or eager in prosecuting this Popish Plot against so inconsiderable a party, as Papists now are in this <hi>Kingdom,</hi> except they had greater designs, or were more concerned in that Plot themselves, than they would have the <hi>World</hi> believe. But <hi>time</hi> will tell truth.</p>
               <p>Your ignorance tells you, I have affronted the <hi>Clergy</hi> of the <hi>Church</hi> of <hi>England,</hi> by calling them <hi>Dumb-dogs;</hi> but you should know before you appeared in Print, that a <hi>Dog,</hi> for his natural vigilancy, is the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon <hi>Emblem</hi> of an <hi>Ecclesiastical Pastor;</hi> and if our <hi>Prelates</hi> now be less active than is necessary for to prevent your <hi>Treacherous</hi> designs, and countermine your <hi>pernicious</hi> contrivances against their Flock, they may attribute this application of <hi>Gods word, Isa.</hi> 56.10. not to any ill meaning of mine, but rather to their own unreasonable carelesness in such a desperate juncture of times, when our greatest, if not our only enemies, the Presbyterians and Papists, are equally, tho' severally, bent for our destruction; <hi>those brethren in evil,</hi> (as the Bishop of <hi>Chiebester</hi> elegantly calls them) <hi>who looking and running two several ways, do like</hi> Samson's Foxes <hi>joyn together in the taile.</hi> in his appeal to <hi>Cesar,</hi> part I c. 4. p. 48.</p>
               <p>Here I shall beg the favour of you, to ask that <hi>Reverend Prelate,</hi> who declared himself in the <hi>Parliament</hi> before the last, so favourable to your Sect, what does he think now of the Presbyterians, or whether in his opinion they took the <hi>Reverend Bishop</hi> of St. <hi>Andrews by the Lawn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sleeves, or by the Throat?</hi> Ask likewise the rest of those learned <hi>Prelates,</hi> whether the Presbyterians have <hi>like waspish Curs bark'd</hi> at that holy man <hi>Archbishop Laud,</hi> or <hi>like your red Dragon utterly devoured him?</hi> Is it credible, think you, these eminent Divines should be of so short a me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mory, as to forget who so lately voted them out of the House of Peers, barbarously imprisoned them in the <hi>Tower,</hi> sequestered their Lands and Revenues, (which to an <hi>Englishman</hi> is worse then to lose his life) de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prived them of all power and jurisdiction both Spiritual &amp; Temporal,
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:204734:8"/>and in fine, quite abolished the whole order and <hi>hierarchy</hi> of that <hi>Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stolical</hi> institution? or is it likely they would now <hi>Apologize</hi> for that faction which have lately so <hi>Antichristianly</hi> abused them? they know it is an old and true saying, <hi>Veterem ferendo injuriam, invitas novam:</hi> and I pray God, they may not find it verified in themselves, who through their excesive meekness and patience towards these ungrateful miscreants, I am afraid, will encourage them once more to attempt the suppressing of this <hi>Apostolical hierarchy;</hi> which we may plainly read in their libells and pamphlets; is their main design. Yet notwith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>standing this, and all other eminent dangers, which daily threaten us from the Presbyterian party, you are so impudent, as to term your self an <hi>Episcopal</hi> Protestant, and yet strain your empty noddle in apolo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gizing for these <hi>Antiepiscopal</hi> Sectaries, and excusing their <hi>Schismatical</hi> separation from the <hi>Mother Church,</hi> thereby encouraging them to act over again their horrid villanies of 48. and sing the second part to the same tune.</p>
               <p>You tell us forsooth, <hi>they are our fellow-protestants, and therefore not to be reputed as enemies to our Church, but to be embraced as brethren of our Reformation.</hi> Protestants, 'tis true, they stile themselves, but false ones they are always reputed by our Church, as Papists are false <hi>Christians;</hi> for (as the Apostle faith) <hi>they are not all Israel, which are of Israel, Rom.</hi> 9.6. Neither are they all Protestants, which are called Protestants; many do love the name, but hate the thing: and therfore why should not false <hi>Protestants</hi> be thought as dangerous to the true faith and wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ship of God, as false <hi>Christians,</hi> I could never yet understand. Papists are but false <hi>Christians,</hi> but the Presbyterians are false <hi>Protestants,</hi> and by consequence they are false <hi>Christians</hi> too: why then should the one be counted our Brethren, and the other our Enemies? or what can we gain by this our ill-bestowed kindness to the presbyterians, but to draw upon us the charge of all their monstrous contrivances, and make our selves accountable for their wickedness, as the papists are now commonly charged with the horrid practices of the <hi>Jesuits?</hi> Do not we see how as the <hi>Primitive Christians</hi> were grievously slandered, and most vehemently hated by the <hi>Heathens,</hi> because of the multiplied villanies of the <hi>Gnosticks</hi> and other prophane Sects of those times, that professed <hi>Christianity;</hi> so true Protestants now are obnoxious to those manifold calumnies unjustly heaped by the Papists and other Sectaries, upon our <hi>Church</hi> and Doctrine, and the whole <hi>Reformation;</hi> because of the seditious practices and wicked treacheries of the Presbyterian party, who commonly stile themselves <hi>Protestants</hi> and <hi>Reformed,</hi> yea, <hi>Refined Christians?</hi> Nay, I do verily believe, that as the monstrous wicked<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ness
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:204734:8"/>of the aforesaid <hi>Hereticks</hi> was then a great bar to the timely con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>version of the <hi>Idolatrous Pagans;</hi> so now the <hi>unchristian</hi> proceedings of the presbyterians do mainly obstruct the <hi>Papists</hi> from receiving the true light of the <hi>Gospel.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>O, but they are our weak Brethren, and we must bear their infirmities.</hi> Weak Brethren, say you? I pray God keep them so, and grant they be never stronger to ruine our <hi>Church</hi> and <hi>State,</hi> as formerly they have done. Now the <hi>Pharisaical Hypocrites</hi> alledge the weakness and tender<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ness of their Consciences for this <hi>Schismatical</hi> disobedience to their lawful Pastors, and separation from the <hi>Mother-Church;</hi> though in 48 no tenderness of Conscience could hinder them from murdering their natural <hi>Sovereign</hi> in <hi>England,</hi> and in 79 their onely <hi>Primate</hi> and <hi>Metropolitane</hi> in <hi>Scotland. O blind Guides,</hi> (as our Saviour said of the Pharisees) <hi>which strain at a gnat, and swallow a camel, Matth.</hi> 23.34. Yet these blind Hypocrites you must hall in amougst Episcopal Prote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stants, and under the ridiculous name of <hi>dissenting Brethren,</hi> you en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deavour to foster such <hi>Vipers</hi> in the bosom of our <hi>Church;</hi> a name so strange and self-contradictory, as if we had called them our <hi>odious Lovers,</hi> our <hi>loving Enemies,</hi> or the like; for if the Presbyterians ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stinately dissent from our <hi>Church</hi> in Communion, or matters of Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion, as undoubtedly they do, how can they be our Brethren? or if they be our Brethren in <hi>Religion,</hi> how can they differ from us in Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munion, or matters of Faith, which essentially is one and individual? for, as the Apostle testisieth, there is but <hi>one Lord, one Faith, one Ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ptism, Ephes</hi> 4.5.</p>
               <p>Ay, but they do not dissent from us as much as the Papists do, not in so many, nor in so necessary points of Religion. But this is to no pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pose; first, because <hi>Heathens</hi> dissent from us more than <hi>Jews, Jews</hi> than <hi>Turks,</hi> and <hi>Turks</hi> than <hi>Papists;</hi> yet we must embrace neither <hi>Jew, Turk,</hi> nor <hi>Papist,</hi> for our dissenting Brethren in <hi>Religion.</hi> Secondly, Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cause even as it is nothing material whether a man dies of one mortal wound, or of twenty; so it skilleth not whether a <hi>Christian</hi> obsti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nately erres in one necessary point of Religion, or in a dozen. For it is in the Christian Religion, as St. <hi>James</hi> saith of the Law, <hi>Whosoever offendeth in one point, he is guilty of all, James</hi> 2.10. Now it is evident to all the world, that the Presbyterians grosly err in three of the chiefest Pillars of <hi>Christian Religion,</hi> as <hi>Charity, Ʋnity,</hi> and <hi>Obedience:</hi> It cannot therefore avail them much that they agree with us in so ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny points of the Superstructure, while they disagree from us in the very Foundation. Hear what St. <hi>Augustin</hi> saith of the <hi>Denatists</hi> in <hi>Africk,</hi> who much resemble the <hi>Presbyterians</hi> in <hi>England; In many
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:204734:9"/>things</hi> (saith he) <hi>they are with me, in few not with me; but in these few wherein they are not with me, the many things wherein they are with me do nothing avail them;</hi> in <hi>Psal.</hi> 54. <hi>ver.</hi> 19. Thirdly because all true <hi>Protestants</hi> acknowledge the Presbyterians are <hi>schismaticaly</hi> separated from the <hi>Church</hi> of <hi>England,</hi> as well as the Papists; and on the other side, in the <hi>sentiments</hi> of all Learned <hi>Divines,</hi> both antient and modern, <hi>Schism</hi> is so heinous a wickedness, that without repentance and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>union with the <hi>Church</hi> (unless perhaps invincible ignorance may lessen the crime) it wholly excludes the Party from <hi>eternal salvation,</hi> accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to the express words of our Saviour, <hi>If be neglect to hear the Church, let him be unto thee as an heathen man, and a Publican, Matth.</hi> 18.17. <hi>There cannot possibly</hi> (saith St. <hi>Irenaeus) be made any reformation of such importance, as the mischief of Schism is pernicious, lib.</hi> 4. <hi>c.</hi> 62. For (as <hi>Dionysius Alexandrinus</hi> testifieth) <hi>It is a more grievous wicked<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ness to divide the Church, than to sacrifice to Idols, ap. Euseb. lib.</hi> 6 <hi>hist. c.</hi> 37. Which is yet further affirmed by the Prince of Divines, the great St. <hi>Augustine, The sacrilege of Schism</hi> (saith he) <hi>surpasseth all wickedness, lib.</hi> 1. <hi>contra ep. Parmen. c.</hi> 4. And lest we should not believe his own single testimony, this assertion he solidly confirms by the fearful pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nishment inflicted on <hi>Corah, Dathan,</hi> and <hi>Abiram,</hi> for their <hi>schismatical</hi> disobedience to <hi>Moses</hi> and <hi>Aaron. At what time</hi> (saith he) <hi>God would teach his People by new and fresh punishments to beware of their former transgressions, when an Idol was made and adored,</hi> (Exod. 32.) <hi>when the Prophets book was burnt by the hosty King,</hi> (Jer. 36.) <hi>and the schism was attempted</hi> (Numb. 16.) <hi>by</hi> Corah and his accomplices; <hi>the Idolatry was punished with the sword, the burning of the book was revenged with wasting War and forreign Captivity; but the Schism was plagued with the sudden gaping of the earth, the Authors thereof having heen swallowed up alive, and consum'd with fire from heaven. Who now</hi> (saith this great Logician) <hi>will doubt, but that was most wickedly committed, which was most grievoufly punished? lib.</hi> 2. <hi>de Bapt. cont. Donatist. c.</hi> 6.</p>
               <p>St. <hi>Cyprian</hi> goeth yet further, and of all <hi>schismatical</hi> Separatists, giv<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth this general sentence, <hi>Such people, though they were killed in the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fession of Christs name, yet that blemish even by blood is not washed away; the unpardonable and grievous crime of dissention is not purged even with death. He cannot be a Martyr that is not in the Church. He cannot at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain to the Kingdom, that forsakes her which is to reign. Such an one may be killed, but cannot be crown'd. The enemy of the Altar, rebellious against the Sacrifice of Christ,</hi> despising the Bishops, and forsaking the Priests of God, <hi>presumes to erect another Altar, and make other prayers by his un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lawful speeches. Lib. de Ʋnit. Eccles.</hi>
               </p>
               <pb n="15" facs="tcp:204734:9"/>
               <p>Neither are our <hi>Modern Divines</hi> less plain in this particular; and to begin with <hi>Calvin,</hi> the great God of the Presbyterians, he gives his verdict in these following words. <hi>We profess the unity of the Church (such as is described by St.</hi> Paul) <hi>to be most dear unto us; and we accurse them that shall any thing violate it;</hi> lib. de necess. Reform. Eccles. And again, <hi>The Lord doth so highly esteem the Communion of his Church, that he holds him for an Apostate, and deserter of Religion, who insolently separates himself from any Christian Society, so it be such a one as hath the true Ministry of the Word and Sacraments;</hi> lib. 4. Instit. c. 1. §. 10. Either therefore we have not the true Ministry of the Word and Sacraments in the Church of <hi>England,</hi> or else the Presbyterians are Schismaticks, nay Apostates and deserters of Religion, even in the Judgment of their own Patriarch <hi>Calvin.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Luther</hi> likewise in his explication upon the <hi>Creed,</hi> speaks to the same purpose: <hi>Neither</hi> Gentile, <hi>nor</hi> Jew, (saith he) <hi>Heretick, or any other sinner, is saved, unless he make Atonement with the Church, and in all things think, do, and teach the same.</hi> As for our own <hi>Divines,</hi> they are in this point both plain and positive: <hi>It is false</hi> (saith our Learned <hi>Whitaker) that Heretical and Schismatical Churches, are true Churches.</hi> controv. 2. q. 5. c. 9. And again: <hi>Whereas he proves, that Hereticks, Apostates, and Shismaticks are not Members of the true Church, it is no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing to us; for this none of us ever affirmed.</hi> controv. 2. q. 1. c. 4.</p>
               <p>And Dr. <hi>Fulk</hi> in his Treatise of the Succession of the <hi>Church,</hi> p. 390. saith: <hi>What skilleth it, whether one being drawn by Heresie or Schism from the Body of Christ, be subject to Eternal Damnation?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Mr. <hi>Casaubone</hi> also in his Letter to Cardinal <hi>Peron,</hi> written by the appointment of King <hi>James,</hi> page 8. thus saith: <hi>The King doth con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demn and detest those, who departed either from the faith of the Catholick Church, and became Hereticks; or from her Communion, and became Schis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maticks.</hi> And the same is taught by Dr. <hi>Humphrey,</hi> ad rat. 3. Cam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piani. p. 207. by <hi>Field,</hi> lib. 1. de Eccles. c. 7. Confess. Helvet. art. 17. Bulling. in compend, fidei. lib. 6. c. 11. Musculus in Locis, tit. de Schismate, p. 621. and many others.</p>
               <p>Is it not evident therefore by the unanimous consent of so many <hi>Protestant Divines,</hi> so exactly concurring with the general vote of the An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cient Writers, and Gods express word, that Schism is so capital a crime, that it cuts off the party from the <hi>Church</hi> of <hi>God,</hi> and thereby from all ordinary means of obtaining eternal Salvation? And is it not likewise certain, that Protestants and Presbyterians (notwithstanding your ridiculous cementing of them together) do mutually censure and charge each other with <hi>Schism,</hi> if not with impious and <hi>Heretical</hi>
                  <pb n="16" facs="tcp:204734:10"/>Doctrines. None I think, can be so ignorant, as not to know what a Cloud of Writers have given their verdict on both sides in this particular. To the end therefore you may not hereafter exclaim a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainst me, or alledge that I make it my business to breed dissention and division between <hi>Protestants,</hi> by calling the Presbyterians <hi>Schismatical Sectaries,</hi> (tho' indeed it is my design to seperate the <hi>Wheat</hi> from the <hi>Tares,</hi> true <hi>Protestants</hi> from counterfeit <hi>Religionaries,</hi> and warn them not to trust again such <hi>Hypocritical</hi> Dissemblers) and that you may be convinc'd, this is no particular opinion of mine, but the general tenet of our Learned <hi>Divines;</hi> hear some of them speak their own minds at a time, when Presbytery was not near so monstrous in it self, nor yet half so dangerous or formidable to our <hi>Church,</hi> as it is at pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sent. <hi>The Puritans</hi> (saith Dr. <hi>Bancroft, Archbishop</hi> of <hi>Canterbury) do pervert the true meaning both of Scripture and Fathers, to serve their own turns.</hi> In his Survey of the pretended Holy Discipline, c. 5. <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>And Mr. <hi>Parkes,</hi> in his book dedicated to the <hi>Archbishop,</hi> in his <hi>Epistle Dedicatory,</hi> thus saith of your holy Brethren: <hi>They are head<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>strong, and hardened in error; they strike at the main points of faith, and shaking the foundation it self, and calling into question Heaven and Hell, the Divinity and Humanity, yea the very Soul and Salvation of our Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viour himself.</hi> And again, ibid. <hi>The Puritans have Pestilent Heresies, they are Heretical and Sacrilegious.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Mr. <hi>Powel</hi> likewise, in his Considerations, saith of them: <hi>They are notorious and manifest Schismaticks, cut off from the Church of God.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>And this is further confirmed by Mr. <hi>Casaubons</hi> excellent Rule, (taken out of S. <hi>Cyprian</hi>'s 69. Ep.) in Exercit. 15. contra Baron. nu. 6. Where he saith: <hi>It is an undoubted verity, that whensoever the pious People adheres to their true and lawfull Bishop, they are Gods Church; unsomuch that whosoever seperates himself from this Congregation, it cannot be doubted, but that he is not in the Church.</hi> Presbyterians therefore are not in the <hi>Church</hi> of God, who have <hi>Schi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>matically</hi> se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perated themselves from the pious and orthodox Protestants adhering to their true and lawful <hi>Bishops.</hi> To be brief, the <hi>Bishop</hi> of <hi>Chichester</hi> gives us a full and short description of these Holy and Sanctified Bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>theren: I <hi>must confoss</hi> (saith he) <hi>my dissent through and sincere from the fuction of Novelizing Puritans; men intractible, insociable, incompliable with those that will not</hi> aedificare ad dissensiones; <hi>but in no one point more, than in their desperate doctrine of Predestination;</hi> in his Appeal to <hi>Caesar,</hi> page 60. And again p. 320. he speaks to the Presbyterians themselves in this manner: <hi>I go no farther, but leave you to your selves, and (if <gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>s<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>sible)
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:204734:10"/>unto more charitable conceits of those that deserve no other imputation, but, they are no Puritans: Which God of his Goodness keep out of this Church and State, as dangerous as Popery, for any thing I am able to dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cern: The only difference being, Popery is for Tyranny, Puritanism for Anarchy; Popery is original of Superstition, Puritanism the Highway unto Prophaneness; both alike Enemies to Piety.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>But lest you should think this learned Prelate any thing transpor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted with prejudice or partiality in this his censure of your Sanctified Brethren, hear what your own Patriarch and first founder speaketh of those, who had the first Fruits of his Spirit, his holy Proselytes at <hi>Genev<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>: It is certain</hi> (saith he) <hi>that a man shall not see so horrible monsters in the Papacy, as where the Gospel is Preach'd and Profess'd; for they will say they are reformed, and yet they seem to be Devils incarnate, neither have we need to go far off to find such sights.</hi> Calvin serm. 10. in ep. ad Ephes.</p>
               <p>Now the Presbyterians on the other side are nothing behind in slan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dering and charging the Church of <hi>England</hi> with all imaginable cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruption; <hi>Schism,</hi> they think, is too small a crime to be alledg'd against her, whilst Popish <hi>Superstition</hi> and the dregs of <hi>Antichrist</hi> do compose the chiefest part of her Liturgy, Doctrine and Government. <hi>The form of the Communion-Book</hi> (say they) <hi>is taken from the Church of Antichrist; as the reading of the Epistles, and Gospels,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>the most of the Prayers, the manner of administring the Sacraments,</hi> &amp;c. in Dr. <hi>Whitgifts</hi> defence, p. 474. And in their Book intituled, The Petition of 22. Preachers in <hi>London,</hi> they say: <hi>In the Communion-Book there be things of which there is no sense, there is contradiction in it, even of necessary and essential points of Religion.</hi> And also in their Book of Cannons and Constitutions Ecclesiastical, printed <hi>Anno</hi> 1604. they say: <hi>The worship in the Church of</hi> England <hi>is corrupt, superstitious, un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lawfull and repugnant to the Scriptures.</hi> Likewise the great Presbyte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rian <hi>Alexander Henderson,</hi> in his first <hi>Paper</hi> to our <hi>Royal Martyr,</hi> in the Book intituled <hi>Reliquiae Carolinae,</hi> pnrt 1. p. 314. thus speaketh: <hi>It is too well known that the Reformation of K.</hi> Henry 8. <hi>was most imperfect in the essentials of Doctrine, Worship and Government: And though it proceeded by some degrees afterwards, yet the Government was never reformed, the head was changed,</hi> Dominus non Dominium, <hi>and the whole limbs of the Antichristian Hierarchy retained. And for this cause</hi> (as our late <hi>Sove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raign</hi> well observes) <hi>their zealous Superstition thinks or pretends, they cannot do God and the Church a greater service, than utterly to destroy that Primitive, Apostolical, and anciently universal Government of the Church by Bishops;</hi> in his Eikon Basilike, c. 9. But to conclude, and if <hi>Sy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>metry</hi>
                  <pb n="18" facs="tcp:204734:11"/>may tell us the true stature of a man by the proportion of his foot, surely we may easily guess what sense the Presbyterians have of those of our <hi>Church,</hi> by that prodigious Sermon of <hi>David Blake,</hi> a <hi>Ring. leader</hi> of the <hi>Kirk</hi> of <hi>Scotland,</hi> who in the year 1596. solemnly preached, <hi>That all Kings were the Devils Barns, that King</hi> James <hi>his heart was treacherous, and that the Devil was in the Court, and the Guiders of it; that Queen</hi> Elizabeth <hi>was an Atheist, and a wicked Wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man; that the Nobility and Lords were miscreants, bribers, degenerated, godless, dissemblers, and enemies to the Church,</hi> &amp;c. And yet this most <hi>se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditious</hi> and <hi>Anarchical</hi> Sermon was so far from being censured by the <hi>holy Synagogue</hi> of the Presbyterians, that they openly told King <hi>James, It was Gods cause, and they must protect and defend him to the hazard of their lives.</hi> See <hi>Spotiswood</hi>'s History of the <hi>Church</hi> of <hi>Scotland, page</hi> 423, &amp;c.</p>
               <p>Speak now, <hi>Sir Presbyter,</hi> and tell us plainly your opinion of your holy dissenting Brethren; can you defend their going out of the <hi>Church of England</hi> from the brand of Schism? Is it not the infallible Badge of Sectaries, to depart from the Communion of Orthox Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stians? Observe what the beloved Disciple saith, <hi>They went out from us, but they were not of us; for if they had been of us, they would no doubt have continued with us.</hi> 1 <hi>Joh.</hi> 2.19. Who therefore is to be esteemed in your judgment the greatest <hi>Schismatick,</hi> the <hi>Church</hi> of <hi>England,</hi> for not complying with the Presbyterians pretended re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fining of the <hi>Reformation,</hi> or the Presbyterian <hi>Synagogue</hi> for not obey<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the <hi>Church</hi> of <hi>England,</hi> and their lawful <hi>Bishops?</hi> For undoubted<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, in this Separation, and mutual exclaiming against each other, either Party must unavoidably be guilty of <hi>Schism;</hi> otherwise we must confess, the <hi>Novatians, Aerians, Luciferians,</hi> and <hi>Donatists,</hi> to to have been most unjustly reputed <hi>Schismaticks</hi> by the antient Wri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters. Do not we know, that one of the chiefest points for which <hi>Ae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rius</hi> was anathematized even for an <hi>Heresiark</hi> by the <hi>Primitive Church,</hi> was his asserting the Parity or Equality of <hi>Bishops</hi> and <hi>Presbyters?</hi> as St. <hi>Augustine</hi> recordeth, <hi>Haer.</hi> 53. and as St. <hi>Epiphanius, Haer.</hi> 75. testifieth, and fully confuteth. And yet this very Doctrine is now the <hi>Characteristical</hi> note and badge of our holy Puritans. How then can <hi>Aerius</hi> be condemned for a wicked Novelist, and these his followers be extolled for refining <hi>Reformists?</hi> Can the same Doctrine be ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>counted <hi>Orthodox</hi> in the one, and <hi>Heretical</hi> in the other? or must we say, that of all Antiquity <hi>Aerius</hi> alone did see the truth, and all the rest were blind?</p>
               <p>Be not deceived, good Presbyterians, but consider with your selves,
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:204734:11"/>whether it be agreeable to sense or reason, that a single opinion of a private Upstart, grounded upon no express Text of Scripture, should be preferred before the unanimous consent of all <hi>Orthodox</hi> Antiquity, and the whole <hi>Church</hi> of <hi>Christ,</hi> at that time especially, when all the world acknowledgeth her to have been in her greatest splendor and purity. Stand not blind folded with prejudice or partiality, and suffer not your selves to be transported with any preposterous zeal or animosity, which will but obnubilate your understanding, and wea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken your judgment; but rather examine with a sober and unbyass'd mind the grounds and motives of your Separation from your lawful Superiours and Pastors, and consider impartially, whether it be not more reasonable for Christians to follow the Doctrine of the most learned and holy Doctors of the <hi>Primitive Church,</hi> (who have un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doubtedly <hi>followed the Lamb,</hi> and are now glorifi'd in <hi>Heaven</hi>) than the new found opinion and groundless assertion, either of <hi>Aerius,</hi> or his late sticklers, <hi>John Calvin</hi> and his <hi>Genevesian Gospellers.</hi> Remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber how the Lord saith, <hi>Stand ye in the ways, and see, and ask for the old paths, where is the good way, and walk therein, and ye shall find rest for your souls, Jer.</hi> 6.16. And this <hi>rest,</hi> if you expect to enjoy, forsake not the antient form of <hi>Church-Government,</hi> which has continued in <hi>Christs Church</hi> since the Apostles time. <hi>Saepe viatorem nova, non vetus orbita sallit.</hi> Can you find in all Antiquity one <hi>Orthodox Christian</hi> as<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>serting, or one faithful <hi>Church</hi> exercising this your Presbyterian Dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipline? Do not all <hi>Ecclesiastical Histories</hi> tell us, how Christs Church, since his Ascension, has been always governed by Bishops? Was not St. <hi>Augustine</hi> Bishop of <hi>Hippo</hi> in <hi>Affrick,</hi> St. <hi>Ambrose</hi> of <hi>Millan,</hi> St. <hi>Hillary</hi> of <hi>Poictiers,</hi> St. <hi>Cyprian</hi> of <hi>Carthage,</hi> St. <hi>Chrysostom</hi> of <hi>Constantinople,</hi> St. <hi>Athanasius</hi> of <hi>Alezandria,</hi> St. <hi>Irenaeus</hi> of <hi>Lyons;</hi> and, in a word, were not the most eminent <hi>Ecclesiastical Wor thies,</hi> that flourished since the beginning of Christianity, Bishops of their respective Sees or Churches? Did you ever hear of any Society of Christians, since the Apostles time, governed onely by Presbyters or Elders, not subordinate to Episcopal Government? Or can you find in all the holy Scriptures one Text to warrant these your levelling Principles, of abolishing the antient Ecclesiastical Hierarchy of Christs Church? Can you deny, but that until our Saviour's time, there were in the <hi>Jewish</hi> Church Chief or High Priests, which by God's ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointment were Superintendents and Presidents over the Levites and inferiour Clergy? See 2 <hi>Chron.</hi> 19.11. <hi>Matth.</hi> 2.4. <hi>Heb.</hi> 9.6. And is it not as evident, that in the New Testament the Apostles were Presidents and Chief Superintendents, not onely over the Laity of
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:204734:12"/>their times, but also over all the Deacons, nay over the Priests and El<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders of the Church of Christ? Since therefore it is incredible, that this Authority conferr'd by Christ on his Apostles, principally for the good of his Church, should die with their persons, and not rather descend to their Successors, and thereby continue in his Church to the end of the World; it cannot be doubted, but that the Apostles Power and Jurisdiction over Priests and Deacons was invested in others, who, as the Apostles Successors, should govern not onely the Flock, but also the inferiour Pastors and Rulers thereof. Now that Bishops are the lawful Successors of the Apostles in this Spiritual Jurisdiction, may be gathered, first, out of that passage of holy Scripture, where the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stleship of St. <hi>Matthias</hi> is expresly called <hi>his Bishoprick, Acts</hi> 1.20. thereby infinuating, that Bishops are the same, or at least the next in Authority to the Apostles. 2. It may be confirmed by the uni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>versal consent of all antient Writers, unanimously affirming, that Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>shops onely have succeeded to the Apostles in the Government of Christs Church. See <hi>Cone. Neocesar. Can.</hi> 13. <hi>Damas. ep.</hi> 3. <hi>de Chore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piscopis. Hiero. ep. ad Marcellam de Erroribus Montani. Aug. in Psal.</hi> 44. <hi>Leo ep.</hi> 88. <hi>Isidor. lib.</hi> 2. <hi>de Divin. Officiis. Beda in c.</hi> 10. <hi>Luc.</hi> and several other antient Writers of the Primitive Church.</p>
               <p>But before we lanch further into the Testimonies of these ancient Writers, that we may at once both confirm our own Doctrine, and confound yours, let us see what great proofs you can produce out of ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Scripture or Fathers, either for your Presbyterian, or against our Episcopal Government.</p>
               <p>First, you say, there is no mention in holy Scripture of a <hi>Bishops</hi> being above a <hi>Presbyter,</hi> therefore no such thing is to be admitted. A rare <hi>Argument</hi> indeed; but what if I say, that your <hi>Genevesian Discipline</hi> was never mentioned in <hi>holy Scripture,</hi> and therefore is not to be al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowed or admitted in <hi>Christs Church?</hi> What can you answer to this retortion, or what silly <hi>Sophisters</hi> are you, thus blind-fold, <hi>andabata<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rum more,</hi> to run on head-long against your adversaries, and never consider how by this <hi>Argument</hi> you quite undermine your own <hi>Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gregational, Classical, Synodical, Provincial,</hi> and <hi>National Assemblies?</hi> Did you ever hear such barbarous terms in <hi>holy Scripture?</hi> or ever find them (at least in your sense) used by any antient Writer? Why then should you reject <hi>Episcopal Government</hi> so universally practised, and set up the Presbyterian <hi>Democracy,</hi> never heard of in the <hi>Church</hi> of <hi>Christ</hi> before <hi>Calvin</hi>'s days? Certainly though the one had been no better grounded on <hi>holy Scripture</hi> than the other, yet the antiquity of <hi>Episcopacy,</hi> and the quite immemorial possession of <hi>Bishops</hi> in the Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:204734:12"/>of the <hi>Church</hi> so many hundred years together, is reason enough for any peaceable <hi>Christian</hi> to prefer it before any new found invention: It being an undoubted <hi>Maxim, In pari jure vel causa melior est conditio-possidentis.</hi> Moreover, according to the approved rule of St. <hi>Augustin, That, which the universal Church doth hold, and was not instituted by Councils, but hath been always retained, we most justly believe to have descended from no Authority, but the Apostles.</hi> lib. 4. de bapt. c. 24. ep. 119. and in several other places. Since therefore, the <hi>Original</hi> and beginning of <hi>Episcopal</hi> Government cannot be found from the Apostles downwards, we must conclude it is at least of <hi>Apostolical,</hi> and consequently of Divine institution. But to be brief, does not St. <hi>Paul</hi> expresly allow <hi>Timothy,</hi> the first <hi>Bishop</hi> of the <hi>Ephesians,</hi> to judge the <hi>Priests</hi> or <hi>Elders</hi> of that Church? 1 Tim. 5.19, 20. does not he therefore own him to be their Lawful Superior? for surely, common sense can tell us, that no <hi>Magistrate</hi> whatsoever has any legal power to judge his equal in Authority; according to that approved <hi>Maxim, Paribus in pares nulla datur potestas.</hi> Since therefore it must be granted, either that <hi>Timothy</hi> had power and jurisdiction over the <hi>Presbyters.</hi> of his <hi>Church,</hi> or the <hi>Apostles</hi> instructions to him were vain and most im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pertinent, and that none can have any lawful <hi>jurisdiction</hi> over his equal, it evidently ensueth, he was by the testimony of holy Scripture, their true and lawful <hi>Superior.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Secondly, you alledge, that in holy <hi>Scripture</hi> the same persons are pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miscuously called <hi>Bishops</hi> or <hi>Presbyters,</hi> Acts 20.28. <hi>Philip.</hi> 1.1. <hi>Tit.</hi> 1.5, 7. and 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 3. therefore (say you) they are the same Function. A most excellent piece of <hi>Logick.</hi> But are not the same persons promiscuously called <hi>Apostles</hi> and <hi>Disciples</hi> in the <hi>Gospel?</hi> Is it therefore the same thing to be an <hi>Apostle</hi> and a <hi>Disciple?</hi> If so, to what purpose was <hi>Matthias,</hi> (who was already a <hi>Disciple,</hi> Acts 1.21.) so solemnly elected <hi>Apostle</hi> in the place of <hi>Judas?</hi> If not, then the <hi>identity</hi> of names doth not always import the <hi>identity</hi> of <hi>Functions.</hi> Likewise, do not we find in the old <hi>Testament</hi> the same persons called sometimes <hi>Priests,</hi> some<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times <hi>High-Priests?</hi> as <hi>Azariah</hi> (2 Chron. 26.17.) is called only a <hi>Priest,</hi> yet <hi>v.</hi> 20. he is stiled the <hi>Chief-Priest.</hi> Therefore either our <hi>Presbyterian</hi> argument is groundless and <hi>Sophistical,</hi> or else <hi>Chief-Priests</hi> differ'd no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing from the <hi>inferiour-Priests</hi> in the Old Law. And besides, the <hi>Apostles</hi> often called themselves <hi>Presbyters</hi> or <hi>Elders,</hi> 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 5.1. and 2 <hi>Jo.</hi> v. 1. and 3 <hi>Jo.</hi> v. 1. <hi>&amp;c.</hi> Yet I hope our present <hi>Religionaries</hi> will acknowledge they differ'd from single <hi>Presbyters</hi> both in order and jurisdiction. But to come nearer home, what is more common in our own days, than to hear <hi>Priests</hi> or <hi>Presbyters</hi> called <hi>Ministers,</hi> which
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:204734:13"/>word properly signifieth <hi>Deacons?</hi> and yet it is evident, we always count <hi>Deacons</hi> inferiour to <hi>Presbyters,</hi> though the name properly be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>longing to the one, is often attributed to the other; why then should not we conclude, that <hi>Presbyters</hi> are always inferiour to <hi>Bishops,</hi> tho' their names had been sometimes mutually communicated to one ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther? For we must observe, that <hi>Episcopus</hi> originally signifying only an <hi>Overseer,</hi> as <hi>Presbyter</hi> signifieth an <hi>Elder,</hi> or Aged man, such <hi>Presbyters</hi> as had the Cure of Souls, and charge of small <hi>Precincts,</hi> now called <hi>Parishes,</hi> under their true <hi>Bishop,</hi> might well be termed <hi>Overseers</hi> of their respective Flocks, and consequently in some sense be termed <hi>Epis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>copi</hi> or <hi>Bishops:</hi> yet forasmuch as they wanted the fulness of <hi>Ecclesiasti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cal</hi> power, and besides Preaching the word of God and Baptizing be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>l<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>evers, which <hi>Deacons</hi> also might do, could only administer the <hi>Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crament</hi> of the Lords Supper, but were not allowed to confirm the Baptized, much less to ordain other <hi>Priests</hi> or <hi>Elders</hi> in the Church, as hereafter it shall be proved; they were only <hi>Bishops</hi> by name, not by <hi>Ecclesiastical</hi> orders, even as aged persons were called <hi>Elders</hi> for their years, not for any Spiritual jurisdiction.</p>
               <p>But forasmuch as some think the <hi>Apostles</hi> have not been very exact in expressing either the Identity or Diversity of Bishops and <hi>Presbyters,</hi> but left it something ambiguous, and subject to be questioned; to clear this point we shall here observe that excellent <hi>method</hi> prescribed by our <hi>Royal Martyr,</hi> for to find out the true sense of any ambiguous passage of holy <hi>Scripture. If the practice of the Primitive Church</hi> (saith he) <hi>and the universal consent of the Fathers, be not a convincing Argument when the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terpretation of Scripture is doubtfull, I know nothing.</hi> And again: <hi>Albeit I never esteem'd any Authority equal to the Scriptures; yet I do think the unanimous consent of the Fathers, and the universal practice of the Primitive Church to the best and most authentical interpreters of Gods word, and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sequently the fittest Judges between me and you, when we differ, untill you find me a better.</hi> In his 2. paper to <hi>Alexander Henderson,</hi> in the book intituled <hi>Reliquiae Carolinae,</hi> part 1. p. 323. <hi>&amp;c.</hi> This rule therefore and prudent method we shall here observe, and for the better under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>standing of the foregoing texts of <hi>Scripture,</hi> we shall enquire into the doctrine and practice of the <hi>Primitive Church,</hi> concerning the distincti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of <hi>Bishops</hi> and <hi>Presbyters;</hi> but let us first examine what you can pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duce out of these ancient monuments for your own <hi>Genevesian Discipline.</hi> Wherefore,</p>
               <p>Thirdly, you object, that some ancient <hi>Fathers</hi> affirm, the supe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riority of <hi>Bishops</hi> above <hi>Presbyters</hi> to have been introduced only by the custom of the <hi>Church,</hi> not by any institution of <hi>Christ. The same
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:204734:13"/>is a Presbyter</hi> (faith St. <hi>Hierom) which is a Bishop, and before divisions through the Devils instigation were made in Religion, and it was said a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongst the people; I am of</hi> Paul, <hi>and I of</hi> Apollo, <hi>and I of</hi> Cephas, <hi>the Churches were governed by the Common-Councel of the Presbyters: but when every one thought those he baptized, to be his own, not Christs, it was decreed in all the World, that one should be chosen from among the Presbyters and placed above the rest, to whom all the care or charge of the Church should belong, and the Seed of Schism be taken away.</hi> in cap. 1. ep. ad Tit.</p>
               <p>This is the strongest objection or argument you can produce out of the ancient <hi>Fathers</hi> for your pretended holy <hi>Discipline,</hi> and yet so far it is from warranting that new found device, that it quite sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verts and destroys it. For tho' St. <hi>Hierom</hi> seems to affirm, that our <hi>Saviour</hi> left his <hi>Church</hi> at the beginning to be governed, not by <hi>Bishops</hi> alone, but by the common <hi>Councell</hi> of the <hi>Presbyters,</hi> yet he plainly acknowledgeth that the <hi>Apostles,</hi> (in whose time people said, <hi>I am of</hi> Paul, <hi>and I of</hi> Apollos, <hi>and I of</hi> Cephas, as appeareth 1 Cor. 1.12.) to avoid <hi>Schism</hi> (which from the <hi>Anti-hierarchical</hi> equality of <hi>Ecclesiastical Pastors</hi> should unavoidably ensue) appointed <hi>Bishops</hi> above the <hi>Presby<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters</hi> to rule and Govern the <hi>Church,</hi> that so the seed of <hi>Schism</hi> might be taken away. Since therefore what the <hi>Apostles</hi> by vertue of their Function and Commission from <hi>Christ</hi> have done in the new, is with as much reason to be repu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ed done by <hi>Divine Authority,</hi> as what <hi>Moses</hi> did in the <hi>Old Testament</hi> by Gods command and inspiration: you can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not deny, if you stand to St. <hi>Hierom</hi>'s Testimony, but that the prehe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minence of <hi>Bishops</hi> above <hi>Presbyters</hi> in the <hi>Law of Grace,</hi> is as much <hi>de jure divino,</hi> as the Superiority of the <hi>High-Priests</hi> over the <hi>inferiour Priests</hi> and <hi>Levites</hi> in the <hi>Law</hi> of <hi>Moses.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>But let us hear what the rest of the Ancient Fathers, (from whom without doubt St. <hi>Hierom</hi> differ'd not in so material a point) speak of this subject. St. <hi>Ignatius,</hi> the <hi>Apostles</hi> Disciple, in his epistle to the <hi>Phi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ladelphians</hi> writes in this manner: <hi>Good are the Priests and the Ministers of the Word; yet better is the Bishop, who is entrusted with the Holy of of Holies, to whom alone the mysteries of God are committed.</hi> And in the <hi>Canons</hi> which are commonly called the <hi>Apostles Canons,</hi> thus we find, can. 40. <hi>Let not the Priests and Deacons attempt</hi> to do <hi>any thing without the Bishop; for to him the people of the Lord is committed, and he is to give an account for their Souls.</hi> Tertullian likewise lib. de bapt. c. 17. saith: <hi>The High-Priest, which is the Bish<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>p, hath right to give Baptism, and then the Presbyters and Deacons, yet not without the Bishops leave.</hi> And St. <hi>Ambrose</hi> saith in like manner: <hi>In the Bishop there are all the orders, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cause
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:204734:14"/>he is the first Priest, that is Prince of the Priests.</hi> in c. 4. ep. ad Ephes. And here we are to observe, that the ancient writers atribute not unto <hi>Bishops</hi> a bare precedence only, or a civil respect due unto them from <hi>Presbyters</hi> for their Age, Piety, or Learning, but do plainly acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge them to be the true Magistrates of <hi>Christs Church,</hi> endued with Power and Authority to rule and govern both Flocks and Pastors toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, and accordingly they atribute unto them several <hi>Prerogatives</hi> and <hi>Ecclesiastical Functions</hi> (as we have now partly seen) that <hi>Presbyters</hi> were not allow'd to perform; which could never have been so uni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>versally approv'd of, had <hi>Episcopacy</hi> been only a <hi>prudential</hi> constitu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of humane Wisdom, and not the absolute ordinance of Christ himself.</p>
               <p>First, in those ancient times <hi>Bishops</hi> alone were allow'd to sit and vote in <hi>Ecclesiastical Councils,</hi> as evidently appeareth by the respective subscriptions of all the approved <hi>Councils</hi> held in the <hi>Church</hi> for the first 600. years after <hi>Christ.</hi> And therefore when some <hi>Laicks</hi> and others that were no <hi>Bishops,</hi> came into the <hi>Council</hi> of <hi>Chalcedon,</hi> to side with the Heretick <hi>Dioscorus,</hi> the <hi>Prelates</hi> immediately caused them to be expelled, saying: <hi>Put out these superfluous persons, the Council be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>longs to the Bishops.</hi> And <hi>Theodosius junior</hi> the <hi>Emperour,</hi> in his Epistle to the <hi>Council</hi> of <hi>Ephesus,</hi> said: <hi>It is not lawfull for any that is not in the order of the most holy Bishops, to meddle in Ecclesiastical consultations.</hi> To be brief, when any of the Ancient Writers do speak of thes <hi>Church-assemblies,</hi> they always call them the <hi>Councils</hi> of <hi>Bishops: For this cause</hi> (saith <hi>Eusebius) meetings and Councils of Bishops are called to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether throughout every Province.</hi> lib. 5. hist. c. 23 and to the same purpose speaketh St. <hi>Cyprian,</hi> ep. ad Julian. <hi>Athan.</hi> ep. ad solitar. <hi>Hilar.</hi> lib. de synodis. <hi>Ambros.</hi> ep. 32. <hi>Hierom</hi> lib. 2. Apol. contra Ruffin. <hi>Aug.</hi> ep. 119. <hi>Leo.</hi> ep. 16. and a numberless number of other writers, always naming <hi>Synods</hi> of <hi>Bishops</hi> and <hi>Metropolitans,</hi> but never giving the least hint of any inferiour <hi>Presbyters</hi> (unless perhaps delegates) much less <hi>lay-Elders</hi> admitted to fit among them. Our present terms of Art, as <hi>Congregational, Classical, Provincial, National</hi> and <hi>Synodical</hi> As<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>semblies of <hi>lay-Elders</hi> or <hi>single Presbyters,</hi> were <hi>gibbrish</hi> to them in those <hi>primitive</hi> times. <hi>Christianity</hi> perhaps was then but a <hi>suckling,</hi> and therefore unfit for such <hi>mysterious</hi> expressions, which by a new power of the <hi>Gospel</hi> are able to pull down the highest <hi>Crown,</hi> and stoutest <hi>Miter,</hi> and crush them both under the <hi>Cloak</hi> of <hi>Religion.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Secondly, <hi>Bishops</hi> alone were admitted to confirm believers after Baptism, by imposition of hands. All the ancient writers, that speak
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:204734:14"/>of this Ceremony, do either call it the laying on of <hi>Bishops</hi> hands, or do expresly affirm, that none but <hi>Bishops</hi> can do it: Thus <hi>Eusebius</hi> spea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king of the Schismatick <hi>Novatus,</hi> saith; <hi>Neither has he obtain'd the rest, which according to the Cannons of the Church he should receive after Bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tism, neither was he figured by a Bishop with our Lords Seal; which when he received not, how (I beseech you) should he obtain the Holy Ghost?</hi> lib. 6. hist. c. 35. And St. <hi>Hierome,</hi> dial. adversus Lucifer. faith: <hi>I confess this is the custom of the Church, that to such as are by Presbyters and Deacons baptized a far off in lesser Cities, the Bishop goes to lay his hands upon them at the invocation of the Holy Ghost.</hi> And a little after: <hi>If you ask, why he that is Baptized in the Church, doth not receive the Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Ghost, but by the band of a Bishop, which all acknowledge to be given in true Baptism. Know that this observation comes from that Authority, that after our Lords Ascension the Holy Ghost descended upon the Apostles,</hi> &amp;c. In like manner <hi>Innocentius</hi> the first, <hi>Bishop</hi> of <hi>Rome</hi> and contemporary to St. <hi>Augustin,</hi> ep. ad Decent. c. 3. faith: <hi>As for Signing or Confir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming Children, it is manifest, that it is not lawful to be done by any other, but by a Bishop: because Presbyters, tho' they be Priests, yet they arrive not to the height of Episcopacy. For such things to be due to Bishops alone, that they should Sign or give the Holy Ghost, not only the custom of the Church doth demonstrate, but also that lesson of the Acts of the Apostles,</hi> (c. 8. v. 14.) <hi>which tells us that</hi> Peter <hi>and</hi> John <hi>were sent, to give the Holy Ghost to those that were already Baptiz'd.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>And lest you should think that <hi>Bishops</hi> do not give the <hi>Holy Ghost,</hi> because the party confirmed does not speak with Tongues, as in the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>postles time, hear how St. <hi>Augustin</hi> preoccupates and censures that ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jection: <hi>Is there any one</hi> (saith he) <hi>of so perverse an heart, as to deny those Children, on whom we have laid our hands, to have received the Holy Ghost, because they speak not with tongues?</hi> tract 6. in ep. Joan.</p>
               <p>Thirdly, so considerable and so weighty a business was the consecra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of a <hi>Bishop</hi> held by the <hi>Primitive Church,</hi> that this solemnity could not be <hi>Conoinically</hi> performed without the presence of all the Bishops in the Province, at least of three, the rest consenting and approving their proceedings; as it was expresly decreed in the Holy and <hi>Ge<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>um<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nical Council</hi> of <hi>Nice,</hi> in these words: <hi>It is indeed very convenient, that a Bishop should be ordain'd by all the Bishops in the Province, but if this be difficult either for some urgent necessity, or for the longth of the journey; then three Bishops by all means meeting, and those that are absen<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> likewise decreeing and consenting by their writings, let the ordination be performed. Yet the validity of what is done through every Province, must be attributed to the Metropolitan Bishop,</hi> Conc. Nicen. 1. can. 4. And the like decree
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:204734:15"/>is made in the Fourth <hi>Council</hi> of <hi>Carthage,</hi> where St. <hi>Augustine</hi> also was present, <hi>Can.</hi> 2. in these words, <hi>When a Bishop is Ordained, let two Bishops bold the Book of the Gospels over his head and shoulders, and one of them pouring Benediction upon him, let all the other Bishops that are present touch his head with their hands.</hi> See <hi>Conc. Carth.</hi> 2. <hi>Can.</hi> 12. <hi>&amp; Carth.</hi> 3. <hi>Can.</hi> 39. And in the next ensuing <hi>Canon,</hi> speaking of the Ordination of <hi>Presbyters,</hi> they speak in this manner, <hi>When a Presbyter is Ordain'd, the Bishop blessing him, and holding his hand upon his head, let all the Presbyters also that are present lay their hands upon his head by the Bishops hands.</hi> And <hi>Can.</hi> 4. thus they prescribe the Ordination of <hi>Deacons, When a Deacon is Ordain'd, let the Bishop onely that blesseth him lay his hand upon his head, because he is not Consecrated to the Priest<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hood, but to the Ministery.</hi> These two last <hi>Canons</hi> I mention here, that by the different degrees of the <hi>Solemnities</hi> and <hi>Ceremonies</hi> used at the Consecration of <hi>Bishops, Presbyters,</hi> and <hi>Deacons</hi> in the <hi>Primitive Church,</hi> people may understand how differently <hi>Christians</hi> in those days esteemed of these three <hi>Ecclesiastical Orders.</hi> If we may rationally gather, that <hi>Deacons</hi> were then counted inferiour to <hi>Presbyters,</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cause they were Ordained with less <hi>Solemnities,</hi> and fewer <hi>Ceremonies;</hi> surely we have here the self same reason to think <hi>Presbyters</hi> inferiour to <hi>Bishops.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Fourthly, in those <hi>Primitive</hi> times, <hi>Bishops</hi> alone were allowed to confer <hi>holy Orders,</hi> or ordain <hi>Ecclesiastical Ministers,</hi> as evidently ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peareth by the constant practice of <hi>Christs Church</hi> since the very begin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning of <hi>Christianity:</hi> I First, our Saviour himself, who is <hi>the Shepherd and Bishop of our souls,</hi> 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 2.25. while he conversed here upon earth, ordained first his twelve <hi>Apostles,</hi> then his seventy <hi>Disciples, Luke</hi> 9.1. and 10.1. and after our <hi>Saviours</hi> time, the <hi>Apostles</hi> (who were also <hi>Bishops, Acts</hi> 1.20.) either Ordained <hi>Presbyters</hi> and <hi>Deacons</hi> in those <hi>Churches</hi> they converted to the Christian Faith, <hi>Acts</hi> 6.6. and 14.23. or appointed others, whom they invested with <hi>Episcopal</hi> Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority to Ordain them; this appears by St. <hi>Pauls</hi> Epissle to <hi>Titus,</hi> (who was the first Bishop of <hi>Crete,</hi> as all Antiquity and particularly <hi>Eusebius</hi> in his Ecclesiastical History, <hi>lib.</hi> 3. <hi>c.</hi> 4. and our own <hi>Bibles,</hi> at the end of the aforesaid Epistle do testifie) where the <hi>Apostle</hi> saith, he left <hi>Titus</hi> in that Island, purposely to Ordain <hi>Elders</hi> in every City, <hi>Ti<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>.</hi> 1.5. But to what purpose (think you) should St. <hi>Paul</hi> leave <hi>Titus</hi> in <hi>Crete</hi> to Ordain <hi>Elders,</hi> if every inferiour <hi>Presbyter</hi> could per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>form this duty? Was there no <hi>Presbyter</hi> in <hi>Crete</hi> but <hi>Titus</hi> alone? or if there were, why did not he enjoyn them to Ordain those <hi>Elders,</hi> or at least joyn them in Commission with <hi>Titus?</hi> Moreover, if single
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:204734:15"/>
                  <hi>Presbyters</hi> had power to ordain <hi>Clergy men</hi> in the Apostles time, how came they to lose this Authority in ensuing Ages? Is it not evident that all antient Writers always attribute Ordinations onely to Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>shops? nay, they thought this power so inseparable from them, that they held it the chiefest; and sometimes in comparison the sole <hi>Prero<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rogative</hi> belonging to the <hi>Episcopal</hi> Function, and much insisted upon this point, in proving the preheminence of <hi>Bishops</hi> above <hi>Presbyters,</hi> and all other <hi>Ecclesiastical</hi> Ministers, which had not the power of Ordination. See <hi>Conc. Antioch. cap.</hi> 10. <hi>Ancyran. cap.</hi> 12: <hi>Ambrose, Chrysostom, Theodoret,</hi> and <hi>Theophylect, in</hi> 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 3 <hi>&amp;</hi> 3 <hi>Hiero. ep.</hi> 85. <hi>ad Evagr. Epiphan. Haer.</hi> 75. <hi>Aug in Breviculo, collat.</hi> 3. <hi>c.</hi> 5. <hi>Damas. ep.</hi> 3. <hi>de Chorepiscopis. Leo ep.</hi> 88. and many others. St. <hi>Hierom,</hi> though a great Patron to <hi>Presbyters,</hi> and a zealous maintainer of their just priviledges, yet confesseth <hi>Bishops</hi> alone had the power of Ordina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion. <hi>What doth a Bishop do,</hi> (saith he) <hi>except Ordination, that a Pres<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>byter may not do? Ep.</hi> 85. <hi>ad Evagr.</hi> And St. <hi>Chrysostom</hi> likewise, <hi>Hom.</hi> 11. <hi>in</hi> 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 3. saith, <hi>Between a Bishop and a Presbyter almost there is no difference, for to Presbyters also the care of the Church is per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted; and what he said of Bishops do agree also to Presbyters, for by Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dination onely the Bishops are their Superiours, and this alone they seem to have more than Presbyters.</hi> St. <hi>Ambrose</hi> also in 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 3. saith, <hi>A Bishop and a Presbyter have one Ordination, and each of them is a Priest; but the Bishop is first, so that every Bishop is a Presbyter, but not every Presbyter a Bishop, for he is Bishop that is first among the Presbyters. Finally he signifieth, that</hi> Timothy <hi>was ordained Presbyter, yet because he had none before him, he was a Bishop, and therefore he shews him how he may Ordain a Bishop; for it was neither just nor lawful, that an Inferiour should Ordain his Superiour, for none gives what he hath not received. How is it possible</hi> (saith St. <hi>Epiphanius, Haer.</hi> 75.) <hi>that he should Ordain a Presbyter, who hath no right of laying on his hands to Ordain, or say that he is equal to a Bishop?</hi> And the <hi>Council</hi> of <hi>Laodicea,</hi> held <hi>Anno</hi> 320. <hi>cap.</hi> 26. expresly declareth, <hi>That such as are not Ordinaed by Bishops, cannot exercise (&amp; a fortiori,</hi> administer the Sacraments) <hi>either in Churches or Houses.</hi> And likewise the <hi>Council</hi> of <hi>Ancyra, cap.</hi> 12. (<hi>anno</hi> 314.) saith, <hi>That it is not lawful for Chorepiscopi's to Ordain Priests or Deacons.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>But <hi>Demasus</hi> Bishop of <hi>Rome,</hi> contemporary to St. <hi>Hierom,</hi> ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>presly declares Ordinations given by single Presbyters not onely <hi>un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lawful,</hi> but also <hi>void</hi> and <hi>null</hi> from the beginning, for in his Third <hi>Epistle,</hi> speaking of the aforesaid <hi>Ecclesiastical</hi> Persons, called <hi>Chorepiscopi,</hi> who though no Bishops, but onely their Substitutes, or Vicar-Generals,
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:204734:16"/>presumed as <hi>Bishops</hi> to Ordain others <hi>Presbyters</hi> and <hi>Deacons</hi>) he writes in this manner, <hi>Whatsoever they have done in the aforesaid Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nistery of High-Priesthood, it is void and null.</hi> Neither is this a new-found Paradox, or a private opinion of this Bishop, but rather so undoubted a Doctrine, that the invincible <hi>Antagonist</hi> of the <hi>Arians,</hi> the great <hi>Athanasius</hi> insisted upon it in the Council of <hi>Tyre,</hi> (where he was sur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rounded by all his enemies, as a <hi>Lamb</hi> among so many <hi>Lions</hi>) and used it as an uncontrollable argument against the malice of the wicked <hi>Ischyras,</hi> who pretending himself a <hi>Presbyter,</hi> Ordained by <hi>Colluthus</hi> a pretended <hi>Bishop,</hi> falsly accused this <hi>Champion</hi> of Christ with breaking the Cup, wherein himself administred the holy <hi>Communion;</hi> which ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lumny St. <hi>Athanasius</hi> openly confuted, by proving, that <hi>Ischyras</hi> was no true <hi>Presbyter,</hi> as not being ordained by a true <hi>Bishop,</hi> and conse<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quently could not administer that <hi>Sacrament.</hi> This passage is related by St. <hi>Athanasius</hi> himself, in his second <hi>Apology,</hi> where he speaks in this manner, <hi>The Priest that is pretended to have been present, is that so often spoken of</hi> Ischyras, <hi>who was neither chosen Presbyter by the Church, nor when</hi> Alexander <hi>received the Prethyters Ordained by</hi> Miletius, <hi>was he ever counted in that number, nor by him created. How then is</hi> Ischyras <hi>a Presbyter, or by whom was he Ordained? Was he Ordained by</hi> Collu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thus? <hi>for that is the onely shift now remaining; but that</hi> Colluthus <hi>died in the degree of Presbytery, and that all his imposition of hands were an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nulled, and all those that were Ordained by him reduced into the Order of Laicks, and under the name of Laicks admitted to the Communion, is so manifest a thing, that none can doubt thereof.</hi> And again in the same Apology, <hi>They suborned one</hi> Ischyras, <hi>a man that was no Priest, though he boasted of that name, for he was Ordained by one</hi> Colluthus, <hi>not a true, but an imaginary Bishop, who in a General Council was commanded by</hi> Osius <hi>and other Bishops then present, that he should be have himself onely as a Presbyter as he was before; and therefore all those that were Ordained by him, returned unto their own antient state, among whom</hi> Ischyras <hi>also is to be counted.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Now the force of this Argument confists not in the single testimony of St. <hi>Athanasius,</hi> though that same (in my opinion) ought to be pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferred before the Chymera's of <hi>John Calvin,</hi> and a million of his <hi>Myr<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>midons;</hi> but it principally consists in these two points: The first is, That he produces a <hi>General Council,</hi> which likely may be the <hi>Nieene,</hi> to make good his assertion. The second is, That if this Doctrine had not been then unanimously received, as well by the <hi>Heterodox</hi> as by the <hi>Orthodox</hi> Believers, and consequently by all <hi>Christians</hi> in general, the <hi>Arrians,</hi> who left no stone unremov'd to confute their great <hi>An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tagonist,</hi>
                  <pb n="29" facs="tcp:204734:16"/>would soon overthrow St. <hi>Athanasius</hi> his Plea, and tell him, (as <hi>Presbyterians</hi> now would do) <hi>Ischyras</hi> was a true <hi>Presbyter,</hi> though not Ordained by any Bishop, because single Presbyters could lawfully Ordain.</p>
               <p>To all these pressing arguments, which are enough to convince any man not wilfully blind, or possess'd with the spirit of contradiction, we may add another insoluble <hi>demonstration ad hominem,</hi> out of our ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>versaries own concessions. For <hi>Presbyteri<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ns</hi> cannot deny, but that the <hi>Sabbath</hi> was <hi>Jure Divino</hi> transferr'd from the Seventh to the First day of the Week; it being unlawful for any earthly power to alter what <hi>God</hi> has so solemnly establish'd in the old Law: And likewise they cannot deny, but that <hi>Infants</hi> are <hi>Jure Divine</hi> capable of <hi>Baptism:</hi> Yet I defie any <hi>Presbyterian</hi> upon earth to shew better proofs for either of these tenets, than I have shew'd hither to for the Superiority of <hi>Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>shops</hi> above <hi>Presbyters.</hi> For the grounds of all these points is holy <hi>Scripture,</hi> not solely or simply taken, but as interpreted by the <hi>univer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sal</hi> practice and tradition of <hi>Christs Church</hi> since the beginning of <hi>Christianity:</hi> why then <hi>(good Presbyterians)</hi> should not these grounds prove the latter to be <hi>Jure Divino,</hi> as well as the former? or by what authority do you presume to admit the one, and reject the other?</p>
               <p>If you insist upon <hi>Scripture</hi> alone in maintaining either <hi>Paedobaptism</hi> or the translation of the <hi>Sabbath,</hi> you shall thereby gain no more, but make your selves a laughing-stock to all learned and Judicious men. For as to the observation of <hi>Sunday,</hi> it is so obscurely delivered in the new <hi>Testament,</hi> (and the old is diametrically against it) that thereby you cannot convince any opposer whatsoever; the places alledged for it, are these that follow: <hi>Ʋpon the first day of the Week the Disciples came together to break Bread.</hi> Acts 20.27. <hi>Ʋpon the first day of the Week let every one lay by him in store,</hi> &amp;c. 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 16.2. <hi>I was in Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit on the Lords Day.</hi> Revel. 1.10. Yet none of all these texts can con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vince the <hi>Sabbath</hi> to have been lawfully translated from <hi>Saturday</hi> to <hi>Sunday.</hi> For to the first it may be answered, that as the Disciples broke Bread upon the first day of the week, so (no doubt) they did sometimes upon every day of the week, as appeareth <hi>Acts</hi> 2.46. and therefore we cannot conclude hence the change of the <hi>Sabbath</hi> to the first, rather than to any other day. The second likewise proves no more but that the <hi>Apostle</hi> adviseth the <hi>Corinthians</hi> to begin the week with an Act of <hi>Charity,</hi> laying aside then some relief for their oppressed Bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thren. And moreover, it is observable, that in both these places the Original Greek hath not, <hi>the first day of the week,</hi> but <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>,
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:204734:17"/>one of the Sabbaths, which renders the matter yet more obscure, and less decidable by <hi>Scripture.</hi> As for the last, it may be said, that every day is the <hi>Lords Day,</hi> and yet some are so called, because something remarkable relating to God happens in those days. Thus the <hi>Day of Judgment</hi> is called the <hi>Lords Day,</hi> Mal. 4.5. and 1 Thes. 5.2. and 2 Pet. 3.10. yet no man, I think, can affirm, that it falls upon <hi>Sunday.</hi> And in this sense the day spoken of by St. <hi>John,</hi> might well be called the <hi>Lords Day</hi> tho' not <hi>Sunday,</hi> because of the mani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fold Mysteries, which God was pleased then to reveal to his beloved Disciple.</p>
               <p>Now as to the second point, so far it is from being warranted by any express <hi>Scripture,</hi> that the ancient Writers do commonly hold it only as an <hi>Apostolical</hi> Tradition. <hi>The Church</hi> (saith <hi>Origenes) receiv'd as a tradition from the Apostles to give Baptism even to Children,</hi> lib. 5. in c. 6 ep. ad Rom. And St. <hi>Augustin</hi> saith in like manner: <hi>The custom of our Mother the Church in Baptizing Children, is not at all to be despised, nor by any means to be counted superfluous, nor yet to be believed, unless it were an Apostolical Tradition,</hi> lib. 10. de Gen c. 23. And as for those passages of <hi>Scripture,</hi> which are commonly produced for <hi>Paedo-baptism,</hi> as the example of <hi>Circumcision, Christ</hi>'s receiving little Children, and the <hi>Apostles</hi> Baptizing whole Families; tho' together with the <hi>universal</hi> tradition and <hi>practice</hi> of the whole <hi>Church</hi> since our <hi>Saviour</hi>'s Ascen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sion, they are indeed sufficient grounds for this custom, yet solely ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken by themselves alone, they cannot satisfie or convince any inquisitive man. For to the example of <hi>Circumcision,</hi> it may be soon answered, that <hi>Baptism</hi> doth necessarily presuppose Faith, which <hi>Circumcision</hi> did not: For in the Old Testament it was not said, <hi>Teach and Circum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cise,</hi> or <hi>He that believeth and is Circumcised,</hi> &amp;c. as it was said in the New, <hi>Teach all Nations, Baptizing them,</hi> &amp;c. Matth. 28.19. <hi>He that believeth and is Baptized shall be saved, but he that believeth not, shall be damned,</hi> Mark 16.16. Wherefore tho' children could be circumcised in the Old Law, <hi>Gen.</hi> 17.12. Yet this proves not that we ought now to administer unto them the Sacrament of <hi>Baptism,</hi> which seemeth always to presuppose Divine <hi>Faith,</hi> whereof infants are uncapable, because they have <hi>no knowledg between Good and Evil,</hi> Deut. 1.39. And likewise to our <hi>Saviour</hi>'s words; <hi>Suffer little Children to come unto me, and forbid them not: For of such is the Kingdom of God.</hi> Mark 10.14. It may be answer'd, first, that <hi>Christ</hi> admitted <hi>Publicans</hi> and sinners to come unto him, which yet could not be lawfully Baptiz'd without true Faith and Repentance; 2ly, that these Children, whereof our Saviour speaketh, were Circumcised, and consequently were in effect
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:204734:17"/>Baptiz'd according to the Rites of the Old Law. And as to those pas<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sages, where whole families are said to have been Baptiz'd, <hi>Acts</hi> 16.15, 33. and 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 1.16. It cannot be deny'd, but it is probable there were some infants in those families; yet here we do not look for pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bable guesses, but for undeniable testimonies: for since it is evident, that Children cannot actually believe, Deut. 1.39. and that holy Scripture in several places expresly requireth saith in such as are to be Baptiz'd, <hi>Mark</hi> 16.16. <hi>Acts</hi> 8.37 I think, probable conjec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures can be no sufficient warrant for us to do any thing so apparently repugnant to holy Scripture.</p>
               <p>It is plain therefore, that neither <hi>Paedo-baptism,</hi> nor the translation of the <hi>Sabbath</hi> can ever be proved by Scripture alone; all these texts are so ambiguous and uncertain, that had they not been confirmed by the constant practice and tradition of the Church in all Ages (which un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doubtedly is the best gloss and comment we can find on Gods word) we could never be assured of either of these tenets, or convince any op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poser of their verity.</p>
               <p>Now it is evident by all Antiquity, that nothing could be more uni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>versally practiced, than the Superiority and Jurisdiction of <hi>Bishops</hi> a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bove <hi>Presbyters</hi> have been in the <hi>Primitive Church;</hi> and withall it is manifest, that this practice is as much grounded on Holy Scripture, as either of the aforesaid tenets: Why then should we not conclude <hi>Epis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>copacy</hi> to be <hi>Jure Divino</hi> above <hi>Presbytery,</hi> as well as the Presbyterians hold Infants to be <hi>Jure Divino</hi> capable of Baptism, and the <hi>Sabbath</hi> to have been in like manner Translated from Saturday to Sun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>day?</p>
               <p>But our holy Brethren have got an invincible Argument to oppose against all these unanswerable Authorities, and what is this, but their own new-found <hi>Gloss</hi> upon St. <hi>Paul</hi>'s ambiguous words; the Apostle (say they) declares, that <hi>Timothy</hi> was ordained by <hi>Presbyters,</hi> when he saith, <hi>Neglect not the gift that is in thee, which was given thee by Prophe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sie, with the laying on of the hands of the Presbytery,</hi> 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 4.14. But this is a new-found <hi>Gloss</hi> indeed, for no antient Writer, if not <hi>Aerius</hi> and his <hi>Sticklers,</hi> ever dreamt thereof before <hi>John Calvin</hi> and his illu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minated Sectaries, have found it out by a new <hi>Revelation.</hi> St. <hi>Hierom,</hi> by those words, <hi>with the laying on of the hands of the Presbytery,</hi> understands the hands, whereby <hi>Timothy</hi> received the Order of Presbytery or Priesthood.</p>
               <p>St. <hi>Chrysostom, Theodoret,</hi> and others, do understand it of <hi>Bishops,</hi> to whom alone it belonged to confer <hi>Ecclesiastical Orders.</hi> But how<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever it be interpreted, certain it is, that <hi>Timothy</hi> was never Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dained
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:204734:18"/>by single <hi>Presbyters,</hi> St. <hi>Paul</hi> expresly affirming he consecrated him himself, where he saith, <hi>Stir up the gift of God which is in thee, by the putting on of my hands,</hi> 2 <hi>Tim.</hi> 1.6. Wherefore if by <hi>Presbytery</hi> we understand the persons that were <hi>Presbyters,</hi> whether single <hi>Presbyters</hi> or <hi>Bishops,</hi> and not the Order of <hi>Presbytery</hi> or <hi>Priesthood,</hi> as St. <hi>Hierom</hi> expounds it, we must understand it not of any <hi>Presbyters</hi> Ordaining or Consecrating <hi>Timothy,</hi> whereas the <hi>Apostle</hi> himself was his Conse<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crator, but of such as assisted at his Ordination, who according to the aforesaid Second and Third Canon of the Fourth <hi>Council</hi> of <hi>Carthage,</hi> were, together with the Consecrator, to lay their hands on the head of the Person Ordained <hi>Presbyter</hi> or <hi>Bishop.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Our godly <hi>Gospellers</hi> have one Objection more, if yet it deserves that name, against <hi>Episcopal</hi> Jurisdiction, or rather against the undue exercise thereof. The fourth <hi>Council</hi> of <hi>Carthage</hi> (say they) has de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creed, <hi>cap.</hi> 23. <hi>That no Bishop, without the assistance of his Clergy, should hear or determine Ecclesiastical Causes, otherwise the Bishops Sentence should be void and null, unless it were confirmed by the presence of his Clergy.</hi> But what can this make for our <hi>Presbyterian Democracy,</hi> or against the Superiority of <hi>Bishops</hi> to be <hi>de Jure Divino,</hi> which is the chiefest Point controverted between us, I cannot in the least compre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hend. As for our part, we always acknowledge, that since the begin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning of <hi>Christianity, Bishops</hi> had commonly about them many of their ablest <hi>Priests</hi> and <hi>Divines,</hi> as it were their <hi>Spiritual Privy Counsellers,</hi> to consult about <hi>Ecclesiastical</hi> matters, without whose consent and approbation, they seldom transacted any matters of moment, even as <hi>Kings</hi> and <hi>Princes</hi> seldom transact matters of <hi>State</hi> without consulting their <hi>Privy Council.</hi> Thus St. <hi>Cyprian</hi> saith, himself was accustomed to use the advice of his <hi>Priests</hi> and Learned <hi>Clergy</hi> in exercising his <hi>Ecclesiastical</hi> Function, and ordering the affairs of his Church. Yet this argues no more the <hi>parity</hi> of Priests and Bishops, than the aforesaid custom of Princes proves the equality of Kings and Privy Counsellers. Nay further, though Bishops could not determine <hi>Ecclesiastical</hi> matters without the advice and consent of at least the major part of their <hi>Clergy,</hi> yet it should not immediately follow, that they are both of equal power, either of <hi>Order</hi> or <hi>Jurisdiction;</hi> even as many <hi>Kings</hi> of <hi>Europe</hi> can neither make new <hi>Laws,</hi> nor repeal the old, without the assent of the <hi>States</hi> of their <hi>Kingdoms,</hi> yet are far above any of these <hi>States</hi> in power and authority. Likewise <hi>Judges</hi> in <hi>England</hi> can sel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom give sentence of death against any man, without the assent and verdict of the Jury, and yet the Jury is not of equal power and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mission with the Judges in deciding such capital crimes.</p>
               <pb n="33" facs="tcp:204734:18"/>
               <p>Wherefore we say (as it hath been already proved) that <hi>Bishops</hi> are truely superiour to their <hi>Clergy,</hi> and have power from <hi>Christ</hi> to rule and govern both the Flock and Pastors together. Yet we confess, they must not rule arbitrarily, or domineer over their inferiours; <hi>not being Lords</hi> (as St. <hi>Peter</hi> saith) <hi>over Gods heritage, but being ensamples to the flock,</hi> 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 5.3. surpassing the inferiour Clergy in humility, as they exceed them in dignity; for as our Saviour saith to his Apostles, <hi>The Princes of the Gentiles exercise dominion over them, and they that are great exercise authority upon them. But it shall not be so among you; but who<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>soever will be great among you, let him be your minister; and whosoever will be chief among you, let him be your servant. Even as the Son of man came not to be ministred unto, but to minister, and to give his life a ransome for many, Matth.</hi> 20.25, 26, 27, 28. But if the <hi>Apostles</hi> were not allowed to exercise any arbitrary or domineering power over <hi>Christians,</hi> with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out doubt Bishops, who are but the Apostles Successors, have no right to do it; yet this hindereth not, but they may use their Spiritual Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority against obstinate and rebellious persons, who (like <hi>Corah</hi> and his Accomplices pretending an Arbitrary Government in <hi>Moses</hi> and <hi>Aaron, Numb.</hi> 16.3.) insolently depart from their lawful Pastors and Superiors, making themselves Ring leaders of Schismatical Factions; for in this case they may say with the Apostles, <hi>The weapons of our warfare are not carnal, but mighty through God, to the pulling down of strong holds; casting down imaginations and every high thing that exalteth it self against the knowledg of God, and bringing into Captivity every thought to the obedience of Christ,</hi> 2 Cor. 10.4, 5.</p>
               <p>Having thus examined <hi>(Good Presbyterians)</hi> the pretended grounds of your <hi>separation</hi> from our <hi>Church</hi> and <hi>Communion,</hi> I appeal now to your own consciences, if the <hi>Independent Presbyterians</hi> had not as much reason as you can here produce, to depart from your <hi>fraternity,</hi> and the <hi>Quakers, Levellers,</hi> and all those <hi>Leviathan</hi> monsters (which like <hi>Mushrooms</hi> sprung up in the late confusion) to depart from the <hi>In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dependents.</hi> Shew me I beseech you, some reason or authority war<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ranting the one, and condemning the other. Shew me but one express text of <hi>Scripture,</hi> or one true president of antiquity for your <hi>Presbyteri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an Democracy,</hi> and I will be of your <hi>Communion.</hi> In the interim, I beg of you impartially to consider, how desperate is your condition, and upon what <hi>groundless</hi> grounds you separate your selves from the <hi>Mother Church.</hi> Do not think that your usual pretence of differing from her, not in any necessary point of faith (as you say) but only in some inferi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>or truths and few ceremonies, can justify your departing from her <hi>Communion.</hi> For undoubtedly, the less you dissent from her in Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine,
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:204734:19"/>the more you are to be suspected of the heinous crime of <hi>Schism,</hi> which is commonly defined by learned men, <hi>A wilful Separation from the Communion of a Christian Society without any sufficient cause.</hi> If there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore you dissent from the <hi>Church</hi> of <hi>England</hi> only in outward Ceremo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nies, and some few unnecessary points of Doctrine; surely, you have no sufficient cause to forsake her <hi>Communion;</hi> since in reason nothing less than a damnable and intolerable error either in faith or manners, can warrant us to disobey our Superiors, whom by the express word of God we are indispensably obliged to obey, <hi>Heb.</hi> 13.17. How then can you justifie your departure from the <hi>Obedience</hi> of your lawfull <hi>Bishops,</hi> or clear your selves from the brand of <hi>Schism,</hi> if you differ from them only in such trivial points of <hi>Religion?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Do but consider a little, what unspeakable miseries this your separa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion has caused this 100 years past in this Island of Great <hi>Britain.</hi> What factions, what divisions, what massacres it occasioned among us? how strangely it weaken'd our Government both Spiritual and Temporal, and encouraged our enemies so often to design our ruine, they knowing that <hi>a Kingdom divided against it self, is easily brought to desolation?</hi> Matth. 12.25. What <hi>Locusts</hi> of unheard off Sectaries it produced, to the apparent ruine of so many seduced souls? Our <hi>Muggletonians, Qua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kers, Levellers, Brownists,</hi> and a numberless number of other <hi>Apocalyptical Enthusiasts,</hi> we must chiefly atribute to your pretended refining of the <hi>Reformation;</hi> for by your example they perswaded themselves, they might as well reform your <hi>Gospel,</hi> as you pretend to reform the <hi>Church</hi> of <hi>England.</hi> Consider, I say, this <hi>deluge</hi> of mischief brought upon your native <hi>Country,</hi> through your groundless separation and disobe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dience to your lawful Pastors, and tell me, what good has your preten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded <hi>Holy Discipline</hi> ever done to the <hi>Church</hi> of <hi>Christ,</hi> to countervail these woful calamities? Or do you think, it is possible, that such a <hi>dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipline</hi> should be of God, which upon such trivial pretences is the occa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sion of so much trouble and confusion?</p>
               <p>Wherefore, <hi>Good and well-meaning Presbyterians</hi> (for such to be among you I must in charity believe, and with such only I have any hopes to prevail) if you expect the blessing of God, and the love of the <hi>Church</hi> of <hi>England,</hi> or if you desire not to be reputed, as well as Papists, sworn enemies to all <hi>Episcopal</hi> Protestants, lay aside this Spirit of contradicti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, and since the <hi>Prophet</hi> assures us, that <hi>to obey is beter than Sacrifice,</hi> 1 Sam. 15.22. <hi>Obey you them that have rule over you</hi> (as the Apostle speaketh, <hi>Heb.</hi> 13.17.) <hi>and submit your selves</hi> to those, who by the Laws of the Land, by the Canons of so many ancient <hi>Councils,</hi> and the universal uninterrupted custom of the <hi>Church</hi> of God since the <hi>Apostles</hi>
                  <pb n="35" facs="tcp:204734:19"/>time, are appointed your Pastors and Prelates to direct and guide you in spiritual matters. Forsake these factious <hi>Ring leaders,</hi> who make you but Asses for themselves to ride upon in state, and therefore to make themselves great, mind nothing but Sedition and Rebellion, tho' to you they pretend but <hi>Religion</hi> and <hi>Liberty,</hi> using (as St. <hi>Peter</hi> spea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth) <hi>their liberty for a Cloak of Maliciousness,</hi> 1 Pet. 2.16. like these wicked <hi>hypocrites</hi> described by <hi>Leo</hi> the great, ep. 23. in these words: <hi>Private designs are carryed on under the pretence of piety, and every one has Religion as the Handmaid of his ambition.</hi> For (as our <hi>Royal Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tyr</hi> elegantly saith) <hi>It is no news to have all inovations usher'd in with the name of Reformations in Church and State, by those, who seeking to gain reputation with the vulgar for their extraordinary parts and piety, must needs undo what ever was formerly setled, never so well and wisely;</hi> in his Eikon Basilike, c 16. <hi>For I have observed</hi> (saith he again c. 27.) <hi>that the Devil of Rebellion doth commonly turn himself into an Angel of Reformation; and the Old Serpent can pretend new lights. When some mens consciences accuse them of sedition and faction, they stop its mouth with the name and noise of Religion.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Forsake you therefore such counterfeit <hi>Religionaries,</hi> and take notice of what the <hi>Angel</hi> said to <hi>Hagar</hi> in the Desert; <hi>Return to thy Mistriss, and submit thy self under her hands;</hi> Gen. 16.9. Return you to the <hi>Church</hi> of <hi>England,</hi> and if you intend to escape out of the <hi>Desert</hi> of <hi>Schism,</hi> sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit to her Laws and Ordinances; she will receive you with as much tenderness and affection, as the <hi>Father</hi> embraced his <hi>Prodigal</hi> Son in the <hi>Gospel,</hi> Luke 15.20.</p>
               <p>By this you shall fully clear your selves of all imputations of <hi>Schism</hi> and innovations, and shall avoid all future suspicions of contriving a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny <hi>Stratagems</hi> to ruine your native <hi>Country,</hi> or subvert the <hi>Government</hi> either of <hi>Church</hi> or <hi>State;</hi> you shall strengthen the <hi>Protestant</hi> interest both at home and abroad, be a means by degrees to suppress <hi>Popery</hi> and all those mushrums of <hi>Christianity,</hi> that spring up among us, and procure to your selves peace and quietness both in this World and in the World to come; which <hi>God</hi> of his mercy Grant us all; <hi>Amen.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <pb n="36" facs="tcp:204734:20"/>
               <head>An Advertisement to all true Protestants.</head>
               <opener>
                  <salute>
                     <hi>My beloved</hi> Countrymen <hi>of the</hi> Church <hi>of</hi> England</salute>
               </opener>
               <p>AS I have undertaken both this and the former treatise for your sakes, to make you sensible of the <hi>Presbyterians</hi> impostures, and deceitful contrivances against our <hi>Church</hi> and <hi>State;</hi> so now I hum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly dedicate and recommend them to your serious considerations. Truly I have been always very loath to rub up these old sores, which have so lately cost us so much Money and Bloud, to the draining both of Purse and Veins, or mention those monstrous <hi>Tragedies</hi> which with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in the memory of man have been acted upon the Stage of this unfortu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nate Island; and had people now been as unwilling to tread the steps of their predecessors, as I am to rake up those cursed Cindars, the world should be troubled neither with my papers, nor their frenzies. But for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>asmuch as there are at present such certain signs and symptoms appa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rently to be read in the words and actions of some discontented <hi>Relig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ionaries,</hi> that whosoever hath but eyes to see, may apprehend some fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tal <hi>Apoplexy</hi> to be near at hand: I think it no less than our interest, timely to look about us, least we be again surpriz'd by these politick <hi>Machiavels,</hi> who unless prudently prevented by those who sit at the Helm, I am afraid, will once more attempt to restore their so much long'd for Common-wealth.</p>
               <p>Yet this, I do not say, is (at least directly) intended by the generali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, nor yet the major part of that faction. I doubt not, but there are, and have always been, even in that Communion some vertuous and godly men, who were rather moved by an ignorant <hi>Zeal</hi> and the pesti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent influence of their <hi>Ring-leaders,</hi> to commit those prodigious actions, than of themselves any thing inclined to act such abominable wicked<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ness. Wherefore, I think it is the duty of all Charitable <hi>Protestants,</hi> to distinguish, as far as possible, between a misled <hi>Presbyterian</hi> and a misleading <hi>Factioneer,</hi> and accordingly pity the one, but hate and detest the other. Pity those, who through their credulity and well-meaning <hi>Zeal</hi> are so deludedby their <hi>Primum Mobile's,</hi> that unawares they are forced to act against their inclinations; but hate and curse the rest, whose <hi>Religion</hi> we find by experience is <hi>Rebellion,</hi> whose <hi>Faith</hi> is <hi>Faction,</hi> and whose practice is the <hi>destruction</hi> of <hi>Kings and Kingdoms,</hi> whensoever they find opportunity, and their ability correspondent to their malice: yet still to take heed, and carefully beware of both, vigilantly watch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing over their proceedings, least our carelesness and stupidi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:204734:20"/>may at any time encourage them to attempt our ruine.</p>
               <p>Wherefore, my beloved <hi>Countrymen,</hi> let us consider how as our <hi>Savi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>our</hi> was crucified between two Thieves, so is the <hi>Church</hi> of <hi>England</hi> now endangered between two extrems, the <hi>Presbyterians</hi> and <hi>Papists,</hi> both being equally willing, tho' not equally able to destroy us. The <hi>Papists,</hi> I know, are no less apt than the <hi>Presbyterians,</hi> to commit any treacheries to promote their superstition; but through <hi>Gods</hi> providence, their power now is so weak and inconsiderable, that whensoever they at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempt our ruine, they will but hasten their own; for I dare venture my life, I might with a thousand, nay, 500. armed men destroy all the Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pists in <hi>England</hi> at this present hour. But the <hi>Presbyterians</hi> are so nu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>merous and of such formidable greatness, daily encreasing by our male<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>contents and ambitious grandees, that if not timely prevented by our prudent Magistrates, our Orthodox <hi>Churches</hi> shall be ere long but Cy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phers to their <hi>Schismatical</hi> Conventicles. We see how boldly they speak every where, and especially in their Coffee-houses (those Shops of Sedition and Anvils of Rebellion) against our <hi>Bishops</hi> and <hi>Prelates,</hi> nay, against our <hi>King</hi> and Government, labouring to poyson the short sighted rabble with their seditious libells and pamphlets. They often repeat those <hi>Antimonarchical</hi> expressions of the <hi>Rump-Parliament,</hi> that the King of <hi>England</hi> is entrusted with a limited power, and oblig'd to govern according to the <hi>Laws</hi> of the <hi>Land,</hi> insomuch that they count it a crime of the deepest die for any man to affirm, that the <hi>King</hi> can hinder or suspend the execution of any Law whatsoever; tho' they cannot deny, but that in several occurrences <hi>summum jus</hi> is <hi>summa inju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ria;</hi> whence our late <hi>Sovereign</hi> writing to his present <hi>Majesty,</hi> judici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ously said: <hi>Your prerogative is best shewed and exercised in remitting, rather than exacting the rigour of the Laws; there being nothing worse than legal tyranny.</hi> In his Eicon Basilike, c. 27. And truly, had all the <hi>Laws</hi> formerly enacted and now in force against <hi>Nonconformists,</hi> been now put in execution against the <hi>Presbyterians,</hi> I doubt not, but we should often hear of <hi>Oppresion</hi> and <hi>Tyranical</hi> Government, from these very creatures, who now so vehemently press the execution of the <hi>Laws:</hi> so that we see, it is altogether impossible for any <hi>King</hi> to satis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fie such unsatiable <hi>Republicans,</hi> unless he unkings himself and become a slave to the worst of Subjects.</p>
               <p>And yet notwithstanding all these <hi>Anarchical</hi> contrivances of the <hi>Puritans</hi> they are tolerated, they are countenanced, yea, seconded by persons, who by their places, by their oaths, and by their allegiance are obliged to maintain with the hazard of their lives the prerogatives of the <hi>Crown,</hi> and liberties of the <hi>Church</hi> of <hi>England.</hi> Nay. if we be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:204734:21"/>the <hi>Presbyterians</hi> themselves, they have the chiefest part of the great City of <hi>London</hi> to joyn with them in their great and unsearch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able designs. Yet so incredible a story it is, that the <hi>Londoners,</hi> after their unspeakable losses by the late <hi>Presbyterian</hi> Rebellion, should now countenance, much less promote the like Insurrection, whereby who<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>soever wins, they are sure to be losers, that I admire if any man of fense can give credit to so unlikely a busrness. Is it possible, that this famous <hi>Metropolitan City</hi> should be insensible of all the indignities and losses they sustained by these disloyal <hi>Gospellers?</hi> or forget what vast sums of money were daily squeez'd out of their purses, without any sums of payment? How many thousands of their Children and Ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prentices were pressed for Soldiers, and forced to fight against those very persons, to whom they ow'd their being and education? How can they digest to remember their <hi>Lord Mayor</hi> violently deposed, their <hi>Aldermen</hi> and chiefest <hi>Citizens</hi> barbarously imprisoned by these hellish <hi>Incendiaries,</hi> without any colour of Justice? And, in brief, can any length of time wear out of their memories the inhumane Butcheries committed upon their unarmed <hi>Apprentices</hi> in <hi>Easter,</hi> 1649. when the <hi>Arch-Tyrant Cromwel</hi> himself cried to the Soldiers, <hi>to kill man, woman, and child, and fire the City about their ears?</hi> See the <hi>History of Independency, Part</hi> 1. <hi>page</hi> 49 and 68. and <hi>Part</hi> 2. <hi>page</hi> 150. These and many other indignities cast upon this great and famous <hi>City,</hi> for im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prudently adhering to that <hi>Rebellious Faction,</hi> are so strong in my judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, that I will sooner believe them destitute of all sense and reason, than inclin'd now to prostitute their <hi>Loyalty</hi> to so treacherous a <hi>Party.</hi> 'Tis a common saying. <hi>If a man deceives me once, it is his fault; but if he deceives me again, it is my own.</hi> Wherefore since the <hi>Londoners,</hi> by the <hi>Presbyterians</hi> specious pretences, and promises of Reformation, have been once deluded to side with those <hi>sanctified Brethren,</hi> and have by woful experience found they were deceived; if they should again upon the same grounds engage themselves into the like troubles, surely neither friend nor foe would pity their sufferings, neither God nor man would pardon their treacheries.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Reformation</hi> indeed both in <hi>Church</hi> and <hi>State</hi> is so considerable a Treasure to the <hi>Weal publick,</hi> that he must be reputed a sworn Enemy to <hi>God</hi> and his <hi>Countrey</hi> that would in the least oppose it; yet to en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deavour to introduce it by violent and tumultuous means, or with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out the joynt and free concurrence both of Prince and People, is a <hi>re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>medy</hi> far worse than the <hi>disease,</hi> which will produce nothing but <hi>Anarchy</hi> and <hi>Irreligion.</hi> For even as people talk, that it's easie for <hi>Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jurers</hi> to raise the <hi>Devil,</hi> but to lay or conjure him away, is very hard
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:204734:21"/>and difficult; so, it is very feasible for <hi>factious fellows</hi> to create trou<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>bles and disturbances in a <hi>Kingdom,</hi> but to allay the Tempest, and bring things again to a firm settlement, <hi>hoc opus, hic labor est.</hi> The reason is, because when a body <hi>politick</hi> is once in such a violent com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>motion, it is impossible for people to stand or rest where they designed, the throng will undoubtedly carry them beyond their aim, and at last make them either act against their consciences, or suffer against their wills. This we find true by experience in our late <hi>Tragieal</hi> con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fusion, when I am confident a great many of those, who voted for raising an Army against their Sovereign for to promote their pretended <hi>Reformation</hi> either in <hi>Church</hi> or <hi>State,</hi> never designed to Sacrifice his Sacred person for not consenting to their demand. Yet they were so over-acted by a prevailing party, that even as they did not assist his Majesty when they could, so when they would, it was not in their power to help him, according to that ancient saying:
<q>
                     <l>He that will not, when he may;</l>
                     <l>When he will, he shall have nay.</l>
                  </q>
               </p>
               <p>And yet after all these dismal combustions, which made <hi>England</hi> the Theatre of the Worlds wonder, so far were the three Nations from their promised and expected <hi>Reformation,</hi> that they grew daily worse and worse, and fell at last into all kind of <hi>Libertinism</hi> and <hi>Prophaneness.</hi> Their pretended <hi>Reformers</hi> have indeed made a thorow <hi>Reformation</hi> in the peoples purses, but never endeavour'd to procure it either in <hi>Church</hi> or <hi>Commonwealth,</hi> but rather Crucified both with St. <hi>Peter</hi>'s Crucifixi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the heels upwards and the head downwards. For as for the one, tho' in some sort they cast out the unclean Spirit of <hi>Popery,</hi> yet they brought in not seven (as the <hi>Gospel</hi> speaketh Matth. 12.45.) but rather <hi>Seventy other unclean Spirits, more wicked than the former.</hi> So that this Island was a Pantheon, a Temple for all Gods and Religions. And the other they brought to that pass, that in <hi>April</hi> 1649. after the unparalell'd Murder of their <hi>Sovereign,</hi> people openly said: <hi>We never suffer'd the thousandth part of the oppressions, we now groan under.</hi> And surely, they could not choose, having now instead of one pretended, so many real <hi>Tyrants,</hi> who like the 30. <hi>Tyrants</hi> of <hi>Athens</hi> insolently domi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neer'd over the oppressed people, and Arbitrarily govern'd the whole <hi>Kingdom.</hi> Of whom we may truly say with the <hi>Author</hi> of the History of <hi>Independency,</hi> part 1. p. 140. <hi>These are they, that with</hi> Hananiah <hi>break the wooden-yoke from our necks</hi> (Jer. 28.13.) <hi>and put on a yoke of Iron:
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:204734:22"/>free us from a little Ship-money paid thrice in an Age, and impose as much at once for a Monthly Tax: quit us of the Monopolies of Tobacco, and set up Excise on Bread and Beer. The first easeth the Wanton Rich man, and the later grindeth the needy and poor. Yet these are thy Gods, O</hi> London; <hi>these are the Idol-Calves the people have set up and do worship: These be the Molecs to whom ye Sacrifice Sons and Servants by Troops, Regiments and Armies, to maintaine their Soveraignty, Rebellion and Profit.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Having therefore this woful experience of the dismal consequences mevitably ensuing a violent <hi>Reformation,</hi> can any man be so senseless as to believe that the now <hi>Loyal</hi> as well as <hi>Prudent Citizens</hi> of <hi>London</hi> would side with these counterfeit <hi>Religionaries,</hi> in embroiling the <hi>Kingdom</hi> again in such intestine troubles, as have so lately cost them their reputation, their lives, their liberties and estates? If formerly they, or their predecessors rather; have been so imprudent as to be gulled by the plausible pretences and promises of the <hi>Presbyteri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans,</hi> I hope now they have acquired some Wit by their past ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lamities.</p>
               <p>Yet in one thing, I must confess, I cannot well excuse them from the censures of many judicious men, who admire what may be their reason to suffer so many mutineers and seditious fellows publickly to vent among them their pernicious and pestilent Scriblings, which en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flame the Short-sighted vulgar against the <hi>Government</hi> both Spiritual and Temporal, to the unspeakable reproach of the whole <hi>City,</hi> and imminent danger of the three <hi>Kingdoms.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>It was wisely observed by that ancient Author <hi>Arnobius,</hi> advers. Gentes, c. 4. <hi>Whosoever suffers sinners to sin, addeth strength to their bold<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ness.</hi> And <hi>Seneca,</hi> In <hi>Troade</hi> act 2. <hi>Qui non vetat peccare, cum possit, ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bet.</hi> And before them no less judiciously delivered by the great <hi>States<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man Cicero,</hi> who orat. in Pisonem saith: <hi>It is not much different, especi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally in a Consul or Magistrate, whether he vexeth the Commonwealth him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>self by pernicious Laws and tumultuous Speeches, or suffers others to do it.</hi> What shall we say then of these <hi>Magistrates,</hi> whose duty and office it is to examine such matters, and who daily hear and see the pestilent scriblings of the <hi>Presbyterians,</hi> poysoning the blind rabble with their <hi>Seditious</hi> Libells and Pamphlets (very ominous indeed to this <hi>Kingdom,</hi> if we remember 41.) yet do seldom or never enquire after those facti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous Spirits, but seem rather in a great proportion, either through fear or love, to countenance their insolency, which is already come to that height, that it is altogether intolerable, for tho' the dissembling <hi>hypocrites</hi> pretend to write against the <hi>Papists,</hi> yet insensibly they fall from thence to rail against our <hi>Bishops</hi> and learned <hi>Clergy,</hi> not without
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:204734:22"/>open hints and reflections upon his Sacred Majesties Person and Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment. Their writing against the <hi>Papists</hi> is onely to colour their cursed designs, and if they can but fill our senses with the horrour of the <hi>Popish Plot,</hi> and daily bring us new <hi>alarms</hi> of the <hi>Papists</hi> trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cheries against us, and thereby make us wholly intentive and bent against that Party, their work is done. They are sure to carry on their own designs with such dexterity and smoothness in so fair an opportu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity, that insensibly they may surprise and destroy us. I think there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore in my conscience, it is our interest now so to beware of the plot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting <hi>Papists,</hi> that yet we may have a vigilant eye over the treacherous <hi>Presbyterians,</hi> and narrowly sift and examine their proceedings and pretences, lest at last we find a <hi>Snake</hi> in the grass, as dangerous as that of the <hi>Rump-Parliament,</hi> whose steps our <hi>modern Presbyterians</hi> seem exactly to follow.</p>
               <p>Let not the name of <hi>Protestants,</hi> or <hi>reformed Christians,</hi> nor yet the smalness of our differences in <hi>Religion,</hi> promise us any security from these unsociable <hi>Gospellers,</hi> since we have so lately seen, how the holy Brethren had no sooner overthrown the <hi>common Enemy,</hi> the <hi>Church</hi> of <hi>England,</hi> but they presently fell by the ears among themselves, one <hi>Faction</hi> endeavouring to suppress and destroy the other. So that what the Lord threatned to inflict upon the <hi>Egyptians,</hi> the same he exactly fulfilled in these pretended <hi>Reformists, I will set the Egyptians against the Egyptians, and they shall fight every one against his brother, and every one against his neighbour, City against City, and Kingdom against Kingdom, Isa.</hi> 19.2. But if the <hi>Dependent Presbyterians</hi> were so eager against the <hi>Independents,</hi> who no less than the former stood for the <hi>Presbyterian Discipline,</hi> and differed from them onely in some small Formalities of <hi>Church-Government,</hi> is it possible they should be faithful to the <hi>Church</hi> of <hi>England,</hi> whose Communion they openly censure as <hi>Popish</hi> and <hi>An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tichristian?</hi> Do not we see even in these present times, when we have the Sovereign Authority, and all the Laws of the Land against them, with what stratagems nevertheless they stop the mouths of his Majesties Loyal and Orthodox Subjects? They know, nothing can be more odi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous to <hi>Protestants</hi> than <hi>Popery</hi> and <hi>Popish Superstitions;</hi> nor to a Free<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>born <hi>English Subject;</hi> than <hi>Tyrannical</hi> and <hi>Arbitrary Government;</hi> and whosoever is found endeavouring to introduce either of these two Monsters into this Kingdom, he must undoubtedly be reputed a sworn enemy to the People of <hi>England.</hi> Wherefore because these <hi>Puritaus</hi> chiefest aim and design is, to crush both <hi>Monarchy</hi> and <hi>Episcopacy</hi> under the <hi>Cloak</hi> of <hi>Presbytery:</hi> this plausible pretence they use with such wonderful dexterity, as a two-edged Sword against all their
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:204734:23"/>adversaries and opposers. For if any has the courage to speak in defence of his <hi>Majesty,</hi> or his present <hi>Government,</hi> he is immediately cried down as one disaffected to the <hi>Liberties</hi> of the <hi>English</hi> Nation; nay, as an in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>troducer of <hi>Tyrannical</hi> and <hi>Arbitrary Government;</hi> and then, <hi>God</hi> be merciful to his Soul, for nothing but his downfall must satisfie these bloody <hi>Canibals.</hi> And likewise whosoever presumes to speak for the <hi>Church of England,</hi> or stand in her defence against the <hi>Schismatical Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctaries,</hi> he is presently cri'd down for a <hi>Papist,</hi> or at least <hi>Popishly</hi> in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clin'd, and so exposed to the fury of the blinded Rabble, like those in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nocent <hi>Christians,</hi> exposed by the Tyrant <hi>Nero</hi> to the fury of his Dogs, in the skins of Bears and other savage Beasts; though it is evident to all the world, no Party can be apter to introduce <hi>Papists</hi> and <hi>Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pery,</hi> if they find it for their advantage, than the <hi>Presbyterians</hi> them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>selves.</p>
               <p>We cannot surely forget how earnestly the <hi>Scottish Presbyterians,</hi> and particularly the Lord <hi>Lowdon,</hi> and others of the chief Confede<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rates of that <hi>Kingdom,</hi> in the year 1639, courted the <hi>French King</hi> to favour their proceedings, and grant them his assistance against their <hi>natural Sovereign.</hi> We know what sway <hi>Cardinal Richlieu,</hi> the <hi>French Kings</hi> great Minister of State, bore among these holy <hi>Gospellers,</hi> (who yet pretended to fight for Religion) sending his own <hi>Chaplain</hi> and a number of his chiefest <hi>Jesuits</hi> into <hi>Scotland,</hi> to foment the differences, and exasperate the <hi>Rebels</hi> there. See <hi>Bakers Chron. page</hi> 489.</p>
               <p>How then do we know, but they are swayed by the same Faction even at this present time, and endeavouring to open the Sluces for <hi>Popery,</hi> though they cry Whore first against the <hi>Church</hi> of <hi>England?</hi> Certain it is, the <hi>French King</hi> has now also many active Emissaries to promote his designs, and we may easily guess, it is not the least of his thoughts to inflame this <hi>Kingdom</hi> into a total combustion; nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther can he excogitate fitter instruments for his purpose than those <hi>fiery spirits,</hi> who are, as it were, born to <hi>embroil Kingdoms,</hi> and, like <hi>Ishmael, to have their hand against every man, and every mans hand against them, Gen.</hi> 16.12.</p>
               <p>But they are the most inveterate against the <hi>French King</hi> and his <hi>interest,</hi> how th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> can they be inclin'd to promote his <hi>designs?</hi> They are indeed <hi>inveterate</hi> against him in <hi>some particulars,</hi> but in <hi>others</hi> they joyntly concur; both <hi>Parties</hi> are agreed to <hi>divide</hi> and <hi>inflame</hi> this <hi>Kingdom,</hi> and thereby sacrifice it, the one to his <hi>Tyranny,</hi> and the other to his <hi>Anarchical Democracy.</hi> And this was the reason why the <hi>Presbyterians,</hi> in their late grand Rebellion, so much courted the <hi>French</hi> to their assistance against King <hi>Charles</hi> the first. The truth
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:204734:23"/>is, they are so eagerly bent upon the <hi>abolishing</hi> of <hi>Monarchical Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment</hi> here, that to accomplish their desires, they would not scruple to say with that cursed <hi>Sorceress,</hi>
                  <q>Flectere si nequeo superos, Acheronta movebo.</q>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Monarchy</hi> is a sting that continually galls them, and the onely <hi>yoke</hi> (besides <hi>Episcopacy</hi> and <hi>Gods Commandments</hi>) they think insupportable and inconsistent with their <hi>Christian,</hi> or rather <hi>Antichristian. Liberty.</hi> To be rid therefore of this <hi>bondage,</hi> we need not doubt, they will leave no stone unremoved, no villany unattempted. Yet because this <hi>great Work</hi> can hardly ever be accomplished, except first the <hi>very foundation</hi> of the <hi>present Government</hi> be vigorously shaken, and the <hi>whole frame</hi> put out of joynt, by making this <hi>Kingdom</hi> of an <hi>Hereditary</hi> to become an <hi>Elective Monarchy,</hi> they use all possible arts and artifices to exclude the <hi>right Heir</hi> to the <hi>Crown,</hi> and raise a <hi>King</hi> of their own making, who has no better <hi>Title</hi> to the <hi>Sovereignty</hi> than the <hi>meanest</hi> of themselves, to the end that by what <hi>Power</hi> they should <hi>create</hi> him, they might also <hi>annihilate</hi> him at their pleasure, and thereby banish all <hi>Monarchical Government</hi> (and <hi>Episcopacy</hi> they are sure must consequently vanish) out of this <hi>Island</hi> for ever.</p>
               <p>For the <hi>Person</hi> they now pretend so much to <hi>idolize,</hi> they know is neither of <hi>parts sussicient</hi> to countermine their <hi>contrivances.</hi> nor of <hi>in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terest</hi> able to oppose their <hi>commands,</hi> whensoever they would be plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sed to call him to an account, with a <hi>Redde rationem villications tuae,</hi> and cause him (as formerly they did to <hi>Richard Cromwel</hi>) to come <hi>cap in hand</hi> to his Masters, and acknowledge their <hi>Sovereignty;</hi> in the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terim, he must be reputed the onely <hi>Demi-god</hi> of the <hi>Fanatical Repub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>licans,</hi> who, in <hi>Absolom's</hi> language, whispering in the Peoples ears, de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lude the short sighted Vulgar with a <hi>parturiunt montes</hi> of those <hi>golden days</hi> they promise them are near at hand.</p>
               <q>
                  <l>Postquam, <hi>Saturno</hi> tenebrosa in tartara misso,</l>
                  <l>Sub <hi>Jove</hi> mundo erit.</l>
                  <l>Vivat at ad multos <hi>Carolus</hi> Philadelphius annos.</l>
               </q>
               <p>Yet against these and such other <hi>Serpentine suggestions,</hi> I think it is a sufficient Antidote for any man of <hi>commonsense,</hi> to call to mind what a <hi>deluge of miseries</hi> have since the <hi>Conquest</hi> hapned in this <hi>Island,</hi> by the means of some <hi>ambitious</hi> and <hi>aspiring Spirits.</hi> Surely it is a sufficient <hi>caution</hi> for all prudent men to consider, what an <hi>inundation of English
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:204734:24"/>blood,</hi> what <hi>cruel Massacres</hi> of <hi>innocent Subjects</hi> followed the <hi>Tyrannical Ʋsurpation</hi> of <hi>King Henry</hi> IV. though grounded on his <hi>Predecessors Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>signation,</hi> and confirmed by <hi>Act of Parliament,</hi> as the Learned Bishop of <hi>Carlisle</hi> judiciously foretold, and as magnanimously endeavoured to prevent. And to come to matters of later date, and no less to our purpose, certainly the <hi>dismal combustions</hi> occasioned in <hi>Scotland</hi> by the wicked Earl of <hi>Murray</hi> alone, should be warning enough for all en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>suing Ages; this man, though but <hi>Bastard Son</hi> to <hi>King James</hi> V. yet alledged his Mother was married to the King, and thereby pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended a <hi>Title</hi> to the <hi>Crown,</hi> which to snatch from Queen <hi>Mary</hi> of <hi>Scotland</hi>'s Head, first opened a sluce to the <hi>Genevesian Incendiaries,</hi> who upon a sudden so infected the People with <hi>Puritanism,</hi> and conse<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quently with the spirit of <hi>Anarchy</hi> and <hi>disobedience,</hi> that they could never since be fully reduced to a due temper of <hi>Reformation,</hi> or firm <hi>Loyalty;</hi> and then he raised almost the whole <hi>Kingdom</hi> in open <hi>Rebel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lion</hi> against their <hi>Sovereign,</hi> though at last, through the just judgment of God, to his <hi>own ruine</hi> and <hi>destruction.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Shall we therefore be so imprudent, as to <hi>connive</hi> or <hi>approve</hi> of the like <hi>proceedings now,</hi> contrary to his <hi>Majesties</hi> express will, contrary to the safety both of himself and all his <hi>Subjects,</hi> and withall contrary to all <hi>Laws</hi> both <hi>Humane</hi> and <hi>Divine?</hi> Shall we forsake the <hi>true Temple of God,</hi> and go <hi>worship</hi> the <hi>Golden Calf of Jeroboam?</hi> exclude the <hi>Right Heir</hi> to the <hi>Crown,</hi> and set up an <hi>Idol,</hi> chosen by <hi>Fanaticks,</hi> not for any love to his Person, nor his Policy or Prudence in State affairs, nor yet for his Zeal for Religion, but meerly to make a <hi>Tool</hi> of him to drive on their own mysterious designs, and thereby undo both himself and the whole Nation before he is aware of their contrivances; to which pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pose, the <hi>hypocritical Zealots</hi> do so applaud and extoll him daily, as if he had been the <hi>spring</hi> of all our <hi>happiness,</hi> (God send the <hi>Puritans</hi> make him not the contrary, to his <hi>own</hi> and <hi>others ruine</hi>) and the onely hopes of the <hi>three Kingdoms.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>But of his <hi>R. H.</hi> they give such strange and monstrous <hi>representa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions,</hi> that it is unconceivable to any, not acquainted with the <hi>Presby<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terians,</hi> what the malice of man can do: Nothing but Queen <hi>Mary's days,</hi> nothing but <hi>Fire and Faggot</hi> must serve their turn, to frighten the poor people out of their <hi>little wits,</hi> and make them believe they are already at the Stake in <hi>Smithfield.</hi> And to what purpose is all this? Why, they know his <hi>R. H.</hi> is of that profound Wisdom, and Heroick Spirit, that it is impossible for them to <hi>out-reach</hi> or <hi>out-wit</hi> him in any of their <hi>Antimonarchical undertakings,</hi> nor yet impose upon his <hi>Sacred Majesty,</hi> while his <hi>R. H.</hi> is near at hand to dissipate the Rebellious
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:204734:24"/>Councels of such <hi>Abitophels.</hi> And because they perceive there is no aspersion more odious among <hi>Protestants,</hi> nor more difficult to be wi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ped off, than the imputation of <hi>Popery;</hi> this charge the <hi>Fanaticks</hi> most eagerly press against his <hi>R. H.</hi> purposely to bring him into an <hi>Odium</hi> with the people; nay, they must have it for granted, and he cannot be half reformed that will deny it, tho' grounded upon the most filly and most groundless suspicions imaginable, without any colour or appearance of prooff, besides the <hi>Presbyterians</hi>
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>.</p>
               <p>Because his <hi>R. H.</hi> to maintain his priviledg and prerogative above or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinary <hi>Subjects,</hi> refused to take the Oaths of <hi>Allegiance</hi> and <hi>Supremacy,</hi> as being never intended to betendred to any of the <hi>Royal Family,</hi> whose birth is a greater tie of their fidelity to the <hi>Crown,</hi> than any Oath the wit of man can invent, he must presently be reputed a <hi>Papist,</hi> and thereby exposed to the <hi>malice</hi> and <hi>hatred</hi> of the <hi>mobile.</hi> But do not the <hi>Presbyterians</hi> also reject these <hi>Oaths?</hi> how then can it be an argument of <hi>Popery</hi> in the <hi>D.</hi> to refuse them? Can it be reputed <hi>Popery</hi> in the one, and <hi>Puritanism</hi> in the other? Or if the <hi>Papists</hi> and <hi>Puritans</hi> have two distinct reasons to refuse these <hi>Oaths,</hi> why might not his <hi>R. H.</hi> have a third motive, distinct from both, to reject them?</p>
               <p>Oh! but he does not <hi>Communicate</hi> with the <hi>Church</hi> of <hi>England.</hi> And no more do the <hi>Presbyterians.</hi> Must we therefore conclude they are <hi>Papists</hi> too? We must indeed conclude they are infected with the very dregs of <hi>Papery,</hi> as <hi>Treason, Rebellion,</hi> and <hi>Kingkilling</hi> principles. And I am confident, the chiefest reason why they are so inveterate against the <hi>Papists,</hi> is not for any diversity of Religion, but rather because <hi>two of a Trade eannot agree. Figulus odit figulum,</hi> and so very often one <hi>Traytor</hi> hates another.</p>
               <p>As for his <hi>R. H.</hi> tho' of late he communicates not with the <hi>Church</hi> of <hi>England,</hi> yet we cannot find that ever he communicated with the <hi>Church</hi> of <hi>Rome</hi> either in <hi>Doctrine</hi> or <hi>Sacraments.</hi> Upon what grounds then can we conclude him a <hi>Papist?</hi> And since <hi>Christianity</hi> commands us to think the best we can of all persons, and that it is undeniably batter to communicate with no <hi>Church</hi> at all, than with one confes<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sedly erroneous; because the one is but to omit what is good, but the other is positively to commit what is evil; the one is against an affir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mative precept, which doth not bind us for all times and seasons, the other against a negative which doth always oblige: Is it not more <hi>Charitable</hi> in us, to think his <hi>R. H. Communicates</hi> with no <hi>Church</hi> at all, than rashly affirm, without any grounds, he <hi>Communicates</hi> with the <hi>Church</hi> of <hi>Rome?</hi> Especially, since it cannot be denyed, but that a man may for a time suspend his <hi>Communion</hi> as to the <hi>Sacraments,</hi> and
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:204734:25"/>outward <hi>Ceremonies</hi> from all vilible <hi>Churches,</hi> and yet be a true <hi>Christian</hi> still. Shall we be so mad as to imitate the profane <hi>Puritans,</hi> who spare neither the prerogatives of God, nor of Gods vicegerent but arro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gantly presume to dive into peoples hearts (which are subject only to the divine omniscience) and without any appeal to their actions, pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tend to know their most inward secrets?</p>
               <p>Let us rather endeavour to dive into the <hi>Presbyterians mysterys of in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iquity,</hi> and by their outward actions we may easily guess their inward designs. <hi>Ex operibus eorum cognoscetis eos.</hi> There you shall plainly find, it is neither for any <hi>Zeal</hi> for the <hi>Protestant Religion,</hi> nor for any good they wish the <hi>Church</hi> of <hi>England,</hi> they charge his <hi>R. H.</hi> with <hi>Popery,</hi> or use such Virulent invectives against him, but meerly out of their boundless malice and antipathy against <hi>Monarchical Government.</hi> And in proof hereof, I durst venture my life, had the matter been wholly left to the <hi>Presbyterians</hi> choice, they would rather wish his <hi>R. H.</hi> should openly protess the <hi>Romish Religion,</hi> than now declare himself to be, or rather still to have been of the <hi>Church</hi> of <hi>England:</hi> the former they know might be a specious <hi>Cloak</hi> for their <hi>Knavery,</hi> but the latter, would deprive them of their most plausible pretences. Besides, they cannot deny, but that his <hi>Majesty</hi> is as likely to survive his <hi>R. H.</hi> as otherwise: if therefore their design had been only to secure the <hi>Protestant Religion,</hi> as they pretend, to what purpose should they (had the <hi>D.</hi> been really a <hi>Papist</hi>) so much exclaim against a <hi>Popish Successor</hi> who is likely either not at all, or at least not long to survive his Sacred <hi>Majesty;</hi> and consequently, is not like to be able, tho' he were wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling, in so short a time to suppress a Religion (to speak nothing of Gods providence) so unanimously professed, and so firmly established by Law?</p>
               <p>Their reason without doubt is, because they find themselves altoge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther unable to oppose his <hi>Majesties Prerogative</hi> and <hi>Soveraign</hi> Authority, joyned with the great <hi>Conduct</hi> and <hi>Resolution</hi> of his <hi>R. H.</hi> and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore observing that <hi>Machiavilian Maxim</hi> of the <hi>Jesuits, Divide &amp; im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pera,</hi> what joyntly they cannot overthrow, they labour severally to un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dermine. To this end they use all possible devices to possess his <hi>Majesty</hi> with jealousies and sinister apprehensions, thereby toalienate his affect<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ions from his only Brother, contrary to the ties not only of Nature, but also of common Gratitude to a person of his merits and services both at home and abroad; and whom God has joyned together these <hi>Republi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cans</hi> labour to put asunder.</p>
               <p>How fatal this Stratagem proved in King <hi>Edward</hi> the 6<seg rend="sup">th</seg>s days to the great <hi>D.</hi> of <hi>Somerset</hi> and his brother the <hi>L. Admiral,</hi> our <hi>Historians</hi>
                  <pb n="47" facs="tcp:204734:25"/>can sufficiently testifie. These two, while united amongst themselves, like a triple Cord, were so strong, and seemed so formidable to their adversaries, that it was concluded nothing but their separation could put a period to their so much envyed greatness. Their enemies there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore by strange artifices prevailed at last with the <hi>Protector,</hi> who du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring the <hi>Kings</hi> minority had the chief management of affairs, to sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>scribe to his brothers execution, but thereby condemned his own head to the <hi>Block, as</hi> soon after he found too true by woful experience For being thus left alone, he was presently exposed to the implacable ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lice of his bloud thirsty adversaries, and not having now his brother to espouse his quarrel, he was at last sacrificed to their fury. <hi>A warrant</hi> (saith <hi>Baker,</hi> speaking of the <hi>Admiral</hi>'s untimely death) <hi>was signed un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the hand of his brother the</hi> Protector, <hi>to cut off his brothers head.</hi> Whereby (at it proved) he did as much as if he had laid down his own head to the <hi>Block:</hi> for whilst these brothers lived and held together, they were as a strong Fortress one to the other; the <hi>Admiral</hi>'s Cou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rage supporting the <hi>Protector</hi>'s Authority, and the <hi>Protector</hi>'s Autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity maintaining the <hi>Admiral</hi>'s Stoutness; but the <hi>Admiral</hi> once gone, the <hi>Protector</hi>'s Authority, as wanting support, began to totter, and fell at last to utter ruine. Besides, there was at this time, among the Nobility, a kind of Faction; <hi>Protestants,</hi> who favoured the <hi>Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tector</hi> for his own sake; and other of the <hi>Papal</hi> inclination, who favou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red him for his brothers sake: but his brother being gone, both sides forsook him, even his own side as thinking they could expect little assistance from him, who gave no more assistance to his own brother. Hitherto <hi>Baker,</hi> page 307.</p>
               <p>And we may be sure, this Stratagem proving then so successful, cannot but animate our <hi>Machiavels</hi> now to use the like contrivance, to carry on their hellish designs against our <hi>King</hi> and <hi>Kingdom.</hi> They have often declared of late years in their <hi>Clubs</hi> and grand <hi>Cabals,</hi> that if they could but once be rid of his <hi>R. H.</hi> they might make what they pleased of his Sacred <hi>Majesty:</hi> And truly, in my opinion, they had rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>son to expect no less: for surely, no man can be so blind, as not to see, that if the <hi>King</hi> should at any time give way to the <hi>Presbyterians</hi> unlimited malice against the <hi>D.</hi> and particularly to the Spirit of re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venge which now agitateth their chiefest <hi>Demagogues,</hi> not one of all his friends but would immediatly desert him, and for their own preser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation leave him to the merciless mercy of the <hi>Antimonarchical Republi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cans;</hi> as formerly it happen'd to the D. of <hi>Somerset,</hi>
                  <q>Si licet exemplis parvis in grandibus uti.</q>
               </p>
               <pb n="48" facs="tcp:204734:26"/>
               <p>The reason is, because they could not in prudence expect any safe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty or security from him, who (to satisfie an unsatiable Faction, which as King <hi>James</hi> said, no favour or obligation can win) would not secure so good and so deserving a brother against so apparent a malice, which plainly tends to the utter subversion of all Government both <hi>Spiritual</hi> and <hi>Temporal.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>To this our <hi>Ahitophels</hi> will answer,
<q rend="margQuotes">That as for their part they never conspired against his R. <hi>H.</hi>'s life, neither did they aime at any thing else, but the preservation of the <hi>Protestant Religion,</hi> and the <hi>Property</hi> and <hi>Liberty</hi> of the Subject; and to this end tho' they endea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>voured to disinheit his <hi>R. H.</hi> yet they never designed to take away his life.</q> Yet this is but <hi>crambe recocta,</hi> and the old <hi>Canting</hi> of 41. and withal it is the Spirit of <hi>Popery</hi> under the Cloak of <hi>Presbytery.</hi> First, it is well known that by these very pretences the <hi>Godly Gospelers</hi> seduced the ignorant people from their <hi>Allegiance</hi> to the <hi>Father,</hi> as now they endeavour to incense them against the <hi>Son.</hi> It is the usual policy of these <hi>Machiavels</hi> (like him who often transforms himself into an <hi>Angel</hi> of light, 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 11.14.) to make fair beginnings, but very foul endings. Their specious pretences are like the singing of <hi>Syrens,</hi> lulling the un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wary into such a sleep, that he is not able to escape the snares of their malice. Secondly, this artifice exactly resembles that cunning distin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction of some <hi>Papists,</hi> who say that the <hi>Pope</hi> may Authorize Subjects to depose, but never to kill or murder their <hi>Soveraign;</hi> whereas it is manifest, that whosoever can justly depose, he may lawfully put to death any <hi>Prince</hi> whatsoever; and what cause soever grounds the one, must of necessity justifie the other. Nay, a <hi>Prince</hi> is no sooner disin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>herited or deposed, but he is <hi>ipso facto</hi> alloted for a Sacrifice to his ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies. Private persons may, but it is impossible for <hi>Princes</hi> to survive their Dignity. K. <hi>Richard</hi> the 2<seg rend="sup">d.</seg> having so freely resigned his <hi>Crown</hi> made (as he thought) firm conditions with <hi>H.</hi> the 4<seg rend="sup">th</seg> peaceably to lead a private life; yet this could not in the least secure him, or pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vent his <hi>Tragical</hi> execution. The like happen'd to <hi>Edward</hi> the 2d. <hi>Henry</hi> the 6<seg rend="sup">th</seg> and many others: nay, to see a <hi>Prince</hi> (if <hi>compos mentis</hi>) in safety after his disinherison or deposition, is
<q>Rara avis in terris, nigro{que} simillima Cygno.</q>
               </p>
               <p>But suppose the <hi>D.</hi> might survive his disinherison, upon what grounds should he thus forfeit his Dignity, or be deprived of his <hi>Birth right?</hi> Is it, because he is a <hi>Non-Conformist?</hi> If so, then let all <hi>Puritans,</hi> who undoubtedly are <hi>Non-Conformists</hi> and <hi>Schismatical</hi> Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctaries,
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:204734:26"/>first be expelled out of their Lands and Livings, out of their places and employments, that so there may be some grounds to pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceed against the <hi>D.</hi> Ay, but he is supposed a <hi>Papist,</hi> and consequently cannot be a good <hi>K.</hi> for <hi>Protestant</hi> Subjects. Why then, at least let all supposed <hi>Papists</hi> first forfeit their estates, and then we may once more strive for the <hi>Bishops</hi> Lands, and send them to the <hi>Pope</hi> for a pension. Besides, if the <hi>Papists</hi> whether supposed or real be thus dealt withal, why should not the same measure be meted to other <hi>Sectaries</hi> also, as to <hi>Quakers, Brownists, Anabaptists,</hi> who are no less erroneous in their Doctrine, nay, and to the <hi>Presbyterians</hi> too, who are no less wicked in their practices, than the <hi>Papists</hi> themselves. And surely we have al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ready found by experience, that it is far more impossible for <hi>Presbyte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rians</hi> to make good Subjects for any <hi>Monarch</hi> whatsoever, than for a <hi>Papist</hi> to make a good <hi>K,</hi> for <hi>Protestant</hi> Subjects. If therefore the <hi>D.</hi> (who is only supposed, but never proved a <hi>Papist</hi>) should forfeit his right, because of the repugnancy of <hi>Popery</hi> to the <hi>Protestant Religion;</hi> let the <hi>Puritans</hi> (who are known <hi>Schismaticks</hi> and rebels to the <hi>Church</hi>) first be deprived of all their Livings and Employments, because of the undoubted <hi>Antipathy</hi> of <hi>Presbytery,</hi> as well to true <hi>Religion,</hi> as to <hi>Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>narchical</hi> Government. Is it not madness in the highest degree, that known <hi>Sectaries</hi> should be tolerated, and the suspected only be censu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red or condemned? that the son of our late <hi>Soveraign,</hi> who dyed <hi>a Martyr</hi> for our <hi>Church,</hi> should be threatened to loose his right, and and the worthy Sons of his bloudy <hi>Butchers</hi> be left in quiet posession of those Lands, which their Fathers Villanies and their own Wickedness made them unworthy to enjoy? Shall we be again deluded by their spe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious pretences, to make the <hi>Crown</hi> a Foot-ball for <hi>Republicans?</hi> Is this our <hi>Oath</hi> to maintain the prerogatives of the <hi>Crown</hi> with the hazard of our lives, to leave it thus to the enemies of <hi>Monarchy</hi> to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stow it on whom they please? If we look unto former ages, we shall find that the Succession was then held so Sacred and inviolable, that it was counted a crime of the first magnitude for Subjects to meddle in such weighty matters.</p>
               <p>That glorious Princess Q <hi>Eliz.</hi> tho' a Woman, yet never heard the Succession debated, even against a professed <hi>Papist,</hi> either in or out of <hi>Parliament,</hi> but the actors must presently pack to prison to consider and amend their Folly: For (as <hi>Cambden</hi> saith in her Life, p. 73.) <hi>cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainly, she never heard any thing more unwillingly, than that the title of Succession should be called into question.</hi> And therefore in the 8. year of her Reign, she sent Mr. <hi>Thornton</hi> Reader of Law in <hi>Lincolns-Inn</hi> to the <hi>Tower, because in his Reading he called the Q. of</hi> Scots <hi>title in question,</hi> Cam<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="50" facs="tcp:204734:27"/>page 86. And it was alledged by the Earl of <hi>Leicester,</hi> as a great crime against the Lord Keeper <hi>Bacon, that he had intermeddled against the Q, of</hi> Scots <hi>in the matter of Succession, and was privy to a Book wherein</hi> Hales <hi>went about to derive the title of the Crown of</hi> England, <hi>in case the Q. should die without Issue, to the house of</hi> Suffolk. <hi>Whereupon</hi> Hales <hi>was commited to the Tower; But</hi> Bacon <hi>(though he denyed it) was by much a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doe restored to favour.</hi> Cambden page 73. And likewise in a <hi>Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment</hi> held 35. <hi>Eliz.</hi> Mr. <hi>Wentworth,</hi> Sir <hi>Henry Bromley</hi> and others of the <hi>House</hi> of <hi>Commons,</hi> mouing for entailing the succession of the <hi>Crown,</hi> the Q was so much incensed against them, that Mr. <hi>Wentworth</hi> was presently sent to the <hi>Tower,</hi> and the rest to the <hi>Fleet. Tantae molis crat defendere Jura coronae.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>And had this course been taken in these times with some over-act<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ive <hi>Republicans,</hi> who out of their <hi>Antimonarchical Zeal</hi> endeavour to snatch the <hi>Crown</hi> from the right line, I doubt not, but in few days all these Storms might be allayed, and things brought to a firm fetlement; for it is certain, the more they are tolerated, the more insolent they will grow; and if ever they get the opportunity, they will no less bark against the <hi>Possessor,</hi> than the <hi>Successor</hi> of the <hi>Crown;</hi> for in truth not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withstanding all hypocritical clamours of <hi>Religion,</hi> their main de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sign is to expel both <hi>Monarchy</hi> and <hi>Episcopacy</hi> out of this <hi>Island</hi> for ever.</p>
               <p>The case therefore being such, and the <hi>Presbyterians</hi> specious preten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces proving at last so pernicious to our <hi>Church</hi> and <hi>State,</hi> have we not reason to look about us, and timely beware of such dangerous creatures, who like <hi>Judas</hi> outwardly shew us a great deal of kindness, but in their hearts contrive our ruine, and under the colour of securing the <hi>Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>testant Religion,</hi> do labour to subvert our <hi>Laws</hi> and <hi>Government,</hi> and engage the three Nations in endless troubles? Is it not our inte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rest, while we have the power in our hands, diligently to exa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mine these specious pretences, and if possible dive into the bottom of their designs. remembring that pithy saying of the <hi>Roman</hi> Sage, <hi>Fistula dulce canit, volucrem dum decipit auceps.</hi> We see how through our carelessness they daily gain ground upon us, continually tamper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing with those of our <hi>Church,</hi> whose passions they find suitable or ply<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able to their pretences. Such as they find ignorantly <hi>Zealous,</hi> or in the least offended at any thing they misunderstand in our <hi>Ceremonies,</hi> by their <hi>Hypocrisie</hi> and seeming <hi>Sanctity</hi> they are sure to win them to their party. And those they perceive to be of an ambitious and aspiring Spirit, they immediatly gain by rewards aand promises of great preferments.</p>
               <pb n="51" facs="tcp:204734:27"/>
               <p>But such as they find popular and eminent above the rest, or in a posture to do their <hi>Countrey</hi> service, presently they insinuate themselves into their good liking, and if possible, insensibly steal them to their <hi>Puritan Faction.</hi> And so successful they have been in these cunning contrivances, that it is not imaginable what number of <hi>Proselites</hi> they have lately gained from our communion. Nay, these very <hi>Witnesses,</hi> who happily came in to discover the <hi>horrid Plot</hi> of the <hi>Popists,</hi> are so courted and caressed by the <hi>godly Brethren,</hi> that people make it a <hi>grand Quaere,</hi> whether these <hi>Discoverers</hi> be now more inclined to the <hi>Presbyterian interest,</hi> or to the good of the <hi>Church</hi> of <hi>England.</hi> As for my own part, I must confess, this <hi>Problem</hi> has for above this half year past, often put me to a <hi>Non-plus,</hi> and to a great confusion of mind, not well knowing what to conclude in these distracted times: For when I think of these <hi>Witnesses</hi> discovering the cursed <hi>Popish Plot,</hi> I cannot but praise the <hi>Divine Providence,</hi> which always frustrates the hellish designs of these <hi>sons of Belial</hi> against our <hi>Church</hi> and <hi>State.</hi> But when on the other side I consider, how the <hi>Presbyterians</hi> are the most intimat <hi>Privy-Council</hi> of these same <hi>Discoverers,</hi> their greatest sticklers, and chief, if not sole Admirers and Adorers; and withall when I bear of their discovering the Introducers, not onely of <hi>Popery,</hi> but also of <hi>Ty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rannical and Arbitrary Government,</hi> and that I know the <hi>Church of Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land,</hi> (which, as the most <hi>Orthodox,</hi> so is now the most <hi>Loyal Church</hi> upon Earth) or at least all the <hi>Courtiers,</hi> and his <hi>Majesties chief Favou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rites,</hi> may, in the <hi>Puritans Judgment,</hi> as well be charged with the later branch, as the <hi>Papists</hi> have been prosecuted for the former; yea, are in a great number already listed by our <hi>holy Brethren,</hi> some as <hi>Pensioners,</hi> others plainly as <hi>introducers</hi> of <hi>Arbitrary Government,</hi> and of <hi>Popery</hi> too: When I confider, I say, these strange transactions, I stand amazed not knowing what to say in such surprizing circumstances. But, <hi>From Pres<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>byterian contrivances, and the reviving of</hi> 41, <hi>Good Lord deliver us.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The chiefest shield, under the <hi>Divine Providence,</hi> and our <hi>Gracious Sovereigns,</hi> that protected us in former times from the insolency of these <hi>seditious Sectaries,</hi> was the indefatigable diligence of our <hi>Layal</hi> and <hi>Orthod<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>x Parliaments,</hi> which, since the beginning of Queen <hi>Elizabeth</hi>'s Reign, have by good and wholesome <hi>Laws</hi> secured us from all our <hi>ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>versaries,</hi> until the fatal <hi>Apoplexy</hi> of 41, when the <hi>Presbyterians,</hi> by their secret contrivances, and deluding hypocrisie and pretence of <hi>Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion,</hi> gained so far upon the ignorant people, that few but <hi>Presby<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terians</hi> were Elected <hi>Parliament-men.</hi> But if that Election proved then so fatal to our <hi>King</hi> and <hi>Countrey,</hi> what shall we think of these present times? Do not we see how the <hi>Presbyterians</hi> are the most
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:204734:28"/>numerous and the strongest Faction now in <hi>England,</hi> far exceeding in Men, Money, and Resolution, not onely their own worthy Progeny, the ate sprung-up <hi>Fanaticks,</hi> but also the <hi>Episcopal Protestants</hi> of this <hi>Island?</hi> Since therefore the <hi>Representatives</hi> of the <hi>Commons</hi> of <hi>England</hi> are Elected by the major vote of the People, how can we but suspect that the <hi>Presbyterians,</hi> notwithstanding the opposition of the <hi>Orthodox</hi> Party there, shall bear the sway in the <hi>House of Commons?</hi> What grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter security then can we expect from such Members now, than from their Predecessors in 41? Can these make greater demonstrations of their integrity, or pretend more earnestly their <hi>Zeal</hi> for the true <hi>Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>testant Religion,</hi> and their <hi>Loyalty</hi> to their <hi>Sovereign,</hi> than their Prede<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cessors have done? Do not we remember how the <hi>Long-Parliament,</hi> in their <hi>Remonstrance, May</hi> 19. 1641. thus speak in their hypocritical Language? <hi>The services which we desire to perform to our Sovereign Lord the King, and to his Church and State, in proceeding for the publick peace and prosperity of his Majesty, and all his Realms; within the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sence of the same all-seeing Deity, we protest to have been and still to be the onely end of all our counsels and endeavours, wherein we have resolved to continue freed and enlarged from all private aims, personal respects, or passion whatsoever.</hi> Likewise in their Declaration, <hi>Aug.</hi> 1. 1642. <hi>We the Lords and Commons are resolved to expose our lives and fortunes for the defence and maintenance of the true Religion, the Kings Person, Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour, and Estate.</hi> And <hi>July</hi> 12. <hi>Resolved, That an Army shall be forthwith raised for the safety of the Kings Person, defence of both Houses of Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, and those who have obey'd their Orders and Commands, and pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>serving the true Religion, the Laws, Liberties, and Peace of the Kingdom.</hi> See these and many such other expressions, related by Mr. <hi>Fowlis</hi> in his History of the Plots and Conspiracies of the pretended holy Saints, <hi>Circa med.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>What more solemn Protestations than these could people devise, to demonstrate their Integrity and Loyalty? and yet what destructive designs lay in <hi>Ambuscado</hi> under these specious masks of <hi>Presbytery,</hi> I think now the world can tell. What strange stratagems and cunning devices they used, until they got the power and strength of the King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom into their own hands? Then ending their <hi>Masquerade,</hi> they openly shewed themselves, and, like <hi>blood-thirsty Hell hounds,</hi> never rested, until they sacrificed their <hi>Natural Sovereign,</hi> and banished his present Majesty from his <hi>Crown</hi> and <hi>Dignity.</hi> And yet so cursedly im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>penitent were the <hi>Anarchical</hi> Rebels, that even when the Secluded Members were restored by the Noble <hi>General Monck,</hi> and about the latter end of <hi>February,</hi> 1659/60, met in their full Parliament, so far they
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:204734:28"/>were from being touch'd with the least remorse of conscience, that in <hi>March</hi> following they approved of these inhumane transactions, and ordered, that no person should be admitted for an <hi>Officer</hi> in the <hi>Militia,</hi> till he protested as followeth, <hi>I do acknowledge and declare, That the War undertaken by both Houses of Parliament in their defence, against the Forces raised in the name of the late King, was just and lawful, and that Magistracy and Ministry are the Ordnances of God.</hi> See <hi>Bakers Chronicle, page</hi> 716. <hi>Presbyterian Magistracy</hi> and <hi>Ministery</hi> forsooth must be the <hi>Ordnances of God,</hi> and <hi>Monarchical</hi> and <hi>Episcopal Government</hi> the <hi>Ord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nances</hi> of Man.</p>
               <p>And thus we see how miraculous his Majesties most happy <hi>Restora<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion</hi> has been, when by the over-ruling Providence of <hi>God,</hi> and the glorious endeavours of <hi>General Monck,</hi> he was, notwithstanding all his opposers, in the latter end of <hi>May</hi> following, setled in his Fathers Throne, to the unspeakable joy of all his Loyal Subjects, and utter con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fusion of his Rebellious Enemies.</p>
               <p>But though the intolerable insolence of the <hi>Presbyterians</hi> makes peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple apprehend these fears and jealousies of some of their <hi>Representa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tives,</hi> yet we always hope better things of the prudent consultations of that Loyal and Honourable <hi>Senate.</hi> 'Tis very surprising indeed, and I am afraid no less ominous, that notorious <hi>Rumpers</hi> should be the most earnest of the whole <hi>Kingdom</hi> for the sitting of the <hi>Parliament;</hi> that <hi>Arch-Rebels</hi> and <hi>Regicides,</hi> or at least their Sons and Heirs, (of whom we may justly say, <hi>Mali corvi malum ovum</hi>) should be the greatest pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moters of Petitions to his Majesty for that purpose. For surely it can portend no good to the <hi>Protestant Religion,</hi> that <hi>Schismatical Sectaries,</hi> who in former times crept into holes, not daring to appear at the meeting of Parliaments, should now be so earnest for their sitting.</p>
               <q>Tempora mutantur, nos &amp; mutamur in illis.</q>
               <p>But, what may be the reason why the <hi>Presbyterians</hi> do now press with such vehemence the sitting of the <hi>Parliament,</hi> is indeed very hard and <hi>mysterious</hi> to conceive, yet divers do diversly guess and conjecture at it, as they are diversly inclined, for <hi>unus quis{que} judicat prout affectus est.</hi> Some think they have no other reason, but that being such restless spirits, and as it were naturally enclined to breed and foment troubles, they endeavour to be <hi>Ring-leaders</hi> in all tumultuous and seditious pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceedings. Others are perswaded, that their great <hi>Engineers</hi> do appre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hend the <hi>Parliament</hi> may chance smell out their wicked contrivances, and so reward them according to their deserts; and because they know
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:204734:29"/>they are for the sitting of the <hi>Parliament,</hi> the more his <hi>Majesty</hi> has rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>son to defer their meeting, knowing that from the <hi>Anarchical Presby<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terians</hi> no good is to be expected; they endeavour to hinder the <hi>Parli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>aments</hi> meeting by their clamorous Petitioning for their sitting; even as the King of <hi>Spain</hi>'s Drughter, hearing her Father swear he would do nothing that she then begg'd at his hands, hindered the execution of the <hi>Archbishop</hi> of <hi>Toledo,</hi> by begging of his <hi>Majesty</hi> to put him to death. But others are yet of opinion, their chiefest reason is, that they presume the <hi>Parliament,</hi> or at least the house of <hi>Commons,</hi> will stand for the <hi>Pres<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>byterian Gospel,</hi> and again endeauour to erect the <hi>Genevesian Discipline</hi> in this <hi>Kingdom;</hi> and if they have but the house of <hi>Commons</hi> of their side, they doubt not, but by seditious <hi>Stratagems</hi> and continual cla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mours of their <hi>property</hi> and <hi>liberty,</hi> the great <hi>Diana</hi> of the <hi>Ephesians,</hi> they may force the house of <hi>Lords,</hi> and at last the <hi>King</hi> himself to sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>scribe to their demands. <hi>Deus omen avertat.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Yet such is the assured confidence we always repose in the prudence and conduct of our <hi>Gracious Sovereign,</hi> and in the <hi>Religious Loyalty</hi> of his most Honourable House of <hi>Lords</hi> and <hi>Privy Council,</hi> that with the help of the All-seeing Providence of the <hi>Almighty,</hi> we shall have a most happy deliverance from all the contrivances of our enemies, whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther <hi>Papists</hi> or <hi>Presbyterians.</hi> We are fully perswaded, that as the No<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble <hi>Peers</hi> of this <hi>Realm</hi> do unquestionably derive all their Power and Priviledges from the <hi>Royal</hi> Fountain; so now they will not drain the Stream by forsaking the Source, as formerly their Predecessors have most imprudently done, to their unspeakable loss and discredit; but will constantly adhere to their <hi>Prince,</hi> and with their accustomed mag<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nanimity second his <hi>Majesty</hi> in protecting and defending the <hi>Church</hi> of <hi>God,</hi> as by the fundamental <hi>Laws</hi> of the <hi>Land</hi> he engageth himself to do, from all the incursions of her adversaries.</p>
               <p>It has been King <hi>James</hi> his <hi>Aphorism,</hi> and lately verified by woful experience, <hi>No Bishop No King;</hi> and now I think we may add, <hi>No King No house of Lords:</hi> for by the observation of so many ages we find most infallibly, how the interest of this humane <hi>Trinity</hi> is so inseparable, that the one can never be preserved without the safety and welfare of the rest. Streams may as well keep their course after the Spring or Foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain is dryed up, as the <hi>Lords Spiritual</hi> and <hi>Temporal</hi> can subsist with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out the <hi>Royal Fountain</hi> of their <hi>Sovereign:</hi> And an <hi>Eagle</hi> may as well fly without his Wings, as the <hi>King</hi> of <hi>England</hi> can preserve his <hi>Regal</hi> Authority, without his <hi>Lords</hi> as well <hi>Spiritual</hi> as <hi>Temporal.</hi> This <hi>King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom</hi> is like a <hi>Watch,</hi> the <hi>spring</hi> whereof is the <hi>Prince,</hi> the <hi>Lords Spiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tual</hi> and <hi>Temporal</hi> the ballance, and the <hi>Commons</hi> are the interjacent
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:204734:29"/>Wheels; the whole Frame is to be kept in due order, or else no re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gular motion is to be expected. We hope therefore, if peradventure the <hi>Presbyterians</hi> should at any time bear the sway in the house of <hi>Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mons</hi> (which God in his goodness forbid) yet they shall never be able either to introduce <hi>Presbytery,</hi> or again abolish <hi>Episcopal Government,</hi> which has been one of the chiefest means of preserving this <hi>Kingdom</hi> in its due temper and motion these many hundred years. Otherwise, I think, we should incessantly pray, that no <hi>Parliament</hi> should meet in our days.</p>
               <p>But, Good God! what a pitty it is, that our Wise and Religious <hi>Law-makers,</hi> which through the extraordinary blessing of the <hi>Almigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty,</hi> have established the <hi>Church</hi> of <hi>England</hi> in its <hi>Apostolical Purity,</hi> were so far overseen, as not to contrive some means, whereby to pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vent all these dangers and troubles, and secure our <hi>Church</hi> from all fu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture occurrences; which they might easily do, had they but made <hi>Sectaries</hi> and <hi>Non conformists</hi> uncapable of sitting in our <hi>High Court</hi> of <hi>Parliament.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>I must confess, had the <hi>Presbyterian Zealots</hi> been constant to their own Principles, our <hi>Law-makers</hi> have pretty well endeavoured to ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clude them from Voting in the House of <hi>Commons,</hi> when they strictly enjoyned all the Members of that Honourable House solemnly to take the Oaths of <hi>Allegiance</hi> and <hi>Supremacy;</hi> both which, at least the latter, the world knows is directly repugnant to the <hi>Genevesian Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>spel. Such an Headship</hi> (saith <hi>Alexander Henderson,</hi> a notorious Ring<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leader of that Party) <hi>as the Kings of</hi> England <hi>have claimed, and such a Supremacy as the Two Houses of Parliament crave, with the Appeals from the Supreme Ecclesiastical Judicature to them, as set over the Church in the same line of subordination, I do utterly disclaim;</hi> in his second Paper to our Royal Martyr, in the Book entituled, <hi>Reliquiae Carolinae, page</hi> 334. Yet so rare is the Zeal of these politick <hi>Religionaries,</hi> and such is the stoutness of their <hi>tender consciences,</hi> that to get themselves into that station, wherein they are capable of promoting the <hi>good old Cause,</hi> I do not think there is any Test or Oath imaginable, which they would scruple to swallow. Of them we may say with <hi>Horace, Sat.</hi> 3. <hi>lib.</hi> 2.</p>
               <q>
                  <l>— Mille adde catenas,</l>
                  <l>Effugiet tamen haec sceleratus vincula Proteus.</l>
               </q>
               <p>For we find by experience, they make no conscience of breaking, why then of taking any Oath whatsoever. Of Oaths they make poli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tick
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:204734:30"/>
                  <hi>Engiues</hi> to drive on their designs, and delude the Rabble with their dissembling Protestations; whence we may perceive with how much reason and truth the Learned Bishop of <hi>Chichester</hi> affirmed, That <hi>many be arrant Puritans in heart, that onely for preferment do conform; hold with the Hare, and run with the Hound; who, so they might</hi> vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vere <hi>and</hi> valere, <hi>would as willingly have up the Presbyterian Anarchy, as would</hi> Thomas Cartwright <hi>were he living.</hi> In his <hi>Appeal to Cesar, part</hi> 2. <hi>c.</hi> 1. <hi>p.</hi> 111. But surely since <hi>ficta sanctitas duplex est impietas;</hi> and as <hi>Seneca</hi> saith, <hi>Malus ubi bonum simulat, tunc est possimus;</hi> these counterfeit <hi>Protestants,</hi> as they are the wickedest of Christians, so they are to be counted the most dangerous to our <hi>Church</hi> and <hi>State.</hi> I wish therefore our wise <hi>Law-makers</hi> had then further Enacted, That who<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>soever should be prov'd to neglect the service of his <hi>Creator,</hi> or cause<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lesly omit to hear the Word of God, and receive the holy <hi>Communion</hi> from his lawful <hi>Pastor,</hi> or could be found to haunt <hi>Schismatical Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venticles,</hi> and <hi>Illegal Meetings,</hi> should be counted unworthy to serve his <hi>King</hi> and <hi>Countrey</hi> in our <hi>High Court</hi> of <hi>Parliament.</hi> In a word, I wish it had been ordained, that no <hi>Sectary</hi> or <hi>Non-conformist</hi> whatso<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever should have the power either to choose, or be chofen, a Member of that honourable <hi>Senate.</hi> Had this clause been once Enacted, we might assuredly promise our selves, that no Sect or Faction should ever pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vail against us; that no discord or difference should cross that loving and happy union, which has been always continued these many Ages past between our Gracious Sovereigns and their Loyal Subjects, until the <hi>Presbyterians,</hi> about the latter end of King <hi>James</hi> his Reign, most un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fortunately crept into our Parliament, and infected others with the poison of their <hi>Anarchical</hi> Principles, which has been the fource and chief original of all those unspeakable miseries that befell this distracted <hi>Kingdom</hi> above these 50 years; the inexhaustible fountain, whence proceeded the deluge of all our former calamities, and present appre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hensions; hence our Church became gradually vilified, and at last quite rejected and suppressed as <hi>Superstitious</hi> and <hi>unreformed,</hi> our <hi>Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>shops</hi> deposed as <hi>Popish</hi> and <hi>Antichristian,</hi> our <hi>Divines</hi> turned out of their <hi>Pulpits, Schools, Colledges,</hi> and <hi>Ʋniversities,</hi> and deprived of all their <hi>Benefices</hi> and <hi>Livings;</hi> our Loyal <hi>Nobility</hi> and <hi>Gentry</hi> thrust out of <hi>Parliament,</hi> and either cruelly murdered, or tyrannically deprived and robbed of their Lands and Means by an usurping <hi>Nero;</hi> and (to compleat their unparallel'd wickedness) our Gracious <hi>Sovereign</hi> most inhumanely murdered by these <hi>Monsters</hi> of Nature.</p>
               <p>But, to make an end of this endless subject, I shall put a period to this Discourse in the words of that Learned Writer, Mr. <hi>Foulis,</hi> in
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:204734:30"/>his foresaid History, <hi>page ult.</hi> which now I recommend to the <hi>Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders</hi> serious consideration: <hi>To conclude,</hi> (saith he) <hi>if all things, according to the Poets, grow worse and worse, to what stupendious wickedness will the Presbyterians come? If</hi> Caligula <hi>sucked blood when a Child, they might suppose him to be a cruel Monster when a Man. If the Puritans at first rebel against, and imprison their King, murder and clap up the Bishops, seize upon their Lands, and those of the Loyal Gentry, bloudily destroy the best Subjects, and caress the wicked; if at their beginning of rule they multiplyed Religion into so many Heresies, that every house seemed like that Family at the</hi> Hague <hi>in</hi> Holland, <hi>composed of Seven several Religions: If when they were inferiors, they durst Proclaim the</hi> Queen <hi>a Traytor, call the</hi> King's <hi>actions Scandalous, Impudent, False, Wicked, Tyrannical,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>Impose wicked Oaths upon the Nations, and Violate all Laws. Good God! what as yet unheard of Villany and Impiety will there be invented and found out to please the Disciplinarian palates, if ever they should obtain Superiority, or have the least sway in these</hi> Kingdoms? <hi>Which no Honest man can desire, all Good men are bound to oppose, and pray they may never have hopes of such Favour and Authority.</hi>
               </p>
               <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            </div>
         </div>
         <div type="duplicate_pages">
            <pb facs="tcp:204734:31"/>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:204734:31"/>
            <head>THE <hi>Presbyterians Loyalty</hi> AND ZEAL for RELIGION Demonstrated, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
            </head>
            <opener>
               <salute>Good Sir Presbyter,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>YOur Letter I received, and have hitherto deferr'd to send you a reply, as well because I could not certainly tell where to direct it, as also because I thought it altogether needless to spend any time in answering such frivolous <hi>impertinencies,</hi> and idle <hi>whimseys;</hi> yet forasmuch as the Wise-man adviseth us <hi>to answer the fool according to his folly, lest he be wise in his own con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceit, Prov.</hi> 26.5. I concluded at last to send you these ensuing Lines as a <hi>New-years-Gift,</hi> and direct them to your <hi>Worship</hi> at <hi>Billingsgate,</hi> where I judge by your <hi>dexterity</hi> in scolding and railing <hi>Rhetorick</hi> you are a <hi>Master of Art,</hi> if not <hi>Chair-man</hi> to that quick-tongu'd and unsocia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble Society.</p>
            <p>Truly, to be railed at by the <hi>Presbyterians,</hi> is so far from giving me the least distaste, that I count it the greatest honour they can place upon me, it being now the common Character of a faithful <hi>Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>triot,</hi> and true <hi>Loyalist:</hi> And had I been in the least prais'd by such factious Spirits, I would undoubtedly suspect my own actions, and say with <hi>Socrates, What evil have I done, that these</hi> Antimonarchical Le<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vellers <hi>should commend me?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>'Tis true, you pretend to be a Son of the <hi>Church</hi> of <hi>England,</hi> and to colour your <hi>knavery,</hi> you most unfortunately make a Cloak of that holy <hi>Church,</hi> whose candour and sincerity is so <hi>transparent,</hi> that your
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:204734:32"/>pernicious designs are plainly seen through it, to the utter confusion of such <hi>hypocritical dissemblers.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But since the world knows, a <hi>Protestant Jesuit</hi> can equivocate as well as the <hi>Puritan Papist,</hi> I think we have reason enough to believe, that by the <hi>Church</hi> of <hi>England</hi> you mean nothing else but your own <hi>Presbyterian Synagogue,</hi> which alone you esteem the true <hi>Church</hi> of <hi>Christ;</hi> for it is evident, a Son of that <hi>Church,</hi> which is now through God's Providence established among us by the Laws of the Land, you cannot pretend to be, unless such a Son as <hi>Nero</hi> was to <hi>Agrippina,</hi> who scrupled not to procure the death of his unfortunate <hi>Mother,</hi> to satisfie his own monstrous voluptuousness.</p>
            <p>You undertake to roll <hi>Sysiphus</hi> his Stone, or wash a <hi>Gypsie,</hi> to vin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicate the <hi>Presbyterians,</hi> and make us believe they are <hi>harmless Lambs,</hi> though all true Protestants hold them for <hi>ravenous Wolves,</hi> and now apprehend them most dangerous both to <hi>Church</hi> and <hi>State:</hi> yet so pitiful a defence you make in their behalf, that I cannot tell whether the <hi>Church</hi> of <hi>England</hi> has greater reason to detest your <hi>Schismatical</hi> intention, than your own <hi>Synagogue</hi> to curse your <hi>ill-manag'd</hi> under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taking; for since, as the Poet well observed,</p>
            <q>
               <l>
                  <hi>Causa patrocinio non bona pejor erit.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>What shall become of an ill Cause very ill defended?</l>
            </q>
            <p>But however you fail in the rest, you are sure not to forget the old contrivances of your Predecessors, the <hi>Parliamentarian Rebels,</hi> and their worthy Progenitors, in charging all those with <hi>Popery,</hi> that pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sum'd to make the least opposition against their bloody <hi>Zeal</hi> for the <hi>Genevesian</hi> Reformation: Which intrigue, as it prov'd most successful to the <hi>treacherous Rumpers,</hi> so it has been no less destructive and per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nicious to the <hi>Church of England,</hi> it being one of the chiefest <hi>stratagems,</hi> whereby the Rebels brought our <hi>Royal Martyr</hi> and his trustiest Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sters into an odium with the blinded Rabble.</p>
            <p>I could instance here several passages of this <hi>Presbyterian policy,</hi> but I shall content my self with two or three, and will begin with one <hi>re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>markable</hi> example, which was a <hi>praeludium</hi> to all our former distra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctions, as their present proceedings, if not timely prevented, do infal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>libly <hi>prognosticate</hi> the like revolutions to be near at hand. In the year 1632. King <hi>Charles</hi> the First, of glorious memory, took a journey into <hi>Scotland,</hi> and thought by degrees to settle there the <hi>English Liturgy,</hi> with its usual Ceremonies; which the <hi>Ring-leaders</hi> of the <hi>Presbyterian Faction</hi> in that <hi>Kingdom</hi> understanding, not onely exclaimed against
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:204734:32"/>our <hi>Liturgy</hi> as <hi>erroneous</hi> and <hi>superstitions,</hi> but also doubted not to tra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duce his Majesty for very strong inclinations to the <hi>Religion</hi> of the <hi>Church</hi> of <hi>Rome.</hi> By which contrivance they quickly possess'd the <hi>short<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sighted Rabble</hi> with such tears and jealousies, as afterwards broke out into a flame of open <hi>Rebellion,</hi> to the utter ruine and destruction both of <hi>King</hi> and <hi>Countrey.</hi> See <hi>Bakers Chronicle, Edit. anno</hi> 1674. <hi>page</hi> 473.</p>
            <p>And so effectual a contrivance was this piece of policy counted by our brave <hi>Machiavilians,</hi> that in <hi>England</hi> also in the year 1641, when the Spirit within them mov'd the blind Zealots to joyn with the <hi>Scotch Rebels,</hi> (as it is recorded by the same Historian, <hi>page</hi> 535.) in the dead of the night, the more to terrifie the timorous vulgar, <hi>they us'd to cry in the streets of</hi> London, <hi>That all people should arise to their defence, for the King with his Papists were coming to fire the City, and cut their threats in their beds. Than which contrivance</hi> (saith the Author) <hi>though nothing were more false, yet found the effects of truth.</hi> Likewise in <hi>No<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vemb.</hi> 1642 <hi>Vicar,</hi> the Presbyterian Historian, in his Chronicle, <hi>Part</hi> 1. <hi>page</hi> 212. speaking of the B<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>ttle of <hi>Edge-hill,</hi> gives this relation of his holy Brethren, <hi>The Sabbath day after their arrival to</hi> London, <hi>the godly and well-affected Ministers</hi> (i. e. the Presbyterian Predicants) <hi>throughout the City preached and praised the Lord publickly, for their joyful and safe return home to their Parents, Masters, and Friends, exhorting those young Soldiers of Christs Army Royal still to retain, and be forward and ready to shew their courage and zeal to the defence of Gods Cause, and their Countreys welfare: shewing them the Plots of their adversaries, to have introduced Popery and Tyranny into the Kingdom; and assuring them, that this War on their parts was waged and managed by Papists, an Army of Papists be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing raised by the Kings command, contrary to his vows and protestations.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>It is needless, I suppose, to repeat here, how often most of our emi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nent <hi>Divines,</hi> and zealous <hi>Church men,</hi> ever since the <hi>Reformation,</hi> have been slandered in this manner by these hot-headed <hi>Enthusiasts,</hi> and compelled to make <hi>Apologies</hi> in their own vindication against such wicked aspersions. Was not the Learned Dr. <hi>Mountague,</hi> Bishop of <hi>Chichester,</hi> forced to write a Book, intituled, <hi>Appello Caesarem,</hi> against the malicious Calumnies of the <hi>Puritan</hi> Party, where the godly man sheweth himself so far from being daunted with their bold attempts and bloody Menaces, that, with true <hi>Christian courage</hi> he openly exposeth to the world their <hi>mysteries of iniquety,</hi> and fully discovereth their per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nicious contrivances to undermine our <hi>Church,</hi> and subvert our <hi>Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment?</hi> and amongst the rest, he speaketh in this manner, <hi>The truth i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> as with the Jesuit he is an Heretick, that is not</hi> furloso <hi>more a Roman
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:204734:33"/>Catholick, so with the Puritan he is a Papist that will not run a madding with them. It is not the first time</hi> (saith he) <hi>for this very cause I have been talk'd of, esteem'd of, traduc'd as a Papist; which I can the better brook, because they have meted this measure to the Church of England it self, as sympathising with Papists in her Liturgy, Discipline, and Doctrine.</hi> In his <hi>Appeal to Cesar, part</hi> 2. <hi>c.</hi> 1. <hi>p.</hi> 110.</p>
            <p>All true Protestants therefore, who prefer the <hi>Harmonious</hi> and <hi>Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stolical Order</hi> and <hi>Government</hi> of the <hi>Church</hi> of <hi>England,</hi> before the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fused hodge-podge of the new-found <hi>Genevesian Discipline,</hi> have now (I think) sufficient reason to beware of such dangerous contrivances for the future, and not suffer themselves to be gull'd again by such gilded pretences, which, like the <hi>Apples</hi> of <hi>Sodom,</hi> are specious indeed and beautiful without, but base and filthy within. The <hi>Presbyterians,</hi> to our sorrow, have by this policy once deceived us, and the Lord forgive them; but if they deceive us again, then the Lord forgive us. <hi>Improbe Neptunum accusat, qui iterum naufragium facit.</hi> As for my part, I de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clare before God and the World, that I renounce with all my heart and Soul as well the <hi>Idolatrous Papists,</hi> as the <hi>Anarchical Presbyterians,</hi> whose blind zeal and transparent hypocrisie, with their appurtenances, <hi>abjuro, denego, detestor.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I must confess, the Presbyterians are something beyond the Papists in matters of <hi>Religion,</hi> neither did I ever compare them together in that point; but I supposed with the most Learned of our <hi>Church,</hi> and particularly with <hi>Englands Solomon,</hi> King <hi>James</hi> of glorious memory, in his <hi>Apology</hi> for the <hi>Oath of Allegiance, page</hi> 19. That <hi>Papists</hi> were never persecuted in this <hi>Kingdom</hi> (if not by <hi>Cromwel</hi> and his <hi>Rumpers</hi>) for matters of Faith, but for their wicked Principles, and destructive Practices against <hi>Temporal Government.</hi> And now I appeal to the judi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious Reader, if I have not sufficiently demonstrated in my former Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per out of the prime Authors and Founders of the <hi>Genevesian Gospel,</hi> as <hi>Calvin, Beza, Knox, Buchanan, &amp;c.</hi> that the Presbyterian Principles are altogether as dangerous and destructive, if not more pernicious to <hi>Temporal Government,</hi> than that of the Papists themselves. And if your Answer to this be not rather a plain confession of the crime, than any vindication thereof, let the <hi>Reader</hi> judge.</p>
            <p>First, you say, <hi>I am fain to go into other Countreys, as far as</hi> Scotland <hi>and</hi> Geneva, <hi>to prove the Rebellious Principles of the Presbyterians.</hi> But, <hi>good Sir Presbyter,</hi> is not that enough, or are not the Presbyterians every where of the same <hi>stamp</hi> and <hi>coin?</hi> And besides, why may it not be as good a way to prove the Principles of the <hi>Presbyterians,</hi> by al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledging the Doctrine of the <hi>Pope</hi> of <hi>Geneva,</hi> and his chief <hi>Incendiarites,</hi>
               <pb n="5" facs="tcp:204734:33"/>as it is to demonstrate the Principles of the <hi>Papists,</hi> by alledging the Doctrine of the <hi>Pope</hi> of <hi>Rome,</hi> and his approved <hi>Emissaries?</hi> But if neither of these reasons be sufficient in your <hi>phantasie,</hi> do but peruse Dr. <hi>Bancrost</hi> Archbishop of <hi>Canterbury's Book of dangerous Positions,</hi> and there you shall find enough even of <hi>English Presbyterians</hi> (though but Sucklings then) eagerly maintaining this <hi>Anarchical Doctrine;</hi> there you shall find a whole Chapter of that particular subject, with this Title, <hi>The Doctrine of certain</hi> English <hi>Ministers, which they learn'd at</hi> Geneva, <hi>and published of purpose to have procured the like course of Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formation in</hi> England <hi>to that in</hi> Scotland. Behold now, <hi>Sir Presbyter,</hi> your <hi>Genevesian Gospellers,</hi> and those <hi>English</hi> too, and <hi>English</hi> that to promote the <hi>good old Cause,</hi> would not scruple to destroy that antient and <hi>Apostolical Hierarchy</hi> of the Church of <hi>England,</hi> and enflame their <hi>Native Countrey</hi> into a total combustion of Sedition and Rebellion. But let us see whether your second Answer be any thing less ridiculous or impertinent than the former. <hi>Yet admit</hi> (say you) <hi>the Presbyterians in</hi> England <hi>hold the same Principles, put the question whether were more Antimonarchical or unsafe to Government, an opinion, that Tyrants and opposers of God, might</hi> (propter id) <hi>be opposed by their Subjects,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>or that a good King, one of the Reformed Religion, meerly for being such, should be deposed, dethron'd, and murthered,</hi> &amp;c? But <hi>(good Sir Phesbyter)</hi> what is more feasible, than for a Presbyterian to make a Tyrant of what <hi>Prince</hi> he pleases? We see now with what dexterity he makes <hi>Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pists and Pensioners</hi> of the most <hi>zealous Protestants,</hi> and no less <hi>faithful Patriots;</hi> and we have lately seen with what <hi>Legerdemain</hi> he made a <hi>Tyrant</hi> of the best of <hi>Princes.</hi> What Sovereign then can be secure from these Presbyterians, if it lies in their breast thus to make him either a <hi>Titus</hi> or a <hi>Nero,</hi> a clement <hi>Prince,</hi> or a cruel <hi>Tyrant?</hi> or can he think himself a <hi>Sovereign,</hi> and not rather <hi>Tenant at will</hi> to his own <hi>Anarchi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cal</hi> Subjects? Yet you would fain perswade us, your holy <hi>Puritans</hi> teach onely, that <hi>Tyrants may be opposed by their Subjects;</hi> whereas all the world can tell, how in our own days they have not onely <hi>opposed,</hi> but also <hi>deposed, dethron'd, and cruelly murdered,</hi> not a <hi>Tyrant,</hi> but the most meek and Religious of <hi>Sovereigns,</hi> and that by a <hi>formality</hi> of Law too; a thing I never heard perpetrated by any Popish Subjects since the crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the World, no, not by the most barbarous Heathens against the worst of Tyrants.</p>
            <p>As for a Kings being of the <hi>Reformed Religion,</hi> we know it signifies nothing to the Presbyterian <hi>Zealots,</hi> except he be of the <hi>Genevesian Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine</hi> and <hi>Discipline;</hi> the <hi>Church</hi> of <hi>England,</hi> say they, <hi>is neither bot nor cold, neither Popish nor Reformed.</hi> And therefore in the Year 1648,
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:204734:34"/>when the late <hi>King</hi> and <hi>Parliament</hi> were like to agree, the Presbyteri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an <hi>Incendiaries</hi> exclaimed against such proposals, untill the <hi>Genevesi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an Discipline</hi> were first established by Law. <hi>This restitution of his Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jesty</hi> (say they) <hi>to the exercise of his Royal power, before security had from him for settling Religion, your Lordships know by our eight desires, and otherwise, is conceiv'd by us to be inconsistent with the safety and se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>curity of Religion.—The bringing of his Majesty to some of his Houses in or near</hi> London, <hi>before satisfaction and security had from him in point of Religion, and in such other things as are necessary for the safety of the Kingdoms, could not (as we conceive) but be an exceeding great discou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ragement and offence to the Presbyterians in England, who will con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive that the remedy is worse than the disease.</hi> In the humble Repre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sentation of the Commissioners of the General Assembly to the Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nourable Estates of Parliament, April the 28. 1648. Likewise, in the year 1649. the <hi>Rebellious-Zealots</hi> would not submit themselves in <hi>Scotland</hi> to their natural <hi>Soveraign,</hi> his present Majesty, except <hi>he would by solemn Oath under his hand and seal, allow the National Covenant of</hi> Scotland, <hi>and the Solemn League and Covenant of</hi> Scotland, England, <hi>and</hi> Ireland, <hi>and would prosecute the ends thereof in his Royal station.</hi> See <hi>Baker</hi>'s Chronicle, page 613. Tell me now, Sir <hi>Presbyter,</hi> are not these rare examples of your Presbyterian Loyalty to your natural Princes, and to Princes of the <hi>Protestant Church,</hi> and <hi>Reformed Religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on</hi> too? But to set down exactly the true state of the question, admit (as you say, and cannot deny) the Presbyterians of <hi>England</hi> hold the same principles with the <hi>Genevesian-Gospellers;</hi> put you the question now, whether is more <hi>Antimonarchial</hi> or unsafe to <hi>Government,</hi> an <hi>opinion</hi> or rather a <hi>fundamental doctrine,</hi> that <hi>Tyrants</hi> and opposers of God, (<hi>i. e.</hi> any Prince that hinders the <hi>growth</hi> of <hi>Presbyterie</hi>) may <hi>propter id,</hi> be oppos'd, nay, depos'd, dethron'd, and cruelly Murder'd by their Subjects, as Presbyterians undeniably hold, and as undeniably have practis'd: or that it is <hi>Herefie</hi> in any <hi>Christian</hi> to affirm, that a <hi>Prince may be slain or depos'd by his Subjects for any disorder or default, either in Life or Government,</hi> as very <hi>Eminent Papists</hi> expresly teach; as (to omit those two <hi>swindging Authorities,</hi> as you call them, of the <hi>Rhemists Commentaries,</hi> and of the <hi>Council of Constance</hi>) it suffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciently appeareth by <hi>Alphons. à Castro. lib. de haeres. in verbo</hi> Tyran. <hi>Dominic. à Soto,</hi> lib. 5. <hi>de Just. &amp; Jur.</hi> qu. 1. <hi>art.</hi> 3. and many others.</p>
            <p>Now do you if you can, produce such another <hi>Ecolesiastical Assem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly</hi> or <hi>Synod,</hi> or such eminent writers of the Presbyterian party, thus declaring it <hi>Impious and Heretical</hi> to believe that Subjects may Law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:204734:34"/>depose or Murder their <hi>Soveraign</hi> upon the account of any Tyran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny or <hi>oppression</hi> whatsoever, and you will make the World have a better opinion of your Sect, than ever they had hitherto: otherwise, not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withstanding all your multiplied bablings, we must conclude, <hi>to give the Devil his due,</hi> that in matter of Temporal Government, the prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciples of the Papists are far Sounder and more <hi>Orthodox,</hi> than the Presbyterian <hi>Catechism.</hi> As for the practises of the one and the other, you tell me, <hi>could I prove my charge against the Presbyterians, as unex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceptionably, as you can that of the Plot against the Papists, I would do something indeed.</hi> But I appeal to any man of common sense, if you be not as <hi>unexceptionably</hi> impudent in your bold assertions, as the Pres<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>byterians are notoriously <hi>Treacherous</hi> in their pernicious practices. The bloud of our late <hi>Martyr'd Soveraign,</hi> and the effusion of so much Protestant bloud in the late Civil Wars, (you should say, <hi>Presbyterian Rebellion</hi>) you are so impudent as to plaister it upon the unfortunate Papists, without any colour or shew of proof, (it being plain to all the World, that in the whole List of the <hi>Regicides,</hi> none is to be found but <hi>notorious Presbyterians</hi>) and withall to affirm, that the former are more evidently prov'd guilty of the <hi>present Plot,</hi> than the latter can be con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>victed of the <hi>Rebellious practices</hi> laid to their charge: whereas on the one side, we have but four or five persons to swear this horrid <hi>conspiracy</hi> against the Papists; but on the other side, all our <hi>Records,</hi> all our <hi>Histories,</hi> nay, our own <hi>memories,</hi> and all the World can testifie the late <hi>Tragical</hi> transactions, as the inhumane Murder of our <hi>Royal Martyr,</hi> the effusion of so much innocent bloud, the burning and pillaging of so many <hi>Cities, Towns</hi> and <hi>Pallaces,</hi> and in brief all the <hi>Massacres</hi> that have been committed, all the <hi>Miseries</hi> that have hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pened in this <hi>Island</hi> of <hi>Great Britain</hi> these 50 years past, to have been wholly and solely perpetrated by these Monsters of <hi>Christianity</hi> the <hi>Anarchical</hi>-Presbyterians, as well <hi>dependent</hi> as <hi>independent,</hi> as well <hi>Scotch</hi> as <hi>English,</hi> the one <hi>beginning,</hi> the other <hi>ending</hi> the <hi>Tragedy,</hi> the one <hi>Selling,</hi> the other <hi>Killing</hi> their <hi>natural Soveraign</hi> to the amazement of all the World.</p>
            <p>Oh! how happy would they think themselves now, had these vil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lanies been as private, as the present conspiracy of the Papists? Had we been trusting to the discovery of Mr. <hi>Oats,</hi> Mr. <hi>Bedlow,</hi> or the rest, concerning these presbyterian treacheries, as well as the Popish Plot; Oh! how boldly the <hi>Puritan-Gospellers</hi> would outface our witnesses? with what black colours they would paint them, to extenuate the cre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dibility of their informations? So far they would think the charge from being unexceptionably proved against them, that they would not
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:204734:35"/>doubt but they might easily perswade the World, nothing could be more unreasonable, than to believe it upon the credit of such inconsiderable witnesses, tho' now against the Papists they hold them for <hi>Delphian Oracles.</hi>
               <q rend="margQuotes">What! (would they say) can it be Law, equity, or consci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence, to take the oaths of some few despicable fellows, very obnoxious to be suspected of malice and corruption, against the lives of good and peaceable Subjects, men of worth and known integrity? to take the oaths of living Vagabonds, before the protestations of dying Christi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans? who can be safe, if this be admitted? or if this be justice, what can be term'd injustice amongst us?</q>
            </p>
            <p>In this manner, we may be sure, or rather in far higher terms, would our <hi>Supersanctified-Hypocrites</hi> rail against these very Persons, they now so much adore for Swearing against the Papists, had their crimes been so occult as to need a discoverer; and these, nay, people of greater credit, and much less obnoxious to exception, had come in to reveal their <hi>Mysteries</hi> of iniquity. The title of <hi>His Majesties Evidence</hi> could not in the least protect them from the snarling invectives of a Presbyterian. All that Papists now say of them, signified nothing to what the Presbyterians would then vomit against them. Witness their usage of Mr. <hi>Willoughby,</hi> alias <hi>Dangerfield, &amp;c.</hi> who when he pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended to discover a Presbyterian Plot, was presently proclaim'd in the <hi>Weekly Intelligences</hi> and other <hi>Pamphlets,</hi> the greatest Knave and Villain upon Earth, and called <hi>Knight</hi> of the Post, <hi>Newgate-Bird,</hi> and such other titles of <hi>Honour,</hi> nay, affirmed to have been actually upon the <hi>Pillory</hi> for his misdemeanours. The Title of <hi>His Majesties Evidence,</hi> or his pretend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to witness for the <hi>King,</hi> could nothing avail him against these <hi>Sansti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied</hi> creatures, tho' now he is reputed among them an <hi>Holy Proselyte</hi> newly inspir'd and illuminated by the Lord. 'Tis true, he gave then (as himself confesses) but false informations against the Presbyterians, being put on that design either by the Popish party to turn the Plot upon their adversaries, or by some Presbyterian <hi>Politicians</hi> to gain the greater credit to their new Informer, or perhaps by himself to gain such maintenance and allowance for the future, as may keep him henceforth from the tryed punishments of the <hi>Pillory,</hi> seeing those of the trade do thrive so well. There are now in the World a great number of <hi>Fool<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hardy Desperadoes,</hi> of no Fortune, but less Honesty, who think their only way to Preferment is, to run upon <hi>desperate courses,</hi> and rather than fail of an <hi>Advancement,</hi> to venture <hi>Neek and all</hi> for a Livelihood, according to that witty saying of the Satyrist:
<q>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Aude aliquid brevibus Gyaris, ant carcere dignum,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Sivis esse aliquid; probitas laudatur &amp; alget.</hi>
                  </l>
               </q>
               <pb n="9" facs="tcp:204734:35"/>For as <hi>Virgil</hi> saith, — <hi>Quid non mortalia pectora cogis Auri sacra fames?</hi> — In St. <hi>Pauls</hi> days, Godliness was great Gain; but to these, Gain is great Godliness: of whom we may justly say with the Poet,
<q>
                  <hi>Ʋnde habeat quaerit nemo, sed oportet habere.</hi>
               </q>
            </p>
            <p>As for Mr. <hi>Dangerfield,</hi> this only I say, altho' he gave but false Infor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mations against the Presbyterians, yet this was not then known to the generality of the people; and tho' it is undeniable, that such a Plot might well be carried on by the Ring-leaders of that Faction, without communicating it to the Vulgar; nevertheless the <hi>Puritan-Rabble</hi> did so bark and snarl at <hi>Dangerfield,</hi> as if they had known by <hi>Revelation</hi> there was no such Plot at all.</p>
            <p>But to return from this digression to our intended purpose, since reason comands us to prefer the unanimous consent of the greatest and ablest men of our <hi>Country,</hi> together with all our <hi>Histories</hi> and <hi>Records,</hi> and our own <hi>experimental knowledg,</hi> before the oaths of four or five persons, tho' never so upright in their lives, or so positive and exact in their informations; and <hi>a fortiori,</hi> of people not so qualified, but obnoxious to several exceptions and suspicious circumstances, which mightily weakens their evidence, and leaves many judicious men in sus<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pence, frustrated of their expected satisfaction of having the Plot clear'd beyond all exception: surely, we cannot but conclude the late <hi>Rebellion</hi> to be far more <hi>unexceptionably</hi> prov'd against the Presbyteri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans, than the present Plot against the Papists. Not that I would in the least vindicate the <hi>Romanists</hi> from those horrid crimes laid to their charge, for I am fully satisfied they are as apt to commit any villany to advance their <hi>Superstitions,</hi> as the Presbyterians are to promote <hi>the Good old cause;</hi> but to shew that the late <hi>Hellish Rebellion</hi> of the one, is far more undeniable than the present <hi>Conspiracy</hi> of the other.</p>
            <p>And if your own <hi>Conscience</hi> did not accuse you of the known verity of this affection, or if you thought the <hi>Presbyterians</hi> have not really committed these Hellish abominations objected against them, to what purpose did you set the Act of <hi>Oblivion,</hi> to bring up the rear of your ridiculous <hi>Apology?</hi> Surely, things that never have been, could not have been forgotten. <hi>Oblivio est praeteritorum.</hi> Yet you very confi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dently bid me <hi>read over the several Tryals, and other pieces extant by Authority, concerning the present Plot, and see whether it be Presbyterians or Papists that murdered Sir</hi> Edmundbury Godfrey; <hi>that hired the</hi> Ruffians <hi>to murder his Sacred Majesty, and to ruine both Church and State.</hi> But I desire you to read over the late <hi>Narratives</hi> of the <hi>Rebellion</hi> in <hi>Scotland,</hi> and see whether Presbyterians or Papists murdered the good
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:204734:36"/>
               <hi>Bishop</hi> of St. <hi>Andrews;</hi> read over likewise the <hi>History</hi> of the late <hi>Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bellion</hi> in <hi>England,</hi> and see whether it be Presbyterians or Papists, that have (not hired <hi>Ruffians</hi> to murder, but themselves like inhumane <hi>Traytors,</hi> actually) murder'd our late <hi>Soveraign,</hi> and totally ruin'd both <hi>Church</hi> and <hi>State:</hi> and then see what you can get by the bargain, but that notwithstanding your ridiculous <hi>Apology</hi> the Presbyterians are still worse than the Papists, whereas the one did but design, the other have actually compleated our ruine. You tell us for strange news, they are not concern'd in the present <hi>Plot;</hi> and very strange it is indeed, that there should be any Plot or Conspiracy in this <hi>Kingdom,</hi> whereof the Pres<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>byterians should nor be the chief <hi>Engineers.</hi> Yet, Sir <hi>Presbyter,</hi> in my opinion you have no great reason to brag of your Brethrens inno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cence of this Popish Plot, since the world knows, they have commited greater villanies, and that in the face of the Sun, and for <hi>Religion</hi> too. Besides, I advise you to observe the common saying. <hi>Lauda finem,</hi> and tho' your <hi>mysteries</hi> of iniquity be not yet revealed, yet beware least be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the present discovery be at an end, your Presbyterians be not found as deeply concern'd, as any Papist alive, either in this, or in another Plot of their own. for how can it be thought, that such <hi>Politick</hi> and active <hi>Machiavels</hi> should let this occasion slip, or omit the fairest op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portunity they could expect of over throwing their greatest adversaries, the one as <hi>Idolatrous</hi> Papists, the other either as <hi>Popishly</hi> inclined, or as introducers of <hi>Tyranical</hi> and <hi>Arbitrary Government?</hi> I omit here, that I have seen several reasons and arguments, very specious indeed to out. ward appearance, strongly insinuating that the Presbyterians are the <hi>primum mobile</hi> even of the present Plot, and the chief, if not the sole contrivers of all these troubles, fraudulently corrupting and suborning most of those witnesses, that came in to swear against tha Papists, pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>posely to draw the <hi>Kingdom</hi> into a confusion, and thereby restore the <hi>Cromwellian-Gospel</hi> and <hi>Government.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>In this assertion, I know, there is no <hi>impossibility</hi> or <hi>contradiction</hi> to be found; I believe it very <hi>feasible</hi> (and without doubt it has been of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten done) to corrupt and suborn men of better credit and reputation than these witnesses have been, that have yet appeared in this disco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very; and withall I am sure, the Presbyterians are too apt to commit any villany to promote the <hi>Good old cause:</hi> yet nevertheless, because we must not insist upon unprov'd, tho' probable suspicions, when we have enough even of plain demonstrations to prove our intended purpose of shewing how dangerous our <hi>Puritan-Gospellers,</hi> if not prudently and timely prevented, are to our <hi>Church</hi> and <hi>State;</hi> the probability of this charge, I leave to be weigh'd and examind by the <hi>Judicious</hi> Reader.
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:204734:36"/>In the interim, tell me I beseech you, what may be the reason that the Presbyterians are the activest and most eager prosecutors of the Papists upon the account of this Plot, and also the greatest promoters and ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mirers of those witnesses, that appear against them. Are the Presbyte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rians the ablest men in the <hi>Kingdom?</hi> or do they only apprehend the danger of this Plot? Do they love their <hi>Religion Lives,</hi> or <hi>Liberties,</hi> better than Protestants love theirs? or were not Protestants to be made away, had this Plot gon on, as well as the Presbyterians? why then are not the latter as moderate as the former, or the former as mad as the latter? Truly, I have heard several <hi>Judicious Protestants</hi> affirm, they could never believe, that the Presbyterians should be so hot or eager in prosecuting this Popish Plot against so inconsiderable a party, as Papists now are in this <hi>Kingdom,</hi> except they had greater designs, or were more concerned in that Plot themselves, than they would have the <hi>World</hi> believe. But <hi>time</hi> will tell truth.</p>
            <p>Your ignorance tells you, I have affronted the <hi>Clergy</hi> of the <hi>Church</hi> of <hi>England,</hi> by calling them <hi>Dumb-dogs;</hi> but you should know before you appeared in Print, that a <hi>Dog,</hi> for his natural vigilancy, is the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon <hi>Emblem</hi> of an <hi>Ecclesiastical Pastor;</hi> and if our <hi>Prelates</hi> now be less active than is necessary for to prevent your <hi>Treacherous</hi> designs, and countermine your <hi>pernicious</hi> contrivances against their Flock, they may attribute this application of <hi>Gods word, Isa.</hi> 56.10. not to any ill meaning of mine, but rather to their own unreasonable carelesness in such a desperate juncture of times, when our greatest, if not our only enemies, the Presbyterians and Papists, are equally, tho' severally, bent for our destruction; <hi>those brethren in evil,</hi> (as the Bishop of <hi>Chichester</hi> elegantly calls them) <hi>who looking and running two several ways, do like</hi> Samson's Foxes <hi>joyn together in the taile.</hi> in his appeal to <hi>Cesar,</hi> part 1 c. 4. p. 48.</p>
            <p>Here I shall beg the favour of you, to ask that <hi>Reverend Prelate,</hi> who declared himself in the <hi>Parliament</hi> before the last, so favourable to your Sect, what does he think now of the Presbyterians, or whether in his opinion they took the <hi>Reverend Bishop</hi> of St. <hi>Andrews by the Lawn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sleeves, or by the Throat?</hi> Ask likewise the rest of those learned <hi>Prelates,</hi> whether the Presbyterians have <hi>like waspish Curs bark'd</hi> at that holy man <hi>Archbishop Laud,</hi> or <hi>like your red Dragon utterly devoured him?</hi> Is it credible, think you, these eminent Divines should be of so short a me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mory, as to forget who so lately voted them out of the House of Peers, barbarously imprisoned them in the <hi>Tower,</hi> sequestered their Lands and Revenues, (which to an <hi>Englishman</hi> is worse then to lose his life) de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prived them of all power and jurisdiction both Spiritual &amp; Temporal,
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:204734:37"/>and in fine, quite abolished the whole order and <hi>bierarchy</hi> of that <hi>Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stolical</hi> institution? or is it likely they would now <hi>Apologize</hi> for that faction which have lately so <hi>Antichristianly</hi> abused them? they know it is an old and true saying, <hi>Veterem ferendo injuriam, invitas novam:</hi> and I pray God, they may not find it verified in themselves, who through their excesive meekness and patience towards these ungrateful miscreants, I am afraid, will encourage them once more to attempt the suppressing of this <hi>Apostolical hierarchy;</hi> which we may plainly read in their libells and pamphlets; is their main design. Yet notwith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>standing this, and all other eminent dangers, which daily threaten us from the Presbyterian party, you are so impudent, as to term your self an <hi>Episcopal</hi> Protestant, and yet strain your empty noddle in apolo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gizing for these <hi>Antiepiscopal</hi> Sectaries, and excusing their <hi>Schismatical</hi> separation from the <hi>Mother Church,</hi> thereby encouraging them to act over again their horrid villanies of 48. and sing the second part to the same tune.</p>
            <p>You tell us forsooth, <hi>they are our fellow-protestants, and therefore not to be reputed as enemies to our Church, but to be embraced as brethren of our Reformatoon.</hi> Protestants, 'tis true, they stile themselves, but false ones they are always reputed by our Church, as Papists are false <hi>Christians;</hi> for (as the Apostle saith) <hi>they are not all Israel, which are of Israel, Rom.</hi> 9.6. Neither are they all Protestants, which are called Protestants; many do love the name, but hate the thing: and therfore why should not false <hi>Protestants</hi> be thought as dangerous to the true faith and wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ship of God, as false <hi>Christians,</hi> I could never yet understand. Papists are but false <hi>Christians,</hi> but the Presbyterians are false <hi>Protestants,</hi> and by consequence they are false <hi>Christians</hi> too: why then should the one be counted our Brethren, and the other our Enemies? or what can we gain by this our ill bestowed kindness to the presbyterians, but to draw upon us the charge of all their monstrous contrivances, and make our selves accountable for their wickedness, as the papists are now commonly charged with the horrid practices of the <hi>Jesuits?</hi> Do not we see how as the <hi>Primitive Christians</hi> were grievously slandered, and most vehemently hated by the <hi>Heathens,</hi> because of the multiplied villanies of the <hi>Gnosticks</hi> and other prophane Sects of those times, that professed <hi>Christianity;</hi> so true Protestants now are obnoxious to those manifold calumnies unjustly heaped by the Papists and other Sectaries, upon our <hi>Church</hi> and Doctrine, and the whole <hi>Reformation,</hi> because of theseditious practices and wicked treacheries of the Presbyterian party, who commonly stile themselves <hi>Protestants</hi> and <hi>Reformed,</hi> yea, <hi>Refined Christians?</hi> Nay, I do verily believe, that as the monstrous wicked<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ness
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:204734:37"/>of the aforesaid <hi>Hereticks</hi> was then a great bar to the timely con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>version of the <hi>Idolatrous Pagans;</hi> so now the <hi>unchristian</hi> proceedings of the presbyterians do mainly obstruct the <hi>Papists</hi> from receiving the true light of the <hi>Gospel.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>O, but they are our weak Brethren, and we must bear their infirmities.</hi> Weak Brethren, say you? I pray God keep them so, and grant they be never stronger to ruine our <hi>Church</hi> and <hi>State,</hi> as formerly they have done. Now the <hi>Pharisaical Hypocrites</hi> alledge the weakness and tender<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ness of their Consciences for this <hi>Schismatical</hi> disobedience to their lawful Pastors, and separation from the <hi>Mother-Church;</hi> though in 48 no tenderness of Conscience could hinder them from murdering their natural <hi>Sovereign</hi> in <hi>England,</hi> and in 79 their onely <hi>Primate</hi> and <hi>Metropolitane</hi> in <hi>Scotland. O blind Guides,</hi> (as our Saviour said of the Pharisees) <hi>which strain at a gnat, and swallow a camel, Matth.</hi> 23.34. Yet these blind Hypocrites you must hall in amongst Episcopal Prote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stants, and under the ridiculous name of <hi>dissenting Brethren,</hi> you en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deavour to foster such <hi>Vipers</hi> in the bosom of our <hi>Church;</hi> a name so strange and self-contradictory, as if we had called them our <hi>odious Lovers,</hi> our <hi>loving Enemies,</hi> or the like; for if the Presbyterians ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stinately dissent from our <hi>Church</hi> in Communion, or matters of Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion, as undoubtedly they do, how can they be our Brethren? or if they be our Brethren in <hi>Religion,</hi> how can they differ from us in Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munion, or matters of Faith, which essentially is one and individual? for, as the Apostle testifieth, there is but <hi>one Lord, one Faith, one Ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ptism, Ephes.</hi> 4.5.</p>
            <p>Ay, but they do not dissent from us as much as the Papists do, not in so many, nor in so necessary points of Religion. But this is to no pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pose; first, because <hi>Heathens</hi> dissent from us more than <hi>Jews, Jews</hi> than <hi>Turks,</hi> and <hi>Turks</hi> than <hi>Papists;</hi> yet we must embrace neither <hi>Jew, Turk,</hi> nor <hi>Papist,</hi> for our dissenting Brethren in <hi>Religion.</hi> Secondly, Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cause even as it is nothing material whether a man dies of one mortal wound, or of twenty; so it skilleth not whether a <hi>Christian</hi> obsti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nately erres in one necessary point of Religion, or in a dozen. For it is in the Christian Religion, as St. <hi>James</hi> saith of the Law, <hi>Whosoever offendeth in one point, he is guilty of all, James</hi> 2.10. Now it is evident to all the world, that the Presbyterians grosly err in three of the chiefest Pillars of <hi>Christian Religion,</hi> as <hi>Charity, Ʋnity,</hi> and <hi>Obedience:</hi> It cannot therefore avail them much that they agree with us in so ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny points of the Superstructure, while they disagree from us in the very Foundation. Hear what St. <hi>Augustin</hi> saith of the <hi>Donatists</hi> in <hi>Africk,</hi> who much resemble the <hi>Presbyterians</hi> in <hi>England; In many
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:204734:38"/>things</hi> (saith he) <hi>they are with me, in few not with me; but in these few wherein they are not with me, the many things wherein they are with me do nothing avail them;</hi> in <hi>Psal.</hi> 54. <hi>ver.</hi> 19. Thirdly because all true <hi>Protestants</hi> acknowledge the Presbyterians are <hi>schismaticaly</hi> separated from the <hi>Church</hi> of <hi>England,</hi> as well as the Papists; and on the other side, in the <hi>sentiments</hi> of all Learned <hi>Divines,</hi> both antient and modern, <hi>Schism</hi> is so heinous a wickedness, that without repentance and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>union with the <hi>Church</hi> (unless perhaps invincible ignorance may lessen the crime) it wholly excludes the Party from <hi>eternal salvation,</hi> accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to the express words of our Saviour, <hi>If be neglect to hear the Church, let him be unto thee as an heathen man, and a Publican, Matth.</hi> 18.17. <hi>There cannot possibly</hi> (saith St. <hi>Irenaeus) be made any reformation of such importance, as the mischief of Schism is pernicious, lib.</hi> 4. <hi>c.</hi> 62. For (as <hi>Dionysius Alexandrinus</hi> testifieth) <hi>It is a more grievous wicked<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ness to divide the Church, than to sacrifice to Idols, ap. Euseb. lib</hi> 6 <hi>hist. c.</hi> 37. Which is yet further affirmed by the Prince of Divines, the great St. <hi>Augustine, The sacrilege of Schism</hi> (saith he) <hi>suprasseth all wickedness, lib.</hi> 1. <hi>contra ep. Parmen. c.</hi> 4. And lest we should not believe his own single testimony, this assertion he solidly confirms by the fearful pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nishment inflicted on <hi>Corah, Dathan,</hi> and <hi>Abiram,</hi> for their <hi>s<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>ismatical</hi> disobedience to <hi>M<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ses</hi> and <hi>Aaron. At what time</hi> (saith he) <hi>God would teach his People by new and fresh punishments to beware of their former transgressions, when an Idol was made and adored,</hi> (Exod. 32.) <hi>when the Prophets book was burnt by the hasty King,</hi> (Jer. 36.) <hi>and the schism was attempted</hi> (Numb. 16.) <hi>by</hi> Corah and his accomplices; <hi>the Idolatry was punished with the sword the burning of the book was revenged with wasting War and forreign Captivity; but the Schism was plagued with the sudden gaping of the earth, the Authors thereof having been sw<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>lowed up alive, and consum'd with fire from heaven. Who now</hi> (saith this great Logician) <hi>will doubt but that was most wickedly committed, which was most grievoufly punished? <gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap>. 2. de Bapt. cont. Donatist. c.</hi> 6.</p>
            <p>St. <hi>Cyprian</hi> goeth yet further, and of all <hi>schismatical</hi> Separatists, giv<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth this general sentence, <hi>Such people, though they were killed in the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fession of Christs name, yet that blemish even by blood is not washed away; the unpardonable and grievous crime of dissention is not purged even with death. He cannot be a Martyr that is not in the Church. He cannot at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain to the Kingdom, that forsakes her which is to reign. Such an one may be killed, but cannot be crown'd. The enemy of the Altar, rebellious against the Sacrifice of Christ,</hi> despising the Bishops, and forsaking the Priests of God, <hi>presumes to erect another Altar, and make other prayers by his un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lawful speeches. Lib. de Ʋnit. Eccles.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="15" facs="tcp:204734:38"/>
            <p>Neither are our <hi>Modern Divines</hi> less plain in this particular; and to begin with <hi>Calvin,</hi> the great God of the Presbyterians, he gives his verdict in these following words. <hi>We profess the unity of the Church (such as is described by St.</hi> Paul) <hi>to be most dear unto us; and we accurse them that shall any thing violate it;</hi> lib. de necess. Reform. Eccles. And again, <hi>The Lord doth so highly esteem the Communion of his Church, that he holds him for an Apostate, and deserter of Religion, who insolently separates himself from any Christian Society, so it be such a one as hath the true Ministry of the Word and Sacraments;</hi> lib. 4. Instit. c. 1. §. 10. Either therefore we have not the true Ministry of the Word and Sacraments in the Church of <hi>England,</hi> or else the Presbyterians are Schismaticks, nay Apostates and deserters of Religion, even in the Judgment of their own Patriarch <hi>Calvin.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Luther</hi> likewise in his explication upon the <hi>Creed,</hi> speaks to the same purpose: <hi>Neither</hi> Gentile, <hi>nor</hi> Jew, (saith he) <hi>Heretick, or any other sinner, is saved, unless he make Atonement with the Church, and in all things think, do, and teach the same.</hi> As for our own <hi>Divines,</hi> they are in this point both plain and positive: <hi>It is false</hi> (saith our Learned <hi>Whitaker) that Heretical and Schismatical Churches, are true Churches.</hi> controv. 2. q. 5. c. 9. And again: <hi>Whereas he proves, that Hereticks, Apostates, and Shismaticks are not Members of the true Church, it is no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing to us; for this none of us ever affirmed.</hi> controv. 2. q. 1. c. 4.</p>
            <p>And Dr. <hi>Fulk</hi> in his Treatise of the Succession of the <hi>Church,</hi> p. 390. saith: <hi>What skilleth it, whether one being drawn by Heresie or Schism from the Body of Christ, be subject to Eternal Damnation?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Mr. <hi>Casaubone</hi> also in his Letter to Cardinal <hi>Peron,</hi> written by the appointment of King <hi>James,</hi> page 8. thus saith: <hi>The King doth con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demn and detest those, who departed either from the faith of the Catholick Church, and became Hereticks; or from her Communion, and became Schis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maticks.</hi> And the same is taught by Dr. <hi>Humphrey,</hi> ad rat. 3. Cam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piani. p. 207. by <hi>Field,</hi> lib. 1. de Eccles. c. 7. Confess. Helvet. art. 17. Bulling. in compend, fidei. lib. 6. c. 11. Musculus in Locis, tit. de Schismate, p. 621. and many others.</p>
            <p>Is it not evident therefore by the unanimous consent of so many <hi>Protestant Divines,</hi> so exactly concurring with the general vote of the An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cient Writers, and Gods express word, that Schism is so capital a crime, that it cuts off the party from the <hi>Church</hi> of <hi>God,</hi> and thereby from all ordinary means of obtaining eternal Salvetion? And is it not likewise certain, that Protestants and Presbyterians (notwithstanding your ridiculous cementing of them together) do mutually censure and charge each other with <hi>Schism,</hi> if not with impious and <hi>Heretical</hi>
               <pb n="16" facs="tcp:204734:39"/>Doctrines. None I think, can be so ignorant, as not to know what a Cloud of Writers have given their verdict on both sides in this particular. To the end therefore you may not hereafter exclaim a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainst me, or alledge that I make it my business to breed dissention and division between <hi>Protestants,</hi> by calling the Presbyterians <hi>Schismatical Sectaries,</hi> (tho' indeed it is my design to seperate the <hi>Wheat</hi> from the <hi>Tares,</hi> true <hi>Protestants</hi> from counterfeit <hi>Religionaries,</hi> and warn them not to trust again such <hi>Hypocritical</hi> Dissemblers) and that you may be convinc'd, this is no particular opinion of mine, but the general tenet of our Learned <hi>Divines;</hi> hear some of them speak their own minds at a time, when Presbytery was not near so monstrous in it self, nor yet half so dangerous or formidable to our <hi>Church,</hi> as it is at pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sent. <hi>The Puritans</hi> (saith Dr. <hi>Bancroft, Archbishop</hi> of <hi>Canterbury) do pervert the true meaning both of Scripture and Fathers, to serve their own turns.</hi> In his Survey of the pretended Holy Discipline, c. 5. <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And Mr. <hi>Parkes,</hi> in his book dedicated to the <hi>Archbishop,</hi> in his <hi>Epistle Dedicatory,</hi> thus saith of your holy Brethren: <hi>They are head<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>strong, and hardened in error; they strike at the main points of faith, and shaking the foundation it self, and calling into question Heaven and Hell, the Divinity and Humanity, yea the very Soul and Salvation of our Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viour himself.</hi> And again, ibid. <hi>The Puritans have Pestilent Heresies, they are Heretical and Sacrilegious.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Mr. <hi>Powel</hi> likewise, in his Considerations, saith of them: <hi>They are notorious and manifest Schismaticks, cut off from the Church of God.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And this is further confirmed by Mr. <hi>Casaubons</hi> excellent Rule, (taken out of S. <hi>Cyprian</hi>'s 69. Ep.) in Exercit. 15. contra Baron. nu. 6. Where he saith: <hi>It is an undoubted verity, that whensoever the pious People adheres to their true and lawfull Bishop, they are Gods Church; insomuch that whosoever seperates himself from this Congregation, it cannot be doubted, but that he is not in the Church.</hi> Presbyterians therefore are not in the <hi>Church</hi> of God, who have <hi>Schismatically</hi> se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perated themselves from the pious and orthodox Protestants adhering to their true and lawful <hi>Bishops.</hi> To be brief, the <hi>Bishop</hi> of <hi>Chichester</hi> gives us a full and short description of these Holy and Sanctified Bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>theren: I <hi>must confess</hi> (saith he) <hi>my dissent through and sincere from the faction of Novelizing Puritans; men intractible, insociable, incompliable with those that will not</hi> aedificare ad dissensiones; <hi>but in no one point more, than in their desperate doctrine of Predestination;</hi> in his Appeal to <hi>Caesar,</hi> page 60. And again p. 320. he speaks to the Presbyterians themselves in this manner: <hi>I go no farther, but leave you to your selves, and (if pos<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sible)
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:204734:39"/>unto more charitable conceits of those that deserve no other imputation, but, they are no Puritans: Which God of his Goodness keep out of this Church and State, as dangerous as Popery, for any thing I am able to dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cern: The only difference being, Popery is for Tyranny, Puritanism for Anarchy; Popery is original of Superstition, Puritanism the Highway unto Prophaneness; both alike Enemies to Piety.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But lest you should think this learned Prelate any thing transpor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted with prejudice or partiality in this his censure of your Sanctified Brethren, hear what your own Patriarch and first founder speaketh of those, who had the first Fruits of his Spirit, his holy Proselytes at <hi>Geneva: It is certain</hi> (saith he) <hi>that a man shall not see so horrible monsters in the Papacy, as where the Gospel is Preach'd and Profess'd; for they will say they are reformed, and yet they seem to be Devils incarnate, neither have we need to go far off to find such sights.</hi> Calvin serm. 10. in ep. ad Ephes.</p>
            <p>Now the Presbyterians on the other side are nothing behind in slan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dering and charging the Church of <hi>England</hi> with all imaginable cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruption; <hi>Schism,</hi> they think, is too small a crime to be alledg'd against her, whilst Popish <hi>Superstition</hi> and the dregs of <hi>Antichrist</hi> do compose the chiefest part of her Liturgy, Doctrine and Government. <hi>The form of the Communion-Book</hi> (say they) <hi>is taken from the Church of Antichrist; as the reading of the Epistles, and Gospels,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>the most of the Prayers, the manner of administring the Sacraments,</hi> &amp;c. in Dr. <hi>Whitgifts</hi> defence, p. 474. And in their Book intituled, The Petition of 22. Preachers in <hi>London,</hi> they say: <hi>In the Communion-Book there be things of which there is no sense, there is contradiction in it, even of necessary and essential points of Religion.</hi> And also in their Book of Cannons and Constitutions Ecclesiastical, printed <hi>Anno</hi> 1604. they say: <hi>The worship in the Church of</hi> England <hi>is corrupt, superstitious, un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lawfull and repugnant to the Scriptures.</hi> Likewise the great Presbyte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rian <hi>Alexander Henderson,</hi> in his first <hi>Paper</hi> to our <hi>Royal Martyr,</hi> in the Book intituled <hi>Reliquiae Carolinae,</hi> part 1. p. 314. thus speaketh: <hi>It is too well known that the Reformation of K.</hi> Henry 8. <hi>was most imperfect in the essentials of Doctrine, Worship and Government: And though it proceeded by some degrees afterwards, yet the Government was never reformed, the head was changed,</hi> Dominus non Dominium, <hi>and the whole limbs of the Antichristian Hierarchy retained. And for this cause</hi> (as our late <hi>Sove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raign</hi> well observes) <hi>their zealous Superstition thinks or pretends, they cannot do God and the Church a greater service, than utterly to destroy that Primitive, Apostolical, and anciently universal Government of the Church by Bishops;</hi> in his Eikon Basilike, c. 9. But to conclude, and if <hi>Sy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>metry</hi>
               <gap reason="missing" extent="1+ pages">
                  <desc>〈1+ pages missing〉</desc>
               </gap>
            </p>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>